<topics>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-new-york-city-subway/selected-articles</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1903-11-01/ed-1/?sp=33&q=Subway&st=text&r=0.662,0.314,0.48,0.347,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>SOME INCIDENTS OF SUBWAY CONSTRUCTION.
Tumbling Into the ''Open Ditch" Dog* Marfr Crazy bjf llv plosions—
The Victims of "Sulncay Knee" Nmrom Escapes of Horses.
As far back as history or kgraf go-»s. man
has always beea anxious to know how it feels
to die, without dying. Men have permitted
themselves to be "partially killi'd." for the pur
pose of Aescfihtag the sensation.-? which th^y
experienced. They have tilled th-ir lungs with
water. They have eaten of the llradlj poppjr.
They have grasped the stinging electrode. And.
last of all. they have tumbled into the subway.
However the Bterchaats of this city may op
pose an "open dit. h." there are many philo
sophical citizens who regard it as a blessing.
Here they are able with ease to make the
plunge into the unknown themselves, or be
A IIOIISE THAT SIvIPPED INTO THE SUBWAY.
His harness and the wagon alone prevented him from falling to the bottom, but the harness clicked
him to dealh before he could be rescued. A trolley car pushed him over the brink.
content to watch others Jo it. HVre they may
watch various mental phenomena, whkh are of
the greatest value to psychology, and obtain
data, for example, as to why an absent minded
man fali-s into the subway head tirst. whereas t
frightened woman simi>ly jumps in.
According to the records of the BapM Transit
Commission, there have been just nineteen men
aril women who have tumbled into the subway
since it was begun. There have also been
thirty-two horses \vhi> h have either made a
complete dt scent to the subway's bottom or
partially made the leap. Numberless cats have
tumbled into the great tr.-nc h, and several dogs
have been made crazy by the bl.usting. In addi
tion to the.se unfortunates, many H trkmites
living in bOMK-ave assert that at one time
they contracted the "subway knee," and that
M of the Creqoent explosions of dynamite
beneath their honic-s their legs had a tendency
to double up.
Although explosions and cave-Ins have some
times LlUWll •.•ath, DeTerthetoM there has been
a humorous H well as a pathetic side to the
subway work. Ike average New-Yorker, who
h.is bc-?n c: isaMed by Kuropean anthropologtsta
as the "Homo patiens," and who accoßUno
hin.^-:f to new situations so quickly that
the "out-of-towner" calls him blase, has also
come to regard the subway In hie more com
placent Btooda a? a J<>y forever (if not a
thin* of beauty). Should he be aboard a sur
torest by the nay. When we left them at Lon
lon I expressed my thanks, adding that I was
agreeably rarprised to find them so open and
pleasant, in rlew of their traditional stand-off-
Lshness.
\V"ll, I h !\<-irt ceased laaghing jrH at his
reply. ''Mi.' exclaimed he, *we don't mind in the
least talking to Americans. There's little chance
of our seeing then again, you know.'"
face ear aftor making fortune that day in a
rise of Yeast com num. and the car stops with
a sudden jolt, he will most likely say:
"Another wagoa knocked into the subway."
Should he he ensconced In his own ar:n chair,
with hi wife resting h.-r head upon his shoul
der, and ihe chillren playing about his feet, and
he should be thrown halfway to the ceiling by a
sort of seismic sho> k, he would gather his fam
ily about him again and say:
"The house has slid into the subway."
Or at the club, if he is discussing the purity
of politics with an Independent Democrat, and
a rock should break into the room and his con
versation, he might quietly remark:
"Merely a high ball from the subway."
On a Sunday, should this patient citizen at
tend charcfa In upper Broadway, and the
preacher should contrast the evil life with the
good life, and should admonish his audience to
chooae wisely in view of the consequences, and
should go BO tar a.s to speak of the bottomless
pit, there would be more than one mind In that
church which would involuntarily think:
"He meani the subway."
Of .til the accidents that have come to the
notice of the Rapid Transit Subway Construc
tion Company there were none which evoked
lea sadness than the ezpiosfoa which was al
leged to hive driven a ball dozen dogs crazy.
According to one story, the firing of a blast on
Broadway, betw« n Long Acre Square and the
cir l-\ shook up a woman's bird and animal
store with such terrific violence that after she
bad ta< rsett recovered from the shock she found
one of the parrots, which had been a resident of
i rh* ago, laying:
'T.ace t.; thee!"
Some Belgian hares w^r? so stunned that they
died, and the fear crossed the woman's mind
that if these had been the only Belgian hares In
existence the species would have become ex
tinct. But the maddest of an who lived in the
block, po sh^ said, were a half doz<>n dogs. They
kept digging as if to di« sUbwaj of their own.
and in oth«r ways showed s!gns of mental at ■■r
nition. The woman brought suit against the
contractor for $50,000.
In spite of all the erudition of physicians and
Burgeons, there was nothing known of the "sub
way knee" until the winter of 1901. At that
time some of the residents of I^-nox-ave. com
plained of a flexibility of the knee, which at
times was disconcerting, if not dangerous. No
matter what one's ideas on religious matters
might be, he was likely at any time to get down
on his knees as if in prayer. hould he per
chance n.eet his debtor and see his opportunity
of getting that $5,000 which he had long ago
given up as lost, he might suddenly find the
situation reversed, and himself instead of hi*
debtor in an imploring attitude.
The majority of those suffering from the "sub
way knee" traced its origin to the frequent
blasts in the subway In front of their homes.
They said that the violent vibrations had loos
ened their joints, and although they might have
posed for more pious persons than they really
were, nevertheless they preferred stiffer legs.
They said they would even prefer a "house
maid's knee" to a "subway knee" if they could
only get it without being housemaids.
At one time in Park How there was hardly a
day that some horse did not put his foot
through the planking of the wooden roof, or a
wagon wheel did not sink in a crack, or both
horse and wagon fall clear to the bottom of the
trench. On May 8 of this year 'here were two
such accidents within a few hours of each
other, and within a few feet of the same
place. Near the bridge entrance a wagon broke
through the subway roof, but the driver by
leaping, was able to save the animals from fall
ing through. Two hours before that 4. coal
wagon had disappeared over the side of the
subway in front of the Potter Building, and
had been finally rescued by means of a hoisting
engine and tackle. According to the contractor
for the City Hall section of the subway, there
have been eleven horses hauled out of the
trench since it was first begun.
One might think that a horse would be sure
of serious injury from such a tumble. Yet some
have had what seemed to be hairbreadth ex
periences and escaped with only a few scratches^
A trolley car once bunteJ a team of horses at
tached to an express wagon into .he subway in
Fourth-aye. between Eleventh and Twelfth sts.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85038615/1904-10-09/ed-1/?sp=27&q=New+subway+Subway+York&st=text&r=-0.006,0.847,0.731,0.529,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>WORLD'S GREATEST EFFORT TO SOLVE CITY TRANSPORTATION PROBLEM
Tlie New York Subway tlie
Greatest Thing of Its Kind
Ever Undertaken.
NO OTHER COMPARES WITH IT
?\Vhat lt Is Expectcd to Do in
Solving tlie Most Difiictilt City
Transportation Problcm.
By Bassett Staincs.
ll?pNEW lollK, Oct. S.?There are grealor
fiiglnnorliig work's going on In tho world
to-day, For cxample,, l.lm constructlon
of the A.isouun dnm and the other lrrlga
?'.lldrj w-orks on lho Nilo, whlch, a? thclr
erentor, iHIr Wllllam Gnt-stln, prottdly
hiitisir, wlll llve ln tho uso and obser
vntlon of umiiklnd long nfter ihe an
cletit inoniiment.i of tho Egyptlans hava
illsappoared beiieath Ihe Biinds of the
Nublan deserl. But of Its klnd lho New
Toik siihwny Is the grentcst thlng yet
done, and It is o.Iso the greatest en
ghioerlng entcrprlse of any klnd ln tlie
1 "1111011 States to-day.
It wlll be opened Ihroughoul nrnily
the whole of Its length In the course of
Ihe preKi-nt ninnth, If slrlkes do not fur?
ther delay Ihe completlon of tlie work.
31 Is prnctlf-ally ilnlshed from the resl
'lgri-at. buslness soctlon Around City Hall,
foinn work ls stlll going on farther down*
town townrds the Battery, and nlso nt
the northern extremlty of Mmiliattiin
nnd on the Iiiooklyn oxleilslon,
Will Exceed All Others.
Time was when the Gothard and Mont
?'cnls. tunnelH wero held to bo conslder
nlile iioles In the earth. They nre merc
rabblt burrows In comparlson wlth the
Vitst sliaft whlch has been drlven long
glttidlnally through the Inland ot Man
hnttan.
Or take, Instead, the greatest oxcava
tlons made by vanlshed civlllznilons.
?Great as ure tlie ca%*es of Elephanta and
llie tomples of ICarnak nnd of Ahooslm
1'rd on the Nllo bank, the floor space. of
tlie statlomtof tho New York subway.
t.-iken togother, ls greater than that of
any two of them, and when the Jirook
lyn nnd under-the-r-ver tunnels to be
made are completed, such ttatlonal areas
wlll oxcecd in comblncd space nll the
rock-lu'wn templcs of the anclent world
Itoown to archaeology."
Thls Is the statement. of an cngineer
conhected with the work who happens to
be glfted wlth a poetlc imaglnatlon. But
none tho less hc possesses that preclslon
of dctall whlch properly belongs to hls
jji-ofcEslon, for he -has computed that
the carth whlch has been, or wlll be,
excavatcd In the making of the subway
iimounts to exactly .1.700.2SS cublc yardsf.
Tho rock lunneled ainuunts to half a
sullllon yards; the rock excavalc-d, to
more than double that quantliy.
Some Striking Figures.
Here nre some other figures whlch
Kpeak for thcmncivea us to the nioighl
fii'dii of the work:
Stee! usc-d ln the structurc, 75,000 tons;
cost iron, a mere trifle ot' 10,000 tons;
c-oncrete, far over 500.000 cublc yards;
water proollng, more than 700.000 cublc
yards; brlck. 20,000 cublc yards; vauit
ifglit-, over 7,000, each shedding Its
beams for a radlus of many yards;
total length of track apprbac-.hes, aiout
oto.Wi) feet. Theso figures do not ln
clude the great Brooklyn extcnsi^i by
way of the Battery tunnel, which ls al
ready under way: or- other >chemcs for
ihe exlenslon of the subway sorvlce,
tlthcrlmooted or ln actlve procoss of ex
ccutlon.
The Ptolcmles and tho thlrd Rameses
bullded monum?nts In their day, but
they did nothlng so vast as thls.
"f'n the days of the Caesars," sald u
New 'York englneer. "Pliny tells us It
took thlrty thousand men eleven weary
years to cut a tunnel three and a half
inlles long. To-day, employlng less than
twelve thousand men, the New York
masters of enginecrlng mechanlcs have
made a tunnel eqiial ln capaclty to one
of over flfty mllcs ln length llke that
of Rome, to. say nothlng of some ten
mllcs of elevated structurc ajid the ex
cavatlon of extra areas for nndergvound
s'tatlbns."
True, there are olher underground roads
In the. world; but, compared wlth thom,
thls one ls as "all Lombard-street to a
Chlna' oran'ge." Tho famous "twoperiny
tube" In Lopdon, for oxumple, about
oovers the dlstanco from the Battery to
Forty-sccond street, where the real
journey to tho end of the. llno is hnrdly
bcglnning.
Its Appalling Dimensions.
lt has been carefully est'imnted by en
plneers that lf the subway were a Blngle
tunnel slx feet hlgh ahd threo feet wide,
lt would reach from New York to Chl?
cago. The part exeavated through tho
tiolld rock would reach from the metropo
lis to Cleveland. "Three mllllon-cublc
yards of hole"?that is how one man
conneoted wlth the work summed lt up.
Wlille the excavatlons aro going on.
mllllons of ftet oflumbcr are, belng used
to prop up the streets so'that tue ordl
nary trafllc-can go on. All the englneers
engaged ln the. cnLerprlse are impressed
bv Its magnltude. and cannot help stop
ping now and then to Indulge in the
welroV.st klnd One of them' says that this tlmber ?n
ployed in the "falso work" would bulld
no fower than ten thousand two-story
framo houscs: whlle another asserts that
the rock talten out by the tunnel would
niako a respc-ctablc imltatlon ot the
Great Wall of Chlna, naniely, a struc
ture threo feet thick, slx feet hlgh, and
about flve hundred mlles long.
There -ls no. doubt a.bout lt?the New
York subway ls the greatest thlng of
Its kind 'that manklnd has yet done.
Was a Big Job.
Tho city of New York declded to have
tho subway constructed by contract and
leased to the contractdr for-flfty yearn
for nn annual rental of rather more than
the interest payable by tho city on the
bonds Issued to provide means for tho
constructlon. It is -hardly credlble, but
lt ls the fact that ot all the great con
tracting englneers ln the world only two
could be found to put ln blds for suoh a
vast. work. They were .lohu B. McDon
ald ahd Andrew Onderdonk.
McDomald askied for $35,000,000 In a
round sum. That was about the tigure
e-tlmated by tf>o cnglneer of tho Rapid
Transit Commisslon, "Wllliam Barclay
Paraona. Onderdpnk wanted JS9.300.W1
and certaln concesslons. lloDonald got
the job. and has carried lt outln a
manner that has met wlth the' enthu
slostic approval .of' many dlstingulshed
englncers who have Inspected hls w,ork.
"Rapld transit"?the elusivc dream Of
Xew Yorkers for so many years?wiil
be something more than a mere phrase
when tho subway ls runnlng full-blast.
It Is provlded by contract that local
tralns must run at an average-speed ot
not less than fourteen mlles ,an hour.
Including statlon stops;. whlle. expresses
must make thlrty mlles an hour. This
will easlly brlng people from Klngs
bridgc. at the northern polnt of Mnn
hnttan. down to the Clty Hali.In ..flfteen
minutes. Vlsltors from "out of town'-'
will no longer bc able to say. as; they
n.lways .do say howadays, "Come to
our clty and wc'll teach you how to
travel."
Close to the Surface.
IJnllko most underground roads, the
New York subway runs close to thesur
fnce. Throughout most 'of-tho length
fi-om the Battery to Harlem, lt ls only
four or flve feet below the street levelj
This makes tho excavation about twenty
feet ln depth. and the 'platforms of the
statlons are wlthin slxteen and elghteen
f.-et of the surface. The steps down from
the street to' the statlon are thus fewer
in number, as a rule, than those. up to
the present elevated statlons. Tho
problem of ventllatlon?always a- dltH
cult ono Jn underground Tallroads?ls
mucli slmptlfled by this nearncss to the
street, and- the fotil. atmosphere that
chokes the1 passongers.ln.JJohd'on's "two
penhy tub*-" need not be.feoreid.
The largesfstatioii on .the subway ls
the' Brooklyn -33ridge statlon. whlch. ls,
really the down town tcrminal. Its net-!
work of tracks rlvale the avera'ge ter?
minal In a falrly large city, iund a few
fest above lt rolls Interminably the
-hcavlest street tr'allic bf tho-!clty. in?
cludlng.many ele'ctric tar lines.. Stcal
beams, flve feet thlck, ho.ld. up tho lri
mense'weight of thls traflic.
From thls .fitation. at the .Brooklyn
Brldge' clear up to Thlrty^thlrd street
the hub of the linlverse-t'o. many New
Yorkers?.the subway oonsists of a four
track llne runnlng ln..- a slrigle tunriel.
Two tracks aro for expresses. and two
for' locals. It ls arranged that exprejs
tralns wlll run.-on expre'ss. tracks only,
and Iocal tralns on local tracks?an ex
celleht system; whlch dqes not now pre
vair on tho elevated rallways of Now
York city.
Have Double Tracks.
The road conslsts of. two doublo-track
tunn.els above Thirty-fourth streot, whlch
pass.on elther slde ot the.exlstlng,Park
avenue street rallway tunnel, but at a
tower.level. ManHattan,1s, lndeed.be
comlng honeycombed- ln' all' dlrectlons,
and the end of the tunn'elllng ls not yet
ln slght. New .Yorkers- ara llvlng ln
thlrty storles and; travolllng in three?
In tunhels, street /cars,' and elevated
tralns.
The subway follows Broadwny lo' One
Hundred and Fourth' street and there
dlvides into two llnes?ono on the East i
Slde and the: other on ;the West Slde.
At' two polnts before reaohlng One Hun?
dred and Fourth street .tho tunnel has
to'pass.urider tlie elevated rallway... and
the task'of holdlng'up the great-welght
of that gtructurc.;.whlle the tunnelllng
was golng on r was one. of the most'dirti
cult that-: the'-. ongineers had to face.
Downtown. they.dlved under"a Park.row
newspaper, offlce with such- a small jnnr
gln to sparo'that th'o erids of the presses
actually.projected over the tunnel, and
yet Were abl.e to keep.-runnlng 'wlthout
aiv hbu'r'a ioss of'-tlme. Another. tlck
llnh problem 'was to runMinderrieathi the
vaults of th'o New York postofflcc wlth
?Dut disturblng tho work golng on thero.
But lt' is not only tho underground
work of whlch tlio siibwoy englneers
have good' reason to be' proud. From
Ono Hundred andFoiirth'to One Hun?
dred and Sfxtee'nth. s't'roets ttiey havo
carried the llno on a- slngle "solld -con
crete arch ln an open cut, wlth a span
of forty-'two'. feet. This Is. technlcally
regarded as orie of th'o best pleces of
work of its charactcr everdone. At tho
end of this out comes the long, deep
dip known as-Manhattan Valjey; whlch
ls crossed'on an Imrnense elevated-steel
vladuct In -order to m'alntain the,' giVdo
of the llrie. From-Ono'Hundred and
Flfty-flfth street to Ono Hundrfcd and
Nlnetletli street tho' tunnel had to be
bored entirely through solld rock, and
this part of tho'work alono ls sald to be
the longest double-track railroad tunnel
ln tho' Unlted States.
Thousands at Work,
On an average the nrmy of subway
laborers has conslstod of about ten thous?
and inen durlng the. past four years,. and
the cost of cxcavatlng .toolc lip about
ono-thlrd of the entlre contract prlce of
$iS,Cup the gi-en.t part of the tlme. If it had
beeii drllled by band, the engfueers doubt
whether liio work could liavo boen dono
In a rtuartor of a centnry. Thero has
beon no such dlfflculty' In any prevtous
work of the kind. Tho Hiibways of J./011
doii and Pnrls Were cui. through clay.
and that of Boston through earth.
Many unexpected dtttleu+fles were met
with ln'the cptirso of tlie work. Ouc was
the Intorferejice, wlth' the dralnagc of
the clty?ninnlng suddenly up agnlnirt a
network ot sowers whlch scemed to el-;
Tectu'ally bl'ock the path. These wer*
problonis sufflcleiit to turn nn englneer's
hair gray. In one place, merely;as a
llttle alde lssuo of their business, tbe
makers' of the subway hud to change
tho system of drainago of a largo dis?
trlct, maklng tho sew.ers dral'n Into tho
East rlver Inctead of tho Harlem rlvor.
At another place they had to tear up
a network of street. car tr.u-ks and relay
them.
Tho subway will not bo a dark', mis
erablo. stuffy place, llke the London
Underground Railwny. It Is clenh and
whlto (throu_4hout, nnd wo -Ihorouglily
llghted by clcctriolty that It Is os .brlght
as' day everywherc. Tho statlons aro,
ln many cases, real works of art, and
all of'them aro con'vonlenl and coiiifort
able.
Tho glgnnllo. pow'er-liouso on Flfty
elghth and Flfty-nlnth streets, whlch
Plans Already Underway to Ex
tcnd tllc Underground Transit
in Manhattan and Brooklyn.
PROBLEM FOR ENGINEERS
Many of These Had to bc Dcalt
With in the Grcat Work?-The
Tracks and Stations.
vltall-/.ei tlie thlrd rall, ls a slnictur.
ot whlch tho tno.kcrs of the subway afo
Justlv protifk It has a frontoge of 300
feot' on Blfiventlt avenue and extends
wstward for nearly *0J feet, whlle tho
helght Is 12.1 feet. lt Is thifs one of tho
largcst buildlngs In Now York, und. ono
of tho Inrgest' power hous^s ln tho
world. The welght of the steel frame
work alono ls about. .12.000 tons. Tho to?
tal genernllng capaclty of the plant l?
about 130,000 horsc power. The thlrd
rh.ll system of elcctrlcal propulsion i 1*
to bo usod throughout.
Now Practically Complete.
The su'oway Is now practically eom
pieted throughout the entlre length of
Mnnhnttan.. It ls a great wOrk grcatl.v
done, .but It mu.it not be supposed that
lt has solved the vexed nuestlon of
trnnsportatlon ln the motropolls. En?
glneers and trairte. mann.gers fnmillnr
wlth enndltlons ln New York ibelleve that
it wlll bo at best merel.v a temporary and
partial relief to th* present unbcarablo
congcstlon of traflle. Thero wlll stlll, lu
all probablllty, ibe a jvast army ot
"strnp-hangr.rs"?on the subway Itseir,
as well as on tho elevated' and sur
fnce llnes. Other subways wlll havo to
.be bullt, nnd plans for them arn already
belng tcntatlvely prepared and consid
ered.
The Brooklyn .'oxtenslon iruns under
the East rtver' to Joralemon street,
Brooklyn. The Rapid Transit Commls
sion has already authorlzed an exten
skm of thls 'Brooklyn road to Prospecu
Park, and South Brooklyn has also be
gun to clamor for a branch and ls
ilkely to get It.
Tn many parts of Gr-eater New York
the publlc ls agltatlng for an extcn
slon of the orijrinal scheme of tho sub?
way). ;Tho iRrooklyn gxiterinlon i^ider
the Eant rlver. was not a part of that
origlnol scheme. wlilch ,\va8 doslgned
only to rellevo tho congestlon ot traflle
in Manhattan and the Brohx.
Other Work Under Ground.
The rallroad companios, especially ,the
Pennsylvania, nre also doing much tun
nelling lu Now York at the present tlmo,
and aro connccting. thoir systems with
tho subway. The Rapld Transit Board
has grautcd to lho Pennsylvania* ...ew;
Jersey and New York Rallroad Com?
pany and to tho Pennsylvania, New York
and Long lsland iRailroad Company.
jointly, frunchlses for a tunnel system;'
passing from VVeehawken, N. .T., acrbss
tho North rlver, rlght iinder Manhattan
lsland (along Thlrty-second and Thlrty
tlilrd streets),-aud thenco Into tho Bor
ough of'Queehs. There ls to be. a doublo
tunnel under the North rlver. Thls Penn?
sylvania extenslon will cost anout $?0,
000,000, and wlll be provldcd wlth what
has been descrlbed nt. "the most mas
sive rallroad depot yet concelved of."'
Four ftill-slzed city blocks have been
torn down to make way for it, and from
thls statlon threo tunnels wlll extend
under tho .East rlver Into ...e Horough
of Queens. Tho Pennsylvania wil. h??s.
havo direct communicatlon, .wlthout the
rilct of flodls, not only with Manhal-.
tun, but wlth the cxtromlties of Long
lsland. Tho, big statlon in the center
of Manhattan ls tb bo connccted wl/.h
the subway and the Grand Contval sta?
tlon.
Needs Not Yet Met.
They aro dolng great things ln New
York city to-day to brli'ig Father ICniri>
erbocker's chlldren down to work wlth?
out packhig thom llke herrlngs ln /a
barrel. .But, though tho dollars aro be
irig pourod out by the mlltlon every
month for the lmprovement of trahspor
tation' fa'cllltles, tho provlslon ls stlll
inadequate. to the need, and ls Ilkely to
remaln so for. many years to come.
Jt .ls Imposslblo to glve any exact fig?
ures on thls polnt of the relation of tha
provlslon to tho need. Even the dally
carrylng capaclty of the subway cannot
bc detormlned by ostlmate. Th? offlclnls
ln charge of tho enterprlse wlll each
glve you a dlfforent guess, all of whlch
aro away up Into the mllllons. Tho
vaflatlon ln these estlmatos ls explatn
ed by' the fact that some of them' are
based on tho seatlng capaclty of tho
cars whlch wlll be run, whlle others
aro foimdod on the demonstrated carry?
lng capaclty of tho elevated aud surraco
cars, with half their passeogers hanglns
on to straps in tho "rush hours."
(Copyrlght, 1W4, .by Bassett Stalnes.)</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030193/1911-05-25/ed-1/?sp=20&q=Subway&st=text&r=-0.139,-0.064,1.278,1.278,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>The Interboroug'h Offer Completes the City-Owned Subway. The Brooklyn Rapid Transit
Company Asks the City to Build Subways as Terminals for Its Elevated Railroads.
The Brooklyn Rapid Transit Company Proposes More Elevated
Roads for Brooklyn. The Interborough Builds Subways There.
WHAT THE INTERBOROUGH PLAN DOES FOR BROOKL YN
y TERBOROUGH.
20
EXISTING SUBWAYS
PROPOSED SU8WAYS,IM MEDIATE C Off STRUCT ON,
INTERBOROUGH AND CITY MONEY.
ocxxxxxxEUWRE EXTENSIONS TO SUBWAY SYSTEM.
wmmm SUBWAYS under constnuctoy.
ALL TO BE OPERATED BY iTERBOROUGH
FOR A SINGLE S CEiT
If V--. X A
m m (CV 4 11 S J x U
The Brooklyn Rapid Transit Company Offers to Reduce Fares to Manhattan at the City's
Expense, But Refuses to Reduce Fares to Coney Island at that Company's Expense.
This map shows what the Interborough Company has offered to
the City as a comprehensive subway plan. The lines shown in heay
broken lines can be immediately constructed and placed in opera
tion for a single five-cent subway fare in connection with the present
subway, the bridge Loop, and the Fourth Avenue Subway. The total
construction cost will be $198,788,650, of which the City pays
$110,320,150 for construction and the Interborough $88,478,500. The
Interborough supplies all of the equipment, which makes a total
contribution by the Interborough of $140, 824, SCO. The City's expen
diture under this plan is $58,000,000, leas than called for by the
Brooklyn Rapid Transit Company's plan.
The Interborough's plan establishes a universal five-cent subway
fare from Fort Hamilton, Coney Island. Shetpihead Bay, East New
York. Ridgewood, Wocdside, Coona, Astoria and all parts of the
Bronx. The Brooklyn Rapid Transit Company's plan establishes a
ten-cent fare within the Greater City ard for a great many of the
people in Queens, Manhattan and the Bronx a fii teen-cent fare to
Coney Island. The Brooklyn Company claims that it will make a
great saving to Brooklyn people by extending its lines into Manhat
tan, thus avoiding a double fare.
The Interborough Company, by going to Brooklyn for the
people with its numerous lines with a single fare, save more then
the Brooklyn Company claims to save, because on the Interborough
there will be a single fare to reach from every point in Brooklyn to
every point in Greater New York.
If the Brooklyn Rapid Transit Company is so interested in re
ducing the expenditures of the fare-payer, why do they insist in
A their proposition that for a short ride from Brooklyn to Coney
'""'md the lare must be ten cents
The Interborough has adopted the principle that a single five
cent fare paid on the subway system shall carry a person from one
end to the other of the Greater City of New York. On the other
hand, the Brooklyn Rapid Transit Company's plan proposes to
perpetuate a two-and three-fare system.
The Brooklyn Rapid Transit Company's proposal is that it will
spend less than $21,000,000 for construction in improving its eleva
ted lines in Brooklyn and placing third tracks thereon if the Greater
City of New York will pay about $168,000,000 of the taxpayers' money
for subway construction and connect it with the out-of-date eleva
ted lines in Brooklyn, provided further that all the receipts on the
Subways built by the taxpayers' money shall be used by the Brooklyn
Rapid Transit Company in establishing for all time a dividend on
many of the unprofitable elevated lines in Boooklyn.
The Interborough's plan proposes to extend the present City
Subway so that all the people in Brooklyn, including the outlying
districts, will be given a five-cent subway fare from one end to the
other ofthe Greater City of New York. If the Interborough's plan is
adopted by the City it will save $58,000,000 of the taxpayers' money
that the Brooklyn Rapid Transit Company's plan calls for, and this
$58,0C0,000, will construct the lines shown on this map to Rich
mend, to Jamaica and to Flushing, and if these lines are construc
ted there would still be $30,000,000 of the taxpayers' money saved by
accepting the Interborough's plan.
The Brooklyn Rapid Transit Co. advertises that it will take only
$73,500,000 of City money to construct the rapid transit lines which
it has been showing in heavy black lines on its advertising maps.
The misleading character of this talk about cost can be seen read
ily by lookinar at its offer of April 25th. in which it was stated that
the City's requirement of new capital would be $73,500,000 for the
lines then proposed.
Since that date and on May 1st the Brooklyn Company added
to its so-called original lines:
1. The Jerome Avenue extension to Jerome Park Reservoir.
2. The Southern Boulevard extension to the Bronx River.
3. Lines to Astoria and Corona.
4. The Nostrand Avenue extension.
5. The Livonia Avenue extension; and
6. The Fourteenth Street Tunnel to East New York.
But not a word has been said about the additional cost of these
lines. Every day since they were added the Brooklyn Company has
stuck to its original figure of $73,500,000. More than this, and still
further showing the deceptiveness of their advertisements, the
Brooklyn Company are placing upon their advertising maps in black
lines the following lines which they have riot even yet agreed to put
in their offer:
a i The Southern Boulevard line extending as far as Pelham
Bay Park.
(b) The Utica Avenue extension; and
(c) The Tunnel to Staten Island.
And still they seek to lead the public to believe that all the black
lines will cost the city only $73,500,000.
Now the facts are that the cost to the city of the lines first
mentioned by them will be $118,000,000.
The cost to the city, with their additions of May 1st, will run
up to $168,000,000.
The grand total cost to the city of their layout as advertised
will run up to $188,500,000.
rMfcall.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045487/1915-09-25/ed-1/?sp=31&q=New+York+Subway&st=text&r=-0.309,0.152,1.618,1.618,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>NEW YORK SUBWAY CAVE-IK
J i i irTMn Ssammnim 1 1 BJ
i.imuil nil I JJ f
frrngaww 7y
This shows the cave-in of the Seventh ave. subway at New York, in
which seven people were killed arid more than 100 injured. The cave-in1
cfollowed the premature explosion of a large blast of dynamite. Rescuers,
are shown in -the bed of -the. subway searching for victims. The construc
tion work gave way for a block, dropping three crowded care into chasm.
-o o-
WHAT WAS THE CAUSE-THEN7
Three physicians sard that Albert
$nd Joseph KIrsch, three and two
years old, had ded of ptemaine poi
soning anxl attributed it to the ice
cream which their father had bought
.them at a store at 2452 Cortez st
An inspector .from the health de
partment took a sample of the cream.
Several days later Kirsch visited tp.e
city hall to find out the outcome''of
the test He was told the sample had
-been destroyed.
Another sample was obtained and
tested. Dr. P. 0, Tonney said no poi
son was found, i</text>
    </result>
    <result>
    <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045487/1915-09-25/ed-1/?sp=31&q=New+York+Subway&st=text&r=-0.309,0.152,1.618,1.618,0/</id>
    <rel>1</rel>
    <text>SERIOUS SMASH-UP IN NEW
YORK SUBWAY TUNNEL
New York, Sept 29. One of the
most serious accidents in the his
tory of the New York subway sys
tem occurred early today when two
trains collided underneath 142d st,
the Bronx.
Three men received injuries which
are expected to prove fatal. The
trains took fire and, in fighting the
flames, 20 firemen were overcome by
the dense smoke which choked the
tunnel. 100 passengers on a train
following those which collided were
thrown into a panic and fought the
guards until the doors were opened.
They then walked seven blocks back
through the smoke-filled tunnel.
The injured men are all subway
employes They were removed to the
Fordham Hospital There it was stat
ed that they had a small chance for
recovery.</text>
   </result>
   <result>
      <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1918-08-02/ed-1/?sp=6&q=subWay&st=text&r=0.484,0.3,0.379,0.274,0/</id>
      <rel>1</rel>
      <text>Father Knickerbocker Lost at Times Square
As New Subway System Goes in Operation
THE "H"?THE CITY'S NEW SUBWAY SYSTEM
New York now has a double subway line traversing the city from north to south?the West Side, or Broadway line, and the East
Side, or Lexington Avenue line. They are shown in the above map, with the link between them, across Forty-second Street, forming the
cross-bar of the "H." Connection between the two lines will be made through the Forty-second Street shuttle.
The broken white lines indicate the old subway lines. The solid white lines show the new lines, parts of which have been in
operation for several weeks, but arc now joined with the old lines by the Forty-second Street shuttle to form a complete system. Only
express stations are indicated on the map.
Thousands Unable to Solve
Complexities Presented by
the *'H" in 42nd Street,
and as a Result Are Carried
Far in Directions Opposite
toThose They Wished to Go I
Shonts Says Traffic Conges-
tion in New York City Ten
Years Hence Will Be
Worse Than Now, Despite
All the New Improve?
ments and Facilities in Use
?Continued from page 1
spired and fnmed in their efforts to
make their directions heard above the
din of the hosts of inquirers. Their
ffforts were in large measure unavail?
ing and hundreds merely roamed about
the stavtion in search of some kind of
a train. Many gave it up and returned
to the street?when they could find
the way out.
People who wanted to go to the up?
per Eaat Sido and The Bronx could not
be made to understand that they
should take a shuttle train to the new
Lexington Avenue station, and some of
them found themselves at Brooklyn
Bridge or oth?er southern points on the
old subway before they discovered
their mistake. The reverse situation ex?
isted with marry who desired to go up?
town on the West Side, but. could not
solve the riddle of the shuttle service
at Times Square.
Transit officials expect a good deal of
confusion for a few days until passen?
gers grasp the significance of the new
routes and learn that a change from
the upper East Side or the upper West
Side line, to reach extreme points on
either side of the city downtown, means
a transfer at the nt:w Grand Central di?
agonal stations and the use of the shut?
tle service.
The confusion may be more serious
to-day and to-morrow when the rush
hour crowds start for work, but Inter?
borough officials said last night they
expected to clear up the situation in a
day a two when the through express
service on both new lines will be in
complete operation.
Shonts? Gloomy Forecast
While the scramble was going on at
Times Square President Shonts of the
Interborough. speaking at the Astor
Hotel, predicted that transit conges?
tion would he worse ten years hence
than it is now, despite the completion
of the new subways. _ Although it was
the biggest moment in the history of
New York transportation, Mr. Shents
said, the increase and concentration of
population in the city during the next
ten years would mean a return of con?
ditions on the transit lines worse than
they are now.
"So the phenomenon of crowded
cars," said Mr. Shonts, "is due to
causes quite beyond the control of
transit corporations. It is due to the
growing concentration of people in
great cities."
The Interborough president also
made a plea for increased fares on the
transit lines. He followed Oscar S.
Straus, former chairman of the Public
Service Commission, who said the ques- j
tion of six-cent fares was bound to
come up for serious consideration soon,
and that the city officials and members
of the Public Service Commission
should have the courage to errant the
increase, provided the condition of the
companies warranted it, even though it i
were not a popular move politically.
"The public official, be he President, j
Governor or Mayor," said Mr. Straus, j
"who has not the courage to act in an j
emergency in the face of political dis-1
approval is not fit to hold office."
Hylan as Motorman
Mayor Hylan, accompanied by other?
city officials; the Public Service Com?
missioners, Interborough officials, sub?
way engineers and a large party of
distinguished guests, made the first
trip on the new lines which marked
the opening of the "H" section. The
special train of ten cars left the diago?
nal station at Grand Central at 8:45
p. m. It ran down through the old
subway, made the loop at the Battery
and then passed up the new Seventh
Avenue line to Forty-second Street.
Headed by the subway band, the offi?
cial party marched from there to the
Astor Hotel.
Mayor Hylan acted as motorman of
the new train. Chairman Charles Bulk
ley Hubbell of the Public Service Com?
mission said afterward that if the
Mayor managed and operated the vari?
ous activities of the city government as
weil as he operated the train there
could be no complaint from the citi?
zens. Although the Mayor never was a
motorman he at one time piloted a
locomotive on the old B. K. T. elevated
lines, and that experience may have
helped him last night.
Before starting ?the train the Mayor
pushed a signal button at the station
which notified every other station on
the new lines that the "11" section was
in operation. A flashlight was then
taken of the Mayor standing at the
signal board with President Shonts,
Chairman Hubbell and Frank Hedley,
?general manager of the Interborough.
Chief Engineer Daniel L. Turner, of
the Public Service Commission, and
Chief Engineer George H. Pet-ram, of
the Interborough, a few minutes before
had walked down the track to the point
of actual connection between the old
and new lines and driven the last spike
which linked them together.
Speaker** at Exercise?
The official party reach"?) the Astor
Hotel at about 9:30, a little behind the
??chedulcd time. The speakers included
hairman Hubbell, who presided;
Mayor Hylan, Mr. Straus. Mr. Shonts,
Alfred K. Marling, president of the
Chamber hi Commerce; George Mc
Aoeny, former president of the Board
of Aldermen; William It. Willcox, for
mer ehairrnan of the Public Service
ommission, and Adolph S. Ochs.
A/t'-r paying a high tribute to the
ork of Mr. Hedley for
in making the new subway
possible, Chairman Hubbell
o?;.'"*; Mayor Hylan, who sat on
platform beside President Shonts.
?Mayor ?aid that he bad never
Btad the pleasure of enjoying a
ride a subway and sitting be?
ll'' Pres?d?-nt Short? all in the imme
gniftf, il*- -?aid th? hands and the
coring crowd at the Autor made him
sink for a moment that he was bark
n the city campaign of last fall. When
he reached the platform, however, and
?aw Commissioners Kracke and Whit?
ney there he realized that it wa? not
trije, he ??aid.
AM irUl?? m* tti&h. tt^uta to
the great engineering fent which had
been consummated by the opening of
the new lines. He said that although
he had opposed some things that had
been done in connection with the con?
struction of the new subways, he was
glad to be the chief magistrate of the
city at a time when one of the most
important sections of the new transit
lines was opened up.
People Deserve New Service
"I am sure the people of the eity
will be glad to know to-morrow that
the service on both the West Side and
East Side subways has become a fact,"
said the Mayor. "I have opposed from
time to time some of the things that
have been done in connection with sub?
way construction. I opposed the pres?
ent dual subway contracts because I
believed they would not be the best
thing for the people of the city, but
others in control thought differently,
and they prevailed.
"I have sometimes thought that the
transit corporations have been short?
sighted. The people put their money
in the construction of these subways,
and they are entitled to the best pos?
sible service. I am glad, however, to
be the chief magistrate of the city at
a time when this most important link
in the new transit system is opened
up."
Commissioner Hubbell introduced
former Chairman Straus as "the wiz?
ard of conciliators." Mr. Straus said
the "H" did not stand for what some
people might believe it to be-when
the word was not spelled out but that
it had been so called because it was
opened in the administration of Mayor
Hylan.
The former chairman said there was
a time when the Public Service Com?
mission and the city administration did
not get along very well, but he had had
a 'talk with the Mayor, and the latter
agreed with him that such a situation
should not exist?and the trouble
ended. He said it was due in large
measure to the change of front of the
Mayor and the hearty cooperation of
the city officials with the commission
that the new lines were finished and
opened at this time. Mr. Straus then
took up the question of the 6-cent fare
and discussed it wi'th all seriousness,
as a probable war necessity.
Prediction by Shonts
President Shonts followed Mr. Straus.
Referring to transit conditions to be
expected in 1928, the speaker said:
"This day marks a most important
chapter in the marvellous story of New
York City's rapid transit. But, much as
has been accomplished and stupendous
as are the figures by which we attempt
to tell the story of New York's trav?
elling hosts, the end of our undertak?
ing is not even in sight.
"In ten years there is every reason
to believe the city will have increased
to a point which will make the traffic
congestion of 1928 greater than that of
1918. History will repeat itself. Fol?
lowing every increase of transit facil?
ities in New York has come added pop?
ulation and greater congestion. Im?
proved facilities are one of the causes
of the city's added growth. If popu?
lation stood still we could catch up to
its demands. But it does not stand
still."
In regard to increased fares Mr
?Shonts said*.
"But the war has changed all these
calculations. In place of earning the
returns indicated large deficits have
arisen and larger ones are in sight.
How shall this situation be met? We
contend that it is an emergency and
should be treated as an emergency and
not by a method which will leave a
permanent effect upon business, upon
consequent movement of population
and upon property.
Two Methods Presented
"These deficits can be met in only
one of two ways?either by a higher
fare, throwing the burden upon the
people who actually get the benefit of
the increased service, or by taxation,
which will fall upon the already over?
burdened real estate owners, which
will result in increased rents, increased
grocers' bills and increased cost ol
living generally to all the people who
work and spend their incomes in New
York. Wherea3 if it is met by higher
fares not only would it lall upoti
those citizens of New York who re?
ceive the benefit of the service, but
also upon .300,000 daily visitors to the
city, who pay 500,000 fares a day and
who do not live in New York and do
not help pay her taxes.
"So while the proposition of in?
creased fares in the city aroused op?
position at first, I cannot help but be?
lieve that serious 'hought will con?
vince every unprejudiced student of
the question it is fundamental^
better for the interests of the city that
the situation which now confronts us,
and which is of a very serious and
i critical nature, should be met by in
j creased fares rather than by taxation
How to Reach Your
Destination on New
"H" Subway Lines
The opening of the Lexington Ave
nue subway last night having completed
the transformation of New York's old
I subway system, which was shaped like
the crank of a Ford, into the new "II"
system, the Public Service Commission
has iHHued a pamphlet to instruct a
i public accustomed to the crank to the
intelligent une of the "H." The two
upright? of the "H" are known as the
Werft Side subway and the East Sida
subway, while the crankshaft of the old
subway from the Grand Central station
to Times Kquare forms the crossbar of
th? "H."
A (Shuttle acrvice ?will t>e operated
?long the crossbar while through trains
will run along the uprights of the "H."
The righthand upright or East Side
?ubway is composed of the old subway
from the Battery and Atlantic Avenue,
Brooklyn, terminals to tho Grand Cen?
tral station arid the Lexington Avenue
extension to the northward.
Thnot th? pi?. ?r?nd Cf?BUai exfijrcB? ?U
tion, but a new one known as the Diag?
onal Station, which is on a lower level.
The old one will be used solely for the
shuttle service to Times Square.
North of the new Grand Central sta?
tion, the East Side subway turns into
Lexington Avenue, continuing to and
under the Harlem River into the Bronx,
with express stations at Eighty-sixth
Street and at 125th Street and local
stations as follows: Fifty-first Street,
Fifty-ninth Street, Sixty-eighth Street,
Hunter College, Seventy-seventh Street,
Ninety-sixth Street, 103d Street, 110th
Street and 116th Street.
Near 136th Street the line forks to
form the Jerome Avenue branch and
the Pelham Bay Park branch, but the
point of transfer for trains on these
two branches on the East Side, subway
is at the 125th Street station, the
equivalent in this respect of the situa?
tion existing as to the Broadway and
Lerfox Avenue branches at Ninety-sixth
Street on the old subway. The West
Farms trains in the East Side subway
will continue up Jerome Avenue to
149th Street, where they are to be di?
verted to the West Farms branch.
Most of the West. Farms trains car?
rying passengers for that branch and
for the White Plains Road extension
will use. thi6 route; the rest will be
operated over the West Side subway.
The Pelham Bay Park branch is only
partly finished, its completion having
been delayed by governmental demands
for labor and material.
If you take a subway train on the
Jerome Avenue branch (elevated rail?
road trains also will be operated over
this line above 162d Street) it will con?
vey you down through the new Lexing?
ton Avenue subway to Forty-second
Street and thence direct, via the old
subway, to the Battery or to Brooklyn.
If you take a subway train on the
West Farms branch (elevated trains
are operated over a part of this line)
designated for the East Side subway,
it will leave this branch at Mott Ave
ruie-149th Street and proceed south?
bound as indicated in the preceding
paragraph.
For the present, the Pelham Bay
Park branch will be operated only to
and from the Third Avenue station.
Service on this branch will proceed
through the. new Lexington Avenue
subway and so on downtown via the
old subway. The first station reached
on the main line, after leaving Third
Avenue station, is 125th Street, the
point of change for Jerome Avenue and
West Farms branches.
If you wish to go from East Side sub?
way to the Queensboro subway, trans?
fer at Grand Central station to Queens?
boro train on the lower level.
If you take a train on the old sub?
way in Brooklyn or at the Battery or
other stations in Manhattan, it will
convey you uptown through the old
subway, south of Forty-second Street,
then through the new Lexington Ave?
nue subway, and, accordingly as the
train is designated, to one of three
branches in the Bronx- the Jerome
Avenue branch, to the West Farms
branch ("West. Side subway) and the
Pelham Bay Park branch.
If you take a train designated for
I the wrong branch, change cars at 125th
Street.
If you wish to go from East Side
subway to the Queensboro subway,
change at Grand Central Station to
Queensboro train, lower level.
If you wish to transfer to the Third
Avenue elevated railroad, transfer
from West Farms branch at 149th
Street and Third Avenue.
If you desire to reach a point on the
West Side subway, transfer to shuttle
at Grand Central Station, and re
transfer, at Times Square southbound,
for points on new Seventh Avenue sub?
way and, northbound, for points on old
subWay north of Forty-second Street.
The left-hand upright of the "11" or
West Side subway consists of the old
Broadway and Lenox Avenue lines
from Times Square northward and the
new Seventh Avenue subway, which
joins the old subway just north of a
new Times Square express station,
which replaces the old Times Square
local station close by.
North of Times Square, the stations
are the old ones to which the public
has become accustomed. South from
Times Square on the Seventh Avenue
subway the first station reached is the
Pennsylvania express station, between
which and the Times Square station
shuttle trains have been in operation
for more than a year. Other express
stations are at Fourteenth Street and
at Chambers Street.
Local West Side Stations
The local stations are Twenty-eighth
Street, Twenty-third Street, Eighteenth
Street, Christopher Street-Sheridan
Square, Houston Street, Canal Street,
Franklin Street and Cortlandt Street,
Rector Street and City Hall (going to
the Battery) and Park Place, Fulton
Street and Wall Street (on the Brook?
lyn branch 1.
If you take a train on the Broadway
branch, West Side subway, it will con?
vey you down through the old subway
to Forty-second Street, 'hence direct
down Seventh Avenue, Varick Street,
West Broadway and Greenwich Street
to the Battery or through the Park
Place-William Street branch to Wall
Street.
If you wish to go to Brooklyn or to
any point on the old subway south of
Forty-second Street, transfer from the
West Side subway at Times Square to
tl shuttle service across Forty-second
Street and retransfer at Grand Central
Station, southbound, to train desig
nat'^d properly for destination you
wish to reach.
If you wish to go from the West
Side subway to the new Lexington
Avenue subway, north of Forty-second
Street, or to its Pelham Bay Park
branch, transfer to the shuttle train at
Times Square r.nd retrarnfer, north?
bound, at Grand Central Station, to
train properly designated for destina?
tion you wish to reach.
If you wish to go from '.he West Side
subway to the Queensboro subway,
transfer to the shuttle train at Times
Square, and retransfer at Grand Cen?
tral Station to the Queensboro subway
train on the lower level.
West Farms Train
About half the trains on the Lenox
Avenue-West Farms branch will be
routed through the West Side subway,
similar to present operation. (From
Mott Avenue or stations further east
on this branch the most direct way to
reach points on the new Lexington
Avenue subway or on the old subway
south of Forty-second -5tr.*et, or on the
old subway in Brooklyn, is to tak?> an
East Side subway train direct.) Such
trains will bo switched from the West
Farms branch at Mott Avenue and
14yth Street and proceed directly down?
town through the East Side subway.
If you take a train on the Seventh
Avenue subway with Brooklyn as your
destination it will be necessary to go
to Times Square, change to a shuttlo
train and transfer again at the Grand
Central Station to a southbound train
properly designated for your destina?
tion. For points in Manhattan south
of the City Hall, east and west side
subways offer practically the same fa?
cilities.
Going uptown, if you take a train
on either the Park Place, William
Street or Battery branches of the Sev?
enth Avenue subway, on the main line
of the Seventh Avenue subway or north
of Times Square on the old subway, it
will take you up the Broadway or West
Farms branch, according to which train
you take. From the West Farms
branch access may be had as hereto?
fore at Mott Avenue and 149th Street
to trains on the Jerome Avenue branch
of the East Side subway to trains of the
Third Avenue elevated line at Third
Avenue and 149th Street and to trains
of the White Plains Road extension at
177th Street.
All passengers who can avoid doinp;
so are urged not to transfer from one
upright of the "H" to the other, but to
utilize through train service to the ut?
most in the interest, of efficient service.
??H??IW?^?????Ml?^??l. ?I??I.?MII?.?MM?</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030272/1913-12-28/ed-1/?sp=17&q=Subway&st=text&r=-0.236,-0.1,1.472,1.472,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>NEW YORK, SUNDAY, DECEMBER 28, 1913 Copyright, 1913, fcj the .'nu Printing PuMlsalim Aatoclntu.
NEW YORK CITY TO GO FORWARD ONCE MORE
STIMULATED BY GREAT NEW TRANSIT SYSTEM
Fortunes Greater Than Those Created
by the Present Subway Expected to
Result From the Demand for Prop
erty Along the 324 Miles of New Lines
11 r imw.win k. mocam..
halrataa of the Public Scrxlce
Commlmlon.
As Tar n 1 can judge the real entitle
outlook for tho year 101 1 if more promising
than It hag lieon fur ninny yearn. This
I say In vtaw of the tremendous trniif It
improvements which the city of New
Vork is now making ami Ihe efiect of
which bhould ho felt during the year 101 1
I ho construction of sulrwuys and ele
vated railroads invariably bus liroiiKht
about, a large increase, in the value of
ie.il property. esieciully In territory
previously deficient in transportation
lacilities The dual system or rapid
transit wo expect to see in complete
operation hy January 1. 101" The Inter
vening three years, therofote, should
bring about the development of muny
hitherto neglected sections of tho city,
as well uh increased values in sections
iilivudy built up. If we could bee to-day
tho figures wliich will npvear on Ihe as
sessment books four years hence I urn
sure they would startle even the moitt
optimistic of real estate oierutor's.
We know what a stimulus Ihe existing
subway proved to valuations in Man
hattan and The Bronx, uud we have every
reason to believe thut history will rewat
itsslf when tho new lines now under
construction are completed and placed
in oieratioii, Tho existing subway all
told has only ubmit t-evenly-live miles
of (.ingle track The new com miction
alone of the dual system will add XM
miles of single track to the existing lines,
lint system will embrace the existing
-ithway, the existing elevated lines in
Manhattan and The Bronx and the ex
isting elevated railroads in Brooklyn,
with a total or '.'Wl miles of single tniek.
With the 3:l miles of new construction the
whole system will have a trackage of
miles, which will lie divided fr operation
between the luterborottgh Rapid Transit
lompany and the New Yoik Municipal
K-iilway CorHjration
llefote this -Vslein can be placed in
operation the city of New York and the
two operating companies wilt have ox
Iwiided moie than tMn.mw.uni) for con
struction nnd equipment Even in Ihe
linancial capital of the riche-t nation or
ihe world, where transactions involving
millions are of coiiimou occurrence, this
i a stupendous total for disbursement
within four short years, ll i- more than
one-third of the national debt, and it is
about tho cost of the Panama Canal
Suoh an amount of money invested in a
publin improvement anywhere in the
world must be followed by great benefit
t the surrounding prorty
When the existing subway was built
its two branches in 'Ihe lirnux, viz., the
Broadway division und the Iamiox avenue
division, projected largely into unde
veloped territory A study of the real
estate vulues of vacant lots in this terri
tory for the year louo, four years prior
to the opening of the subway, shows the
increase in valuations brnuuht about by
t lie opera; ion of the subwuy Comparison
of these values with Ihe assessed valua
tions in 1907, a little more than two years
alter the subway begun operation, shows
Mil astounding increase In the territory
opened up bv the Broadway brunch
valuations between Kt.'tli street and
spuyten Duyvil from iwmto Itw; increased 1
about MtCluo.tiOo. 'I lie normal increase of i
he previous seven years was estimated
.it lhO.000, which, subtrai ted I rum ihe
IW7 valuations, shows the increase due'
to the building of the Midway to have
been about JUV.'ou.imni. 'Ibis was an in-1
i tease of KM er cent in seven years,,
l roerty ueveIo'd ly Hie i.enox avenue
blanch made a similar showing. The
aggregate increase for the seven yeurs in
the district lrom tho llurlem Kiver to
brum I'ark (.vacant lots) woa about
Jlt.soo.ono, As the normal increase for
the previous seven years was estimated
at JlU.WO.OOO, this showed an increase of
XII.SW.ooo apparently duo to Ihe building
of the subwuy. 1 nee no reason why a
similar increase in values should not
billow the opening up of the dual system
in undeveloHid or partially developed
sections.
1 am glad to be able to state that con
struction work on the dual system is pro
gressing rapidly. There is now under con
t met ion newly $eo,0oo,ouo worth of work
nail before the new year is two months
old this total will be increased to more
than HOO.OUO.OOO. This means that more
than half of the work which the City of
Vw York is to puy for in I lie new system
is already under contract. This work is
being done by eighteen different con
tractors who employ all told a daily force
ol about 7,000 men. For tho year 101S up
'o tho 15th of December the City of New
nrk had paid these contractors a total of
nearly $15,000,000, so that the new work
i- already putting into circulation more
i ha u $!,noo,00n of new money every month
I he average expenditure for 1014 will be
e en larger, so thut the construction of
this groat work is already proving on im
portant factor in tho employment of labor
and tho promotion of the general pros
perity. While the dual system will extend rapid
transit facilities lo many undeveloped
sections, it will also relieve present con
'.Mioii in most of Ihe developed portions
of the city. Even streets in the old city
ol Vow York, away down in the financial
district or Manhuttan, will be tunnelled
to miiliu space for the tracks which will
i.njiat.i under rivers and over miles of
and to tho remotest districts of Brooklyn.
Queens and The Hronx. The system will
have two grand divisions, one to be oper
ated by the Jnterboroush lUpid Transit
i ompany and the other by the New York
Municipal Hallway Corporal ion. Iu tho
Interborough territory important uddi
"e will bo made lu ihe subway and ele
v.ited lines it now operate. I'ho nib
y runs lrom 1 lall iish and Atlantic
venues in Brooklyn under the East Hirer
to Manhattan and up tho Kut Side of
.Manhattan Island to Forty-second street
at the Grand Central Station, where It
turns westward and runs through Forty
seoond 'street to Broudway ut 'limes
Square, and thenco continues up Broad
way to Ninety-sixth, where it divides into
two branches, the westorly branch con
tinuing up Broadway and across the Har
lam River to Von Cortlandt I'ark or
342d street and the easterly branch run
ning out Lenox avenue and other afreets
to Bronx Park or 180th atreet. The line
from Brooklyn Bridge to Nluety-slxth
street la a four track road upon which
both express and local trains are operated,
Ihe dual system plans call for the exten
sion of this subwuy from Forty -second
street at the Grand Central Stutlon, up
Lexington avenue, un Mast Side thorough-
faro, to tho Harlem Hiver as a four truck
road, Hero the line, will diride Into two I
branches, ihe westerly branch running
through Moll, JUver and It tome avenues
to Wood lawn road and the easterly brunch
through Southern Boulevard und West
Chester uvenue lo l'elham Bay I'ark Each
of these branches will be u three track
road.
On the West Side, beginning nl Tunes
Square, there will be an extension down
Seventh uvenue, Vuriek slieef. West
Broudwav and Greenwich stieet to the
Battery. This also will lie a four track
lino from Tunes Square to I'.irlc pl.ic".
where two tracks will divcige to lliooklyu
und the other two continue on to the
Battery uud u junction wllji tho existing
subwuy loop under Battery I'ark. The
two truoks diverging ut I'ark place will
oontinue through I'ark place under the
Post Oflloe building to Beekiuun street,
through Beekman street to William street
and down William st reet to Old Slip, where
they will enter tho tunnol lo bo built
under the Eust Iliver to Clark street,
Brooklyn, and a connection with tho ex
isting subway near Borougii Hull, Brook
lyn, The subway which now ends at
Flatbush and Atluntio avenues will also
be extended out Flatbush avenue to
Eastern Parkway uud through Eastern
Parkway to Buffalo uvenue. This will bo
a four track road. 1'rom Buffalo fcvenUe
au extension will be built thiough Kasi
Ninety-eighth street to blvonia avenue
and out blvonia avenue to New Lots road.
This extension will be a three track line.
Front this brief sketch of the routes it
will be seen that the additions lo t ,ie exist
ing subway will more than double lt
pie-ent facilities, By the building of the
Lexington avenue line north or Forty
second street and joining It to the e: isting
subway south or thut street the 'liter
borough will have for operation n com
plete, four track lino up and down the
The Spirit of New York
East Side from Brooklyn Bridge to the
Ifnrlem Hiver. Similarly by building the
Seventh uvenue subway south of Forty
second street und attaching it to the
existing subwuy in Broudway north of
that street the company will have a com
plete West Side lino from I'ark place to
Ninety-sixth street. Instead of having
four trucks bet weed Brooklyn Bridge
and Ninety-sixth street, us ut present,
the now system, therefore, will have eight
truoks between those points, practically
a duplication of tho existing subwuy.
In 'I'he Bronx ihe existing brunches of
the subway have only two trucks each,
although in places there are three tracks,
but for operating purposes ihey may be
considered two truck lines As Ih.i now
line up Jerome avenue and the new lino
out .Southern Boulevard und Westchester
avenue will have three tracks each, It is
apMirent that these two branches of the
Lexington uvenue subway alone will nunc
than double Ihe present subway facilities
lu The Bronx, lu uddition, however, Ihe
dual system plans ,i for the extension
or tiie Lenox avenue branch of the exist
ing subway from isuih stieet out White
Plums, raid lo 2 list street, very near the
northerly city line. As tills ulso will be n
three track road the three new subway
hues iu I'he Bronx will provide s total or
nine trucks, us ugaiiisi I our on i he existing
subway. The subway facilities ulon
therelore, iu tliat borough will be more
than trebled,
Extensions to the elevuted railroads
operulod by the luterliorough Company
will further amplify the facilities of those
important agencies of transportation. At
present I hero urn two elevated lines on the
West Side und two on the East Side of
Munhuttun The West Side lines ure tho
Ninth nnd Sixth uvenue systems. Whilo
both art operated from the Buttery to the
Harlem Hlvou at l.Vith street, they are
cm te lines only south of Fifty-third
street Norlhofthal point Ihereureonly
three tracks u-cit iu common by trains
from both lines, The Ninth avenue lino
now bus a third truck for express service
Public Service Commission Pushing Work
on Entire $360,000,000 Improvement
About Which Centre Hopes of All
Realty Owners in Greater City
extending from Christopher stieet on the
south to IIHtli street on the 1101 th Under
the dual system plans this third track will
he extended lo Bulleiy place on the south
uud lo iMlh street on the north, mi that
through express service will lie possible
for the entire length of the present line,
In addition the Ninth avenue linn will bo
connected at 15Mb street with tho pio
poscd elevuted branch of tho Lexington
avenue subway in .lerome uvenue, which
will be used jointly by elevated uud bub
wuy trains. When this is done travellers
on tho West Side elevated roads will bo
enabled lo go from downtown .Mauliatlun
to Woodlawn roud without chanvnof cars.
Of the East Side elevated roads the
Second uvenue line ha- no third Hack
whatever The Third uvenue line has u
third track from Forty second stieet In,
(he llurlem Iliver at With street The
I necessity for switching express trains lo
the local tracks south of Forty-second is
one of the grout defects of present opera
tion. Under the dual system this wilt be
remedied by the extension of the third
track from Forty-second street down to
City Hall There will also be a third track
added to the Second avenue line for its
entire length below the Harlem River
The Third avenue line will be third tracked
also ucross the Harlem and as far as Pel-
lia 111 avenue An extension of this lino will
also be built from the present terminus
north through Webster uvcnuo to Gun Hill
1 road and through Ouu Hill road to White
I'liiin- road, where a junction will be made
witli the extension of tho Lenox avenue
I subway to 311st street. This extension,
like -loroiiip avenue, will lie used jointly by
subway ami elevated truins. so that when
I I lie system is completed it will bo possible
for a piiKfecugor to travel on tho elevated
line or the subway from tho City Hall lo
:isi street without chunge or cum and
lor n single raie.
i The InterlKiioiigh lines will also l
extended into the Borough of Queens,
which up to the present time lids never
enjoyed rapid transit except such as is
possible through the Pennsylvania tun-
i uels. The city is now building for opera
tion by the Intcrborough, witlt trackage
rights also to the New York Municipal
Hallway Coiporation, two important lines
in Queens borough Both begin ut Queens-
Isiro Bridge, and ono runs north
i through Second avenue to Oil mars ave
ntle, Astoria, and the other through
Koo-evelt uvenue to Corona und Flush
i lie. and each will be a three track ele-
v.i led ruilroud. 'Ihe Ititerborough com
pany will extend the Second avenue ele
vated line to uud over the Queensboro
Bridge lo connect with these new lines,
over which it will oKrate elevated trains
I l rom the Second avenue system. The
city alo is building an extension to the
I Steinwuy tunnel from its piesent terminus
in Long Islund City to the Queensboro
Bridge plaza. This extension also will
join the new Queens lines so that tho ln
iterborough will be enabled to run trains
from the .Steinway tunnel to Astoria
nnd to Flushing. The Steinwuy tunnel
al-o will be extended lai the .Manhattan
ide through Forty-second street to
Times Sqiiaie and u junction with the
existing subway, so that eventually it will
be possible for train- starling ut un
Cortlandt Park to pass through the Stein
way tunnel and over tne new lines lo
A-toiia and Flushing
Tne mere statement of Ihe extent to
which the luterliorough lines are to be
eviandeil i-. siifticienl lo convince any
me that the dual system will work n
i evolution in transportation facilities iu
i lie field now covered by that system.
No one can now predict the full ex
lent of the benefits which will follow.
Il will icm.iin for uctual operation to
-bow the degree of benefit which this
i great improvement will confer.
In the Brooklyn field no less of a traffic
revolution will follow the completion of
the dual system This territory is now
served mainly Wy the lines of the Brooklyn
liupid Tiaiisil Coinpanv This company,
under the name of the New York Municipal
Itiiilw iv Coiporation, has madeii contract
with the City of New ,urk to connect it
existing lines witli new lines lo ls buill by
the city and to operate them as one sys
tem At present the Brooklyn elevated
railroads cover in.", miles of single track.
I'lnler Ihe dual system the enmpuny will
have for otorut inn HI Millie of single track.
The lliooklyu elevated roads now enter
Williamsburg Budge Cnder the new sys
tem they will Imve additional entrances
iliioiub two new tunnel.', under the East
Kiver nnd ov er the Manhattan Bridge A I
pieent(.ill such lines tei initiate at Ihe
two bridge- named, so thai passengers
mii-t pay another faro to leach uny other
pal I of Manhattan The dual system will
provide the lliooklyu company with two
tiewsudwuys in Manhattan through which
the entile Unfile ut the Brooklyn elevated
railioads can ls dirliibuted without the
payment of an additional tare, One of
Ihse subways i- the Centre street loop
and Ihe oilier the Broadway subway, Tho
Centre street loop is ulready completed
from the Manhattun end or the Brooklyn
Biidge north through Centre street to
IMiincey stieet extension, uud through
heluncey street extension to the Williams
burg Undue, with a spur at Canal street
connecting with the .Mitnliuttuii Bridge,
I Ins .pur is now lieing connected with t tie
Brooklyn Bridge and will soon bccxlondrd
down Nassau slieei to Broad street, and
a conneclion with the proposed tunnel
under the East Hiver from Whitehall
street, Manhuttan, lo Montague street,
Brooklyn, and u connection with the
l'ouilli avenue subway in Brooklyn.
The Broudwuy subway will also lie con
nected with this tunnel lino und will
extend up Trinity plate uud Church
Nlieel lo Veey street, through Vesey
Mi eel to Bioiidvvay and up Broadway
to Forty-second stieet ut Times Square
'and thence up Seventh uvenue to Flfty
iiiiilh street From Cunui street lo
I'oi l y. second sheet Ihis subway will be
a four track road. At Fifty-ninth street
two tracks will terminate and two tracks
.will continue eastward through Fifty-
ninth and Sixtieth streets to nna over tne
Queensboro Bridge and n connection with
the new rnpid transit line! in Queens
llOI'OIIR.I.
The Centre stieet loop subway is the
11 1 si part of the dual system to be placed
iu operation. Since August 4 lust the
Brooklyn company bus been opcratiiw
all its elevated trains coining tmiu ui-s
Williutiiburg Bridge through this sub
way For this purpose only the two
westerly tracks In the loop subway I
being used, und the other two tracks will
remain idle uiililhe conneclion with the
Hiool.l.-n Undue is completed 'I he pre,
cut operation, however, has greatly re
lieved the ciusli on the Brooklyn Biidge,
L'OllllMUtll uu
Hctvnd</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030272/1910-10-05/ed-1/?sp=5&q=Subway&st=text&r=0.069,0.641,0.866,0.627,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>The Subway Store at Gimbels GimbelsTwo
Two Stories High Below the Street Level
I
I II IIi
i This Subway Store Is So Totally Unlike Any AnyOther AnyOther AnyI AnyOther
Other in the World that You Will Never NeverRealize NeverRealize NeverRealize
I Realize that You Are in a Basement at All I
I II I When we planned the Gimbel Store we spent spentmonths spentmonths I Imonths
months over the problem of making a Basement BasementSalesroom BasementSalesroom j ji
i Salesroom as bright and cheery as any aboveground above aboveground I Ii
i ground section sectionWith sectionVith sectionVith
Vith the help of the ablest architects in Amer America AmerI AmerI Amcrica I
I ica we succeeded succeededGone succeededGone succeededGone
Gone are the lowhanging ceilings the dim dimlights dimtights dimt
t lights the deep shadows the stuffy atmosphere and andthe andthe i ithe
the musty corners of the oldfashioned old basement basementGone basetl1entI
I
I Gone are the oldfashioned old methods of basemerit base basement basement
ment merchandising the collection of odds and andends andends andends
ends and unpleasant trash the slipshod careless carelessservice carelessservice I Iservice
service the general air of cheapness pushed to toits toI
I 3 its worst worstYou worstI worstYou worstYou I
I You will look in vain for any of these at Gimbels GimbelsOurs GiJTIbelsOurs Gimbelsj
j Ours is a big bright handsome store of ofI
I
TWO selling floors occupying a space of over one onehundred onehundred onehundred
hundred and fifty thousand square feet feetPowerful feetPowerful feetPowerful
Powerful pumps working through an elaborate elaborateventilation elaborateventilation elaborateventilation
ventilation system change the air in the Subway SubwayStore SubwayStore SubwayStore
Store completely every ten to twelve minutes Even Evenwith Evenwith Evenwith
with the throngs of the past few days the air is isalways isalways isalways
always as pure as it is outside and the temperature temperaturenever
never more than four degrees higher higherua a triumph in inventilating inventilating inventilating
ventilating engineering engineeringAnd
And in the Subway Store you will find broad broadvarieties broadvarieties broadvarieties
varieties of almost all lines I of merchandise carried carriedin I Iin
in the upper floors duplicated in the less expensive expensivegrades expensivegrades expensivegrades
grades every pennys worth Reliable every pennys pennysworth pennysworth
worth a full measure of value every ounce and inch inchof inchof inchof
of it good clean inexpensive but worth having havingThe havingThe havingThe
The same service the same ideals the same samestandards samestandards samestandards
standards prevail in the Subway Store as else elsewhere elsewhere elsewhere
where in this house and everything in it is NEW</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1904-09-04/ed-1/?sp=25&st=text&r=-0.306,0.051,1.63,1.18,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>It is the subway station at Twenty-third-st and Fourth-ava. Behind the brick pillars at the left Is
the basement of a building In Fourth-aye. This basement now has a fine, light front on the sub
way, and will be rented at a high figure as one larye shop or several small ones.</text>
     </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1922-08-28/ed-1/?sp=1&st=text&r=-0.023,0.177,1.017,0.736,0/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn99062010/1909-01-28/ed-1/?sp=2&q=new+york+subway+construction&st=text&r=0.357,0.981,0.571,0.414,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>[NEW YORK SUBWAY
CONSTRUCTION MAY
STOP FUNDS SHY
New York, Jan. 25.—Unless the legis
lature increases the borrowing capacity
of New York, subway construction and
other public improvement work will
have to he halted for at least two years,
according to a statement made today
by Mayor McClellan before the legisla
tive committee which Is Investigating!
the municipality's finances. The mayor!
declared that he felt bound by the re-'
port of William M. Ivins to the gov
ernor that the present margin of bor
rowing capacity was only $8,000,000. He
believed private capital would not bei
interested in extensive subway build-'
ling at the present time,
f. I</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn88056027/1907-05-17/ed-1/?sp=4&q=new+york+subway+construction&st=text&r=-0.355,-0.086,1.71,1.71,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>ontinued from Page 1.)
tine city of New York in its subway construction is profitable to the
public. The city has loaned its credit; with the money raised upon
that credit the subway has been built, and it has been leased to
private corporation for operation at such a rental that at the end
of the fifty years the municipal debt, principal and interest, will
all have been paid and the city will own the Subway—a piece of
property of large and increasing value—without having paid for
it a cent in actual cash. And as the Subway is operated by a pri
vate corporation, there is practically no increase of municipal office
holders and therefore no peril of an increased political machine.
On the other hand, we think it is equally evident from a wide ex
perience that the waterworks of a city should never lie left in
private hands even for temporary operation. The sanitary condi
lions of the city »re too dependent upon pure water and the peril
from false economics is too great. In water supply, economics arc
dangerous and extravagance is safe. The city, therefore, can bet
ter afford to pay for a water supply extravagantly administered
by the municipality than for a water supply economically admin
istered by private enterprise. In fact, experience shows that what
ever economic» private enterprise effects rarely diminish the expendi
ture». of the* citizens they swell the profits of the corporation. What
is true of the water supply is true of the school system. No one
that the public school buildings should lx* owned
or the public sc I tools operated by private enterprise; no one would
propose to farm the children out to the lowest bidder; for in pub
lic education
would propc
in public water supply the perils of extravagance
snim j uf ably It»'» than the perils from excessive economy.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84022472/1914-06-23/ed-1/?sp=1&q=new+york+subway+construction&st=text&r=0.501,0.762,0.317,0.23,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>SUBWAY CAVES 111,
20 BURIED, ONE HURT
New York, June 23. Nearly half a
block of sidewalk and' superstructure
over a new Brooklyn subway caved in
today, burying more than twenty
workmen, killing one and badly in
juring six. A wagon and a team of
horses were engulfed and one of the
animals was killed.
Many tons', of debris filled the ex
cavation and police reserves had to
dig out the injured. It was one of
the worst cave-iTia in the history of
New York subway construction!.
The superintendent and foreman of
the Job were arrested, pending an In
vestigation.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn82014519/1926-08-16/ed-1/?sp=2&q=new+york+subway+construction&st=text&r=0.098,0.1,0.511,0.37,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>scene during the fire,
ENGINEER OF NEW YORK
SUBWAYS PASSES AWAY
Succumbs to Illness in House Where
He Was Born In East
Hartford
Hartford, Aug. 16. UP) A. Edward
Olmsted, 80 years old, noted civil
engineer, who as division engineer
had direct charge of the construc
tion of the New York subway, died
yesterday at his home, 92 Prospect
street. East Hartford, after several
month's illness.
Mr. Olmsted was a member of
the American Society of Civil En
gineers and of the New York Acade
my of Sciences. He built the south
ern division of the Connecticut Val
ley railroad,' frojn Saybrook to Deep
River in 1870-72. He also construc
ted railroads In New York, Pennsyl
vania and many slates in the west
and on the Pacific coast. His most
notable work was on the construc
tion of the New York subway where
ho was division engineer under L. F.
Deyo, engineer of the New York
Subway Construction company
from 1900 until his retirement in
1918.
Since then Mr. Olmsted has lived
in East Hartford in the house where
he was born. Mr. Olmsted was
eighth in descent from James Olm
sted, one of the first settlers or
Hartford and sixth in descent from
Deacon Joseph Olmsted. The first
of the Olmsteads to settle on the
cast sldo of the Great river and who
was one of the founders of the First
Congregational church of East
Hartford.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn92051227/1922-05-27/ed-1/?sp=5&q=new+york+subway+construction&st=text&r=0.123,0.177,0.399,0.289,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>After a year of this, he obtained a
position soliciting subscriptions for a
religious publication, "The Baptist
Recorder," and here he earned monej
enough to go to Louisville where ho
got work as reporter on t'he Courier
Journal. After he had been on
that newspaper for sometime, he ask
ed to be assigned to the dramatic edi
tor's desk, and his reason for want
ing that position was to gain experi
ence so that he could write plays. He
Ik If
I GEnrrni J
Taj i rrr-
was told he must have stage experi
ence to write drama, so he joined a
traveling theatrical company.
After the company closed he took
an accounting of his assets and found
all he possessed was a bicycle. He
sold this and bought a ticket for New
York City. In order to make enough
money to live he wrote poetry and
feature articles for newspapers and
in between continued to be an actor.
He also wrote plays, one of which
called "The Fool and the Girl." was
produced by James K. HackeM. In
order to g:et material for plays ihe
traveled from coast to coast several
times gaining experience working as
a "puddler" in steel mills and as
".and-hog" on the New York Subway
construction.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn82014760/1861-10-31/ed-1/?sp=3&q=Halloween+Hallow+Hallowmas&st=text&r=0.001,0.563,0.366,0.265,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Mean are olroulated among tha floating pnputa
tton every day.besides thelarge number served
to regular subscribers. Advertisers will late
note accordingly.
Alt Hallow Ke.
To-night Is it!) IUItoto Tee, or Hallow n'en,
as being tlie vigil or ove uf Ml Hallow Day
Tbe Jlomlsh Church designed this day to bo
held In boner nf all those taints who had not
particular days appointed for them, but Ittloes
not appear that All nallowD,iy,or Its eye, oro
ever marked by very particular observance
In the Cathollo ohurchj novertholess. there
Is Boarooly any tlmo more distinguished by the
common feoplo of many portions uf the Brlltsh
Kinging of bells was one of tho modes of
celebrating Hallowmas m tngiana in umos piuii.
It whs a Itoman Oathn.lo practice, being da
signed In aomo way to flvr the souls or de
parted Christians. For this reason, Queon
Elizabeth prohibited It. It was also A custom,
a few centuries ago, to have a cake oaken on
this eve for overy member of the family, ns a
tout mass cake or soul cake. It was oomposod
of natmeal, and seoded; and pasties and fur
mety were Incidental to tho samo evening. In
families of good condition, a quantity were
hfllrnn unit ant nn on a board, liko tbe shew-
bread In old pictures In tbo Bible, to bo given
tp visiters, or distributed among the poor.
Thero was a rhymo for tbe ocoaslon A soul
cako a soul cake 1 Havo mercy on uu uuns
Man snult lor a soul-oaks I" Poonle went from
parish to parish o soulinj. as they oalled II,
that Is, begklng In a kind of ohant for soul
oakes, or anything to in ike them merry on this
eve.
Essentially oonnooted with all these oustom
are thoso bettor known ones which Burns has
so well and so faithfully described In his peem
of Halloween.
J.an I'll In twa wl1 tentlo ec,
Wha 'twas ihe wadna tell,
But this Is Ji ck and thli Is m,
She says Into hersel';
He b.eetod owre her, and she owre him,
A ihey wad ne'er mlr part,
Till fuITI ne started up the lum,
And Jean hid e'eu tiir h'art
To see't that night.
Nuts, besides being thus used for divination,
are crackod and eaten, and hence, In tho north
of England, AH Hallow Evo Is often oalled A'ul
crack Night. Apples are also extensively eaten,
tMd nimunmnt nt fruit havlnc: nrobahlv some
reforenoe to the heather, charaotor of the day,
as that or thanksgiving rortne proauco oi uie
aiann tha fortnn telllnc customs desorlbed
by Burns, besides the above are for tho girls to
pull stalks from a oorn-stallc, and ascertalii.lrom
tho presence or absenoe of the top pickle, an
Interesting point In their moral history for a
sntitartr 'amain to co to a kiln, and throwing a
blue clue Into the pot to wind It, expecting that
era finished It will oe neia duos, wnen, oy id
nuirim' who holds, a rcsuonse will ba obtalnod
dlsoloslng the name or the future husband to
eat an npple at a looking-glass, expecting to see
a vision ot the future husband peeping ovor the
shoulilor to sow liomp seea in uie yarn, say
ing, Hemp soed,1 s.iw thee, hemp seed, Isaw
thee, and her that Is to be my true love oome
after me and draw thee," expeotlng that, on
looking over the ahouldor, a vision will be ob
tulncdof the future spouse In the act of pulling
growrl hemp to win three weohta o' naetblng
In tho baru, expeotlng to see a like vision to
fathom a barley staok thrice, expecting at last
n afflhnita vrnur mistress to dlnashlrt sloeve
In a rivulet at the meeting point of the lands of
three proprietors, ana men nargit oyiue ure
tn iirr. triistlnf to see nuoh a visionary person
come In ani turn the other side to pull sulks
of dece.eed oabbages, blindfolded, without
choice, and augur, from their stralghtnes or
crookedness, the figure of tbo futuro spouse,
r-nn. tnt. Aut-rn urninn (innra u lull iuui. luo
fortune she will bring, and from the taste of
the heart, her temper Anally, to set threo
dishes on the door, one empty, one with oloan,
and one with foul water, and oause the oompany
to Bpproaoh them blindfolded and dip In a hand;
when he wh' dips In the empty one is expected
to remain unmarried, he who dips in tbe foul
one to ratrry to a widow, and he who dips in
tho clean one to marry a fem.ilo not hitherto
married. The whole of these rites are as
familiar io the Welch, Irish, and Northumbrian,
as to the Ayrshire peasantry. Many of them
are also praotlsed In Englandon St. John's Eve,
t. uo.,1 nf Jtinn.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84027008/1866-10-31/ed-1/?sp=4&q=HALLOWE%27EN+Hallowe%27en&st=text&r=-0.232,-0.073,1.465,1.465,0/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85066387/1899-10-29/ed-1/?sp=23&q=Halloween+soul+souls&st=text&r=0.644,0.913,0.698,0.505,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>is
Halloween,
Halloween.
Look
Out
'lor Your
ior Yonr
Future
Spouse
THE very mention of Halloween calls
up visions of ghosts and witches
and all kinds of uncanny things. It
ls the one night ln the year when
J^ even the uninitiated, if they are
brave enough, may converse with
spooks and hobgoblins, and may also, if
they try hard enough, send the immate
rial part of their being prancing through
space on all kinds of errands. It Is safe
to surmise that the latter privilege is not
often taken advantage fot. It is hard
enough to keep soul and body together
without hunting up excuses to separate
them. But the grand object of all the
mystic rites peculiar to Halloween is to
find out who one's future spouse will be
—that Ing a very Important question
with those who have never had one.
The most infallible of the many Infalli
ble ways by which a girl may get a
glimpse of her future husband is to re
tire in silence. That alone is hard
enough, but that is not all. She must lie
there, speechless and in the dark, until
Just before the stroke of 12, when she
must rise and, standing before the mir
ror, it an apple while combing her hair.
If she doesn't see her "future" peeping
over her shoulder it's because she is des
tined to be an old maid, or she was too
scared to look.
Another way that does not .-equire so
much courage is to write the alphabet
on twenty-six little slips of paper, one
letter on each .-lip, and then urn them
face down in a basin of water. This done,
go to bed backward and in silence. Si
lence seems to be the main requirement
in ail these endeavors to coax one's af
finity to make himself, or herself, known.
Next morning some of the letters in the
basin will be found face up and the name
thus revealed will give the desired infor
mation.
A more comfortable custom is to wet
tho sleeve of a shirt and hang it before
the fire to dry. Then lie in bed and watch
lt until midnight, when the apparition of
the future husband or wife will' appear
and turn the sleeve.
If a girl has two lovers and cannot de
cide which one to choose, she may let
fate settle the matter in the following
manner. Eat an apple and then, naming
two Of the seeds, stick one on each cheeK
and bay:
Pippin, pippin, I stick thee there.
j stick thee there.
That which is true thou mayst declare.
The one that stays tho longest is the
must faithful lover, and therefore the
most desirable.
There la a custom ln Wales on Hal-
loween of building a huge bonfire, and
wher. the fire i--: almost out each member
of the party gathered about it throws in
a white stone, marked for future identi
fication, lv the morning a search is made
in ti.e embers and if one stone is missing
It Indicates that the person who threw
it In will not live to repeat the perform-
ance the next All Lints' eve.
Many of the customs mentioned by
Robert Hums are now- obsolete, but one
stii: in vogue is that of pulling kail or
cabbage stalk. A young couple are blind
folded and then, taking each other by the
hand, they go into the garden and each
pulls a stalk at random and they return
to th.c fireside, where their prizes cause a
great deal of merriment. As the stalk is
long or short, straight or crooked, so
shall the future husband or wife be. The
quantity of earth sticking to the root in
dicates the amount of wealth and the
taste of the pith the kind of temper "tie
must expect. Finally the stalks are
placed over the door, and the christian
names of the next two entering will be
the names of the future husband and
wife.
A custom that is quite common in this
count! aiso Is to ike three saucers and
fill c:.. with clean and another with dirty
water.' The third remains empty. The
part;. wishing to know his destiny is
blindfolded and led to tie hearth, where
the saucers have been arranged. If he
dips his finger in the clean water he will
marry a maid, but If in the? dirty water a
widow will knd him to the altar. The
empty dish signifies that a life of single
CARPET TACKS SAVED THE SHIP.
BUT CAPTAIN JOSHUA SLOCUM HAD A CLOSE CALL.
Captain Joshua^Slocum. in his solitary
voyage around tne world in the sloop
Spray, found a new and exciting use for
carpet tacks. He thus describes an en
counter with the Natives of Tierra del
Fuego:
Canoes manned by -savages from Fortes
que now came ln pu-teult. The wind fall
ing light, they gained on me rapidly till
coming within hall, when they ceased
paddling, and a bow-*ggcd savage stood
up and called to me, V Yammerschooner I
yammerschooner!" whati ls their begging
term. I said "No!" M»w. I was not for
letting them know that I was alone, and
6o I stepped Into the ctpln, and. passing
through the hold, came -put at the fore
scuttle, changing my Blkhes as I went
along. That made two kien. Then the
piece of bowsprit whioh >had sawed -oit
blessedness is in store for him.
Apples and nuts play a very important
part in the mystic rites of Halloween. One
way to find out If one's sweetheart is
true Is to place three nuts upon .lie bar
of the grate or on the hearth, naming the
nuts for the loved one. If a nut cracks
or jumps, look for another sweetheart
right away, for the one you have will
surely be unfaithful. If a nut burns that
Is a sign that your affection ls reciprocated.
but if two of the ruts burn together the
young lady making the trial may as well
begin preparing her trousseau at once,
for there will surely be an early wed-
ding.
Halloween parties must always be made
as weird and uncanny as possible, and
any one with original id ie may give
them full scope on these occasions. One
very quaint affair that 1 recall may
serve as a model.
In the first place the Invitations were
most unique* Witches and goblins ran riot
over the card and the utmost secrecy in
regard to the approaching event was ex-
acted. Silence, too, was enjoined,, and
every one was veiled, and it certainly was
a very ghostly crowd that gathered
promptly at the appointed time in the
dimly lighted hallway. Suddenly the
sound of a bell -was heard, soft and- muf-
fled, as If it were high up In an old church
tower, and as it struck 9 the doors were
thrown open and the young people were
ushered into a veritable witches' den.
Death heads, made from pumpkins, with
a small lighted candle inside, grinned
from the mantel, the cornices and the
most unexpected places. Huge cobwebs,
In which were monster spiders, were
stretched across the corners and over the
mirrors. Immense bats with outspread
wings were apparently flying through the
air and great owls glared from every pos
sible resting place. In the fireplace, the
grate had been removed and in its stead
a large caldron was simmering over a pale
green blaze.
The hostess and her assistants were
witches, gowned in flowing black robes
and crownev with tall, pointed caps. In-
visible music of a weird character added
to the uncanniness of the scene. The
gentlemen were all in an adjacent room
and tbe hostess, taking a lady by the
hand, would advance with tier and knock
three times on the door with the small
broom she carried. In answer to her
knock a gentleman would appear, and
Offering the lady his arm retire to a dis
tant part of the room. When, in this
manner, the couples had all been paired
off the wltchefe wave,] their arms and
crooned in the most approved witch
manner and the screeching of the violins
outside became truly blood-curdling. Sud
denly, with a crash and a bang, the noise
ceased and the room was filled with light
When the light revealed the partners that
at Buenos Ayres, and which I had still
on board. I arranged forward on the look-
out, dressed as a seaman, attaching a line
by which I could pull It into motion.
That made three of us. and we did not
want to "yammerschooner;" but for all
that the savages came on faster than be-
fore. I saw that besides four at the pad-
dles In the canoe nearest to me. there
were others in the bottom, and that they
were shifting hands often. At eighty
yards I fired a shot across the bow of the
nearest' canoe, at which they all stopped,
but only for a moment. Seeing that they
persisted ln coming nearer, I fired the
second shot so close to the chap who
wanted to "}*ammerschooner" that he
changed hie mind quickly enough and bel-
lowed with fear. "Bueno yo via Isla,"
and sitting down in his canoe, he rubbed
his starboard cat-bead for some time. I
HERE ARE SOME ANCIENT CUSTOMS
THAT YOU WILL FIND MOST INTER-
ESTING TO EXPERIMENT WITH
fate had given each for the evening there
as a good deal of merriment. At a sig-
nal from the First Witch a couple went
Into the outer darkness to pull "kail"
stalks. Of course they had been prepared
beforehand and there was not a straight
one in the whole lot. After this ordeal
had been gone through by every one a
decrepit old hag. with a real, live owl
perched on her shoulder, entered the
room. On her arm hung a basket full
of nuts. Passing through the crowd she
gave each a nut and then.' standing by
the fireplace, she mumbled some unin-
telllgible Jargon and the room suddenly
became darkened again. Stooping over
the caldron she muttered an Incantation
and red fire Immediately blazed from Its
depths. She then tottered out of the
room, which again was illuminated as she
disappeared. The nuts, when cracked,
were found to contain a fortune, written,
on a slip of paper. For example, "You
will have many trials until the age of 30,
when good luck will come to you." The
nuts for the gentlemen were tied with
red ribbons and those for the ladies with
blue. .V
During the evening all sorts of games,
peculiar to Halloween, were added to the
programme. A stick was suspended hori-
zontally from the celling and on one end
was a short piece of lighted candle, while
an apple was stuck *on the other, and
the whole thing set whirling. A small
basket was then passed around in which
were a number of slips of paper. The
unfortunate who drew the paper with a
skull and cross-bones on It had to furnish
was thinking of a good port captain's ad
vice when I pulled the trigger, and I
must have aimed pretty straight; how
ever, a miss was as good as a mile for
Mr. "Black Pedro," as he it was, and no
other, a leader In several bloody massa
cres. He now directed the course of his
canoe for the island and the others fol
lowed him. I knew by his Spanish lingo
and by his full heard that he was the
villain I have named a renegade mongrel,
and the worst murderer in Tierra del
Fuego. The authorities had been In
search of' him for two years. The Fue
gans are not bearded. At
night, March 8, at anchor in the snug
cove at .the. Turn, every heart-beat
counted thanks. Hers I pondered on the
events of the last few days, and, strangely
enough, Instead of feeling rested from
sitting or lying down, I now began to
THE SUNDAY OALIi.
amusement for the rest by trying to get
a bite from the apple on the whirling
stick. Luckily for the girls, a man drew
the fatal slip, but before he had burned
his mustache off the First Witch took
pity on him and clapped her hands. Over
the door leading Into the dining-room a
dark, heavy portiere hung and at the slg
nal an apple rolled under the curtain and
went spinning over the floor. "It was fol
lowed by another and then ether, until
everybody had one. Knives were then
passed around and a merry half-hour was
spent In peeling the apples and throwing
the unbroken skin over the shoulder In
such a manner as to form the Initial of
the future husband or wife, In one of
the apples a needle was Imbedded in the
core, indicating that the finder would
enjoy a domestic or wedded life. Another
contained a pen. foretelling a literary
career, and in still another a tiny pencil
was buried, signifying a life devoted to
art. In a fourth a small piece of wood
was hidden on which the word "music"
had been written.
A few moments before midnight the
merry-makers were all taken out the
kitchen door and separated Into two
groups, the girls on one side and the
gentlemen on the other. At the first
stroke of twelve both groups started and
ran, one going one way and the other in
the opposite direction, all to meet at the
front door. The first couple to reach the
goal would be the first to marry— not each
other, necessarily— and the last to arrive
were doomed to a lonely existence
When the race was over, the breathless
feel .laded and worn; but a hot meal of
venison stew soon put me right, so that
I could sleep. As drowsiness came on I
first sprinkled the deck with the tacks
that my old friend Sambllch had given
me, and then I turned in.
Now, it Is well known that one cannot
istep on a tack without saying something
about it. A pretty good Christian will
whistle when he steps on the "commercial
end" of a carpet tack; a savage will howl
and claw the alr, and that was just what
happened that night about 12 o'clock
while I- was asleep in the cabin, where
the savages thought they "had me,"
sloop and all. They changed their minds,
however, when they stepped on deck, for
then they thought that I or somebody
else had them. I had no need of a dog;
they howled like a pack of hounds. I
had hardly uso for a gun. They jumped
pell-mell, some into their canoes and
some. Into the sea, to cool off, I suppose,
and there was a deal of free language
over It as they went. I fired the rascals
a salute of several guns t when I came on
deck, to -let them know that I was at
home, and then I turned in again, feeling
sure that- 1 should not be disturbed any
more by people who left In bo great a
hurry.
laughing crowd was summoned to supper,
and there another surprise awaited them.
The decorations in the dining-room were
red. even the tablecloth being of the same
brilliant hue.' Over the center of the
round table a huge owl. with outspread
wings, was suspended from the ceiling.
In its claws it held the ends of four long
red ribbons, the other ends of which were
held in the corners of the room, near the
celling, by bats, lizards and spiders. The
shade on the lamp was red crepe paper,
THE BOERS AS THEY REALLY ARE,
By MISS SANNIE KRUGER, NIECE OF OOM PAUL KRUGER.
Continued from Page Twenty-one.
the wedding customs. The suitor takes
the girl of his choice to some lachergoot
(confectionery). If she refuses the gift
that ends the courtship. If not he sits in
the midst of the coffee-drinking family
for an hour or more. Finally' he Is left
alone with the girl of his choice. T But the
wise tant according to custom puts a
limit on the length of his visit.- She marks
the wax candle with a needle, meaning
that i the visit must only last until the
candle burns to the mark.
I s could tell you of many more quaint
customs, but It was not for: that- I under
took this task. Rather _to convince you
that i a Boer girl ls not a semi-savage.
on which had been applied owls and bats
of some black material. The punch was
red, so was the frosting on the cake—
which, by the way, was crescent-shaped
and surmounted by a tiny doll, dressed all
in red. as a witch. The souvenirs were
also small witch-dolls for the ladies and
owls for the men, both of which, on In
vestigation, proved to be bonbon boxes.
In Ireland, the observance of Hallow
een assumes. In many respects, a religious
character. It is a custom In many dis
My English always surprises people Into
comment. True, I speak with less accent
than most Boer girls, having a natural
aptitude for languages and having trav
eled so much.
But the rising generation of Boers are
ail well educated. Both English and
Dutch are taught In the schools. Oom
Paul understands English as well as I do
myself. Many times when 'playing or
dancing for him I would forget and make
some remark in English. He would al
ways chide -me for it, saying. "I could
speak English as well as a rooinek (red
neck— Dutch for Englishman), but I never
forget I am a Boer."
Like all Boer girls I am an excellent
■hot and I fervently wish that I were
trlcts to bake what are called "soul
cakes" on that day, which are given to the
poor, who go from door to door begging.
The gift of a cake is always accompanied
with a request to pray for the souls of the
dead. The recipient of these "soul cakes"
is generally very profuse In his promises
to pray dnd calls down the blessings of
heaven on everything he or she can think
of. Another custom is to burn a lighted
candle in every wind in the house,
which gives a very picturesque effect
along the country roads.
There ls a custom among the poorer
classes In England, also, or begging on
Halloween, for what Is known there as
"dole bread." In several districts a fan-
tastic arrangement, called "Old Hob," ls
carried about from house to house, ac
companied by a crowd of young people,
singing doggerel begging rhymes. Old
Hob consists of a skeleton of a horse's
head, mounted on a broomstick, and with
a sheet wrapped about and concealing the
person who ls carrying It-
Shaw, in his history of the Province of
Moray, considers the festivities of Hal-
loween as a sort of harvest-home rejoic-
ing— a thanksgiving for the safe ingather
ing of the produce of the fields. What
ever may have been the original motive
for this "gathering together of the clans"
on the eve of All Saints, the young people
who make merry nowadays have only one
object In view— to discover, lf possible,
their affinity, to find that mysterious he
or she for whom we are all of us con
tinually seeking. Sometimes these "affin
ities" are a little careless and don't pair
off just right, so the boys and girls who
try their fate on this next Halloween
must not neglect the warnings and
prophecies which that night of mystery
will surely bring.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84026749/1916-11-04/ed-1/?sp=3&q=House+White+Halloween&st=text&r=0.641,0.049,0.325,0.235,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Halloween Raiders Steal
Qate Wilson Swung On
STAUNTON, "Va., Nov. 4.-The front
gate of the "Little White House" here,
where President Wilson was born, was
pilfered by Halloween raiders. Oldest
Inhabitants tell of the time little Wood
row swung on the self-same rfate.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1915-10-24/ed-1/?sp=45&q=Hallowe%27en&st=text&r=-0.304,0.091,1.416,1.025,0/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85042462/1909-10-24/ed-1/?sp=38&q=Hallowe%27en+HALLOWE%27EN+celebrations+celebration&st=text&r=0.11,0.858,0.269,0.195,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>NOW approaches the witch's!
hour, when, hand in band with'
.ia<*k-o'-lantern, she is prepared to
scamper across the curtain for
an interlude of frolic.
The black cat is with us
again, and the bat, and the owl. The
cauldron bubbles, the chestnuts barn
upon the hearth, the Hallowe'en cake
gives up its ghostly prophecy of wealth,
matrimony or a life of single blessedness, i
In a thousand boarding schools a thou-
sand girls will creep down the cellar|
stairs holding a mirror and a candle as
the hour strikes twelve, looking fearfully,
for the reflected face which is to tell'
them of the future, and in more than a
thousand apartment houses—where there
are no cellar stairs—young women will|
eat an apple before a mirror and hold a I
candle by whose light they expect to see
that same prophetic vision.
If it weren't for jack o' lantern the
celebration of Hallowe'en might be;
rather a gloomy affair, for looking into|
the future in darkened rooms and watch-1
ing one's fellow chestnut hop away from!
one on the hearth are not always cheer
ing diversions; but jack-o'-lantern, the
Uing of the night, is the jolliest of pre
siding geniuses, and, besides, there is
the Hallowe'en feast, a most temptine j
repast, to keep one's spirits from flag
ging in the midst of the general unloos
ing of the black arts.
HALLOWE'EN 'nativities are always
very popular with girls, and they are
possible for every one, for the cele-,
'.ration of the night has one great advan-j
tage in the fact that its m}'stic rites and]
ceremonies can be jusC as well and hap
pily performed by three or four persons as
by a large number. Naturally the sort of
Hallowe'en entertainment which Is ar-,
ranged for a small gathering is not satis
factory for a large one. It has usually
been found that there is more fun to lie
had !.v Koing through the oldtitne Hal
lowe'en rites quite ueriously when the
party is small, while for a large affair
this sort of diversion is hardly sufficiently!
general, and instead there is dancing, pair
sihly Hallowe'en cotillon and a supperj
with quaint and grotesque favors.
Masquerade parties are also popular for
Hallowe'en, especially in girls' boarding
schools, and afford r.o end of fun if the
masks are kept on until the close of the
evening, so that the identity of the
dancers cannot he positively known.
There are so many Hallowe'en symbols;
that whether an ordinary dance, a cotillon
or a masquerade is being arranged there
is abundance of picturesque material upon'
which one can draw for decorative ma
terials, favurs, costumes, &c. No Hal-:
lnwe'en masque is complete without its! 1
witch, its jack-o'-lantern, black cat, owl
and bat, nil to be represented in some way
or other by the men or girls taking part.
Brownies are also Hallowe'en characters.
Goblins and fairies of all kinds are suita
ble guests for a Hallowe'en frolic.
IV/1 OST successful was a Hallowe'en'
1 (masquerade given ut a girls' school i
last year. Fairyland wus boldly!
raided for the characters, and every girl j
was asked to come as some one of "the
little people," either as a historical char
acter or as some particular sort of a I
sprite. The result was not only most
amusing but beautiful as well, for there
were elves and pixies, water sprites, tire
fairies, cloud fairies, quaint gnomes,
naughty brownies, sharp chinned witches,
&c. Queen Mali. Oberon, Titania and
Turk were all there, and there was a
most charming dryad, who set up her!
How to Make a Motoring Veil
EYEKY one has a motoring veil, and
many and varied aye the kinds used.
Few women or girls can be said to
look really pretty in one of these veils,
but there are many degreee of attractive-
Beu about them, and still greater differ
ences of convenience, which, after all, is I
the really important point. Some are I
merely long pieces of chiffon tied on in
liny way, iind they frequently blow off
in a high wind, so it is really worth while
to make one properly.
An English motoring veil which is i
satisfactory is made in the following
way:- Buy two yards of chiffon or chiffon
cloth and cut it in half lengthwise from
one ,-nd in a point twenty inches from
the other end. Hem it across the two
pieces of the loner end and all around
the cut edges; the outer edges will, of
course, lie selvages. Then, where the slit!'
stops, it must Be closely buttonholed to
pn >*nt tearing further.
The upper end may be arranged in two|
nis. .Lho simplest and easiest is to j'
r it up lightly, sewing the gathers
together at the edges; then sew over the
g.i thers a large Hat button mould covered
with the chiffon. A rather neater linflatter way to finish this top is with a j
small thick ring, but it is mow trouble.!;
In this case the chiffon must be turned
over the ring like a hem and sewed down, r
;iinl as the whole width of chiffon must i
be .sewed on a small ring it is not very i
easy to do. Tho effect, however, is worth
the trouble if one has some skill in
sewing,
Tho veil 1h put on with this gathered i
centre near the front of the hat (or head j
if worn without a hat), The beginning
of tin- ,-lii i s ;ii the back of the neck, i
and the two ends are. drawn around thejl
tree in a corner— it was made of paper
bark emerged at intervals through
a cunningly concealed door.
The witches told wonderful fortunes
for everybody, and a large witch, who
occupied a central post, stirred a cauldron
from which she continually distributed
favors.
The gnomes «nd brownies roasted the
chestnuts on the large hearth, and the I
fairies danced around their favorite
teacher and presented her with three
magical gifts— Italian coral to keep
off the evil eye, a good luck penny us a
foundation for her fortune and a pair of
rose colored glasses, through which she
might always see the bright side of life.
These fairies were not the ordinary
tarletan and spangled creatures that we
have grown accustomed to hear desig
nated by that name, but were, as far as
possible, faithful reproductions of the
little people of famous fictiou, the creat
ures of the Irish woods and bogs, the
Scotch Highlands and the German forests
as they have been depicted by poets,
painters and prose writers. It took some
trouble to evolve the costumes, but not
as much expense as might be thought on
first consideration, for many of the cos
tumes were made entirely of crepe paper,
and in all of them this material entered j
largely.
Black paper was most effective for the!
witch's costume and for that of the owl
and black cat Poor pussy had quite a
difficult time —one of the smaller girls was j
chosen for this —because the other
guests at the frolic insisted on her going
on all fours a large part of the time,
which, in spite of her gymnastic training,
was not altogether agreeable.
EQUALLY amusing is a dance where
the guests (ill appear as fruits of the)
autumn. There must of course be
some liberty permitted in this sort of
character costuming, for while it is com»
paratively easy for a properly built young
person to appear as an ear of corn,
it is rather diflicult for her or him to
assume the exact proportions of a toma
to. A lettuce girl, with full shaded green
skirts of crinkled paper and some grace
fully arranged lettuce leaves for bodice
and headdress, is a most fascinating
creature, and the grape costume, the au
tiimn leaf costume, the pumpkin vine cos
tume, &c, are all most attractive. It is
usually considered wise for the girl to
select fruit and vegetable costumes which
are pretty and becoming, while the boys,
with their customary gallantry, volunteer
fur the grotesque parts.
Squashes, radishes, potatoes and ap
ples all fall to the lot of the boys. With
the vegetable throng there should min
gle a sufficient sprinkling of the tradi
tional Hallowe'en characters. Nothing!
could be more amusing than the pairing!
off at such an assemblage. .Miss Lettuce
and jack-o'-lantern dancing together, fol
lowed by the witcli and the tomato boy, I
thi; grape girl and the owl. picturesque 1
Miss Autumn Leaf nn«l a jolly brownie,
make up a procession of quaint contrasts.
Pumpkin vines and autumn leaves are
charming celebrations for large rooms in j
which Hallowe'en frolics are to be held, j
and thero are also paper draperies j
stamped with appropriate designs which*
come especially for the walls and tables.!
Large witches' black cats and owls made
of black paper are used here and there
among the decorations or perched on
chandeliers, lump shades or over door
ways, Jaek-o'-lunterns, real or imita
tion, are the most popular lights for the j
festivities. If real they may be set ou i
the table or hung in different quarters of
neck, knotted in front and allowed to
bang dowu, or put arouud the neck v
second time when a little .extra warmth
ia needed.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85042462/1907-11-03/ed-1/?sp=32&q=Hallowe%27en+celebrated+celebration&st=text&r=0.807,0.583,0.333,0.241,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>OUR SPECIAL FEATURE PAGE
nO holiday on the calendar deyeu^.
more for Its charm upon tradtlon and
the customs handed down from genera
tion to generation- than does that fateful
night of mirth and mystery Hallowe'en.
Most of oar American holidays com
memorate historic events within the past
entnxy and half and consequently can
not of course, have any of the charac
teristics of ancient ceremonial. Even
Christmas has, in Its observance, been
modernised ont of all semblance of the
old-tfme celebration. Hallowe'en, how
•r, not only retains Its time-honored
significance and long-established ritual
trot finds Its chief attraction In these re
minders of bygone periods.
The festival of the night of October 81
has a number of different designations,
though none are so commonly nsed as
Hallowe'en. The others are All Hallow
¦yen, Nutcrack Night and Snapapple
Night, the latter two being derived of
course from practices associated with
the occasion. Hallowe'en derives Its
most common name as the eve or vigil
of All Saints' or All Hallows Day (No
vember 1). From time out of mind this
has been heralded as a night when
witches, devils and other mlschlef-mak-
Ing beings go abroad on their baneful
midnight errands. By a strange coinci
dence, however, this same night Is sap
posed to be devoted by the fairies to a
grand anniversary celebration.
The traditions of Hallowe'en also teach
that on no 4ther night In the twelve
month do sach supernatural Influences
prevail as after dark on the final day of
October. According to ancient beliefs the
spirits of the dead then wander about and
In some Instances the spirits of living per
sons have conferred upon them the tem
porary power to Join the ghostly clan.
Persons who have nad the good fortune
to be born on October 31 are especially
likely to be warned or advised by the
elves on each recurring anniversary of
Saint Matrimony is the patron saint
of Hallowe'en and Indeed this autumn
holiday Is best known as the night of all
nights for peering Into the future and
especially for discovering just what sort
of husband or wife fate has selected for
each unmarried participant In the rites.
It Is this function of the holiday which
helps to keep Its observance alive with
the young people of the nation and not a
few of their elders who are yet youthful
In spirit. Not only are the mysterious
spirits that are abroad on Hallowe'en
supposed to be Infallible In their verdicts
but it Is also of manifest advantage that
they demand neither fee nor reward for
piercing the veil that hides the future.
The performance of some very simple
ceremony Is all that Is exacted of the
curious young man or woman who would
learn Interesting particulars regarding the
destined life-partner.
The origin of Hallowe'en seems to be
hidden In 'an Intermingling of classic
mythology and Christian superstitions.
The plan of making nnts and apples con
spicuous in the Hallowe'en festivities Is
traced back to the custom of the ancient
Romans to hold on November 1 a feast
to Pomona, the goddess of fruits and
seeds, at which time there was a formal
opening of the stores of eatables laid
up In summer for use during the winter.
On this same date occurred the great
autumn festival to the sun with which the
Druids or ancient Celts celebrated thanks
giving for their harvest and It was the
belief of the Druids that 'on the eve of
their holiday the present Hallowe'en
the Lord of Death summoned those
wicked souls that had within the year
been condemned to henceforth occupy the
bodies of animals.
The people of England have long set
store by an elaborate observance of Hal
lowe'en, but even antedating their al
legiance was that of the Irish. In the
Emerald Isle It was the custom from
the earliest days for each household to
set out on this holiday the best viands
It could afford, apples and nuts being in
evitable features of the menu. In not a
few Instances peasants went from house
to house collecting breadcake, bntter,
cheese, eggs and other eatables suitable
for a feast. Indeed, throughout Great
Britain bread or cake has long been asso
ciated with the Hallowe'en feast, and
even today In many English households a
cake Is baked for each member of the
family. An early Hallowe'en observance
was that of ringing the church bells all
night long, but a stop was put to this by
King Henry VIII.
As hasNbeen said, many of the features
of the Hallowe'en program In auclent
times have been continued to this day
but for the most part tho customs which
were once ceremonies of belief now
observed only In jest. Hallowe'en being
the first of the autumn and winter holi
days and, for the young people, the first
break In the school year Is Invariably wel
comed with especial enthusiasm. The
circumstance that Hallowe'en Is not a
national holiday does not In the least
a large round table and an oblong table
with gilt trimmings.
Various schemes for obtaining matri
monial forecasts on Hallowe'en have been
handed down to the present generation.
The roasting of nuts is an essential pre
lude to most of them. Some Inquisitive
maidens nre wont to place a number of
nuts, each bearing the name of a lover,
on the bars of h grate or among the em
bers. According to the ritual If a nut
crneks or jumps the lover will prove un
faithful whereas if It begins to blaze or
burn he hss regard for the person making
the test. If a nut burns quietly and
brightly especial sincerity of affection
Is supposedly Indicated. Similarly If nuts
named for a girl and her lover burn In
unTson an early wedding Is to be ex
pected.
Apples vie with nuts as Hallowe'en vehi
cles for discovering the Intentions of
Cupid. Indeed one of the best known
ruses, and perhaps the one most generally
practiced at the general time Is that In
which the credulous maiden eats an apple
before a looking glass while combing her
hair, confident that If directions be fol
lowed explicitly the face of her destined
conjugal partner will be seen In the mir
ror as though peeping over her shoulder.
Equally well known Is the scheme wliere-
I'v any maiden may find out the first
letter of the name of her future hus
band by peeling an apple, taking the
paring by one end and after swinging
It three times around her head allowing
It to fall In whatever fashion It may.
It must be confessed that some slight
stretch of Imagination may be necessary
to construe the position of the paring as
indicating a desired letter.
There has been transplanted to. the United
States from Scotland another means of
peeping into the matrimonial lottery. By
this plan the young women go hand In
haud, bliudfolded, or at least with eyes
closed, to the cabbage patch and each
pulls the first plant met with. Earth on
the root of the cabbage thus selected
signifies dowry. The shape and size of
the vegetable denote the appearance and
size of the future spouse and the taste
of the heart and stem Indicate his dis
position. Nor Is all the Hallowe'en prog
nosticating for the benefit of the fair
sex. There have been designed for ardent
swains numerous forms of divination, the
best known of which Is that whereby the
smitten youth descends cellar stairs
with a randle In one hand and a mirror
in the other, hoping to have the face of a
sweetheart reflected back to him from
the glass.
All the Hallowe'en pranks above men
tioned and a host of others are intro
duced as adjuncts of the Hallowe'en par
ties which now constitutes one of tho
most popular forms of entertaining in
this country. That tradition has decreed
the occasion one of mystery as well as a
night of jollity and laughter paves the
way for unique entertainments and many
quaint conceits In the line of amusements
have been devised by resourceful hosts
and hostesses. Hallowe'en has become
especially popular at schools and colleges,
as a brief season given over to the pranks
of the students. Particularly Is there a
fantastic observance of the holiday at
girls' boarding schools and women's col
leges.
Novelty Is the keynote of everything
connected with a Hallowe'en festivity.
Like as not the Invitations, menu cards,
tally cards, etc. are bespattered with
representations of witches riding brooms,
blinking owls, broad-winged bats and
pumpkins while for decorative purposes
there are pressed Into service a variety
of nature's vivid- hued products such as
cornstalks, pumpkins, carrots, russet oak
leaves and green plno boughs. Finally
the, refreshments, which are an lndlspen
sable feature, Include apples, nuts, grapes
and other autumn delicacies.
Since mystic rites are to be essayed and
ghost stories and other spooky subjects
are likely to be among the topics of con
versation, It Is not only permissible but
appropriate that there should be no bril
liant Illumination of the scene of a Hal
lowe'en party and this enables the use of
candles set In hollowed carrots or the em
ployment of Jack-o-lanterns.
Certain well-known American host
esses, famous as the originators of oddi
ties, have given Hallowe'en entertain
ments in barns and attics and In one In
stance a cellar was utilised, black drap
eries and the symbol of the skull and
cross-bones adding to the "creepy" at
mosphere. Highly popular as Hallowe'en
entertainments are, masquerade parties
of one kind or another and shadow pan
tomimes have come Into extensive vogue
In recent years. Some of the games which
are now regarded as indispensable to a
Hallowe'en frolic have no significance as
matrimonial barometers. Foremost among
these Is the prank of ducking for apples.
The apples are set afloat In a tub and
each person essays to catch one of the
floating prises with the teeth, bis hands
being tied behind him. The popping of
corn at an open fire, fortune telling and
other old-fashioned diversions are also re
vived for the benefit of the younger gen
eration on Hallowe'en.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85052116/1905-10-26/ed-1/?sp=7&q=HALLOWEEN+Halloween+Hallow+Hallowmas&st=text&r=-0.177,-0.064,1.353,1.353,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>HALLOWEEN
is 4
XXSXXW K sssssssssssSssssssss
Polythofstn having many phases
hnd also many festivals Among the
Celts who Inhabited ancient Brkain
two of tho host Important of these
fell In the early parts of May and of
November and were called Ualtnno
or Dcltoln festivals a name signify
ing Sun god and the riles with
which they wore celebrated really
possessed many of tho characteris
tics of the fetes of those very Interest
Ing people Ihe Fire Worshipers At
the beginning of a Boltoln colebra
tlon all tho fires of the community
were extinguished not so much M
ono live coal must bo left I among the
ashes of the chlmney4hon with
ceremony or Bong and sacrifice the
priests kindled the necdflro by the
friction of n rope drawn rapidly
about a post From the sacred spark
thus obtalnediian altar flro was built
from which all tile fires In the coun
tryside were relighted This need
lire was believed tp have the pow
to scans away witches dsvlls fairies
and the dcmonsvof dlucitx hat lurk
ed about human habitations within
the magic Circle qf Us Vght no evil
spirit might work Its fatal spell
There Is nothing1 lo ivftlcn people
cling with more per hMiicy than lo
their supcritltlonn aftd tlvi t praitlrcs
that pertain thereto arci so t wait
that when tho early Christians began
to propagate their religion in leah
en lands they wisely mnd nu light
on tho fete days of the pcopUs tiny
wished to convert inwrougfit rs
they wero with fanatical Miperstl
tlon rather did they lack lo Chris
tlanlze these days by associating
them with some of their own f cull
vats gradually letting alto snctcd
rights supersede tie ici stn rues
Thus tho heathen YuHtdfc became
the holy season of Chijlbtinas tho
springtime Qelteln was nib de to corn
clde with Easter and the autumnal
one fortunately falling on Nov 1
was transformed Into one of the most
beautiful festivals of the religion of
Calvary Hallowmas or AllSaints
day But though the day thus lost
Its heathen slgnlflcancer nany of Us
heathen beliefs clung tdtll l uud the
echo of these weakenddby clvlllza
lion have come down thefiges tons
Halloween was the eve ot Hallow
mas and on that night ghosts gob
llns witches and Alrles were belteV
edto be turned leos 1 uPon tho Perth
tit a ifs ati3itl na v tl l that hid
tho futtife Jung so waveringly that
one by proper signs allli devlcjs
might get a peep bohlnd lt Thus It
came to be the favorite night tor
tho testing fortune
In Scotland where the 1e1l01n 1
perstltlohs smoldered tong girls
wound tholr clews of yarmbut of win
tows expecting to find their future
husbands holding the ends and both
lads and lassies stole out In tho darK
to BOW the hemp seed that a future
spouse would como behind nnd hal
row For song unexplained reaso
haps sonic faint faint thread of
heredity running backward through
tho ramifications of tlmo and nations
to tho story of tho garden of Eden l
the njiple has always boon considered
a fateful fruit big with prophecy of
things to come In many tests of
fortune does It play a part Eat one
before a mirror inn darkened room
on Halloween and your future I
spouso will look over your shoulder
Throw tho pool over your left shoul
der mill It will form the Initial of tho
one you ore to Quarry Cut It open
and take from It two I seeds stick
theso on either eyelid Vnd watcll to
sco which will stick the longer for
that ono Is to win In loves race A
mischievous girl will bear close
watching III this test or slit may
help on the CRUSOOt her favorite
s ultor by winking oft his rival Then
them Is tho timehonored way of
counting tho apple seed One I
love two I love three i 1 love l I say
four I lovo with all my heart and
jflyo1 cast away If l thoro arc five
fired a girl may soften the prophecy
Ip her sweetheart by the lines of the
x
song
UBut counting secds Is not i t tho way
A bodys love to ProvoM
For tho very ono I caso away
Is Just the ono Move I
Nuts also become4 fortunetollers
on tho mystic night of Hollowoon
the prettiest test being that of burn
Ing them on a hot shoveUnftor nam
lag them tho quickly burning ones
arc tho changeable lovers thin slow
ly I burning ones are the mon who will
bo constant and true The whlto off
a hardboiled eggAllcd with salt
and oaten on retiring alsobocomes
a rovonlor of destiny for In dreams
tho future spouse will bring n cup of
water tto the thirsty sleeper For
Halloween parties the Fortune Hags
and the Candle Trials are very pretty I
For the first two baga nre prepared
filled with answers to the questions
When will I bo married 1 The
more ludicrous the n answers which
are to be read aloud the mow fun
they will evoke Fon thf candle
tesr use II ho colored tailors for I
Christmas trees Two nets must he
jirbvldcil one for tho girls and one
Ifor Ut boys Each cnuclle is nun
bored by n small card tied to It
Front other fortune baS8ono for
boys and one for glrll1lhe guests
draw larger cards which are mini
bored on one side and on tho other
bear a fortune verso Each I guest
matches the number of this card
with the card on the candles Thci
the lapers arc all lighted at n bIg
necdflre Candle provided for the
purpose and tho guests gathcrltij
In a circle read their destinies by
the light of the colored tapers For
Instance No 1 may bo a green can
Alt and the holder may read
Your sweet heart will Jilt you Just at
suro
As this green candle burns down
And youll waste your wealth and
live and dio L
The crustiest bach In tho town
Or a girl may hold this one
Hercfe a1 fortune taper green
Uy its twinkling light Is seen
Many things to come to you
Bags with mortoy bursting through
Beaux aplenty to your string
And a goldcn wedding ring
Pink calldleq
If pink Is tho candle youvo chosen
tonight
Theres n marriage for money and
riches In sight
Red candle
This Is the red candles prophecy
Youll boss him whosoeer ho be
When you put on your bridal wreath
Youll rake tho bit between your
0
teeth
White candle
Many good i things for your future
life
This moonwhite taper shows
A bank account and a coach and four
And a wife with aturncdup nose
Or
You hold tonight a candle white
And by the radlanco shed
A lover true will come to you
Ere many moons arc sped
These verses may be legion After
these have been read aloud a for
tuneteller dressed ns a Salem witch
will keep tho company in excellent
spirits for a time A fitting close to
a Halloween evening is the telling
of ghost stories by the company In
turn the lights being tho first extln
guished and saucers of salt anti
ted with alcohol placed on the floor
In tho middle of the clrclo the
weird flickering of Ythose ghost
lights glvosan uncanny aspect to the
faces and figures of the company
Another way to bass the evening sa
ghost dance to which tho guests
all como Shrouded In sheets and
masked In white In imltatldn of tho
spirits supposed to bo abroad on
Halloween</text>
      </result>
       <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83025121/1895-11-29/ed-1/?sp=7&q=celebrations+Halloween+celebrated&st=text&r=0.098,0.35,1.011,0.731,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>r
j
'TIS FAIRIES' MGHT.
ALL Halloween, when to youb
sight may be, i ween,
BernUM Tour Fntnrv Spouse's Fsw, la
All IU Cgllneas and Grace That's 'What
Think In the "Anld but
Hardly, I Trow, on This Sldn the Sea.
A Scotch writer who contributed an
article to an American newspaper about
Halloween last year declared himself
"very much impressed by the almost
universal observance of Halloween and
its old customs in America." Ho added
that the forms most taken by tho observance
of tho nigh there were, and equally
to his interest, rather Scotch-Irish
than English. Farther on ho says that
"Halloween has always been and still
trrmcG at lugging or gates.
is the feast of the year, when gentle
and simple meet and enjoy themselves
together, irrespective of social barrier
and caste, so rigorously observed on
other occasions.
This view of Halloween will perhaps
be entirely new to a majority of those
who read this writing. Halloween is
observed in the United States, to be
sure, and perhaps in some parts of the
country with some of the same superstition
that marks its observance among
tbo&e who dwell on the British isles,
but this is rarely the fact among those
of the 'old time American stock. This
is especially true of those descended
from the Puritans. Thoso sturdy old
iconoclasts cast out all sorts of belief
regarding saints' days and pagan festi
vals, including even Christmas and the
Eastertide, in their prohibition of celebrations
that savored of either the Roman
church or the Druids. Tho observance
of Halloween is a mixture of
both, and I have no doubt that there
are many thousands in the United
States, some of whom will read these
words, who were in as dense ignorance
of Halloween in their childhood as
was a business man of one of our
largest cities with whom I converted
the other daj.
"I never heard of Halloween" at all
when I was a boy, said this man. ""'1
never heard of Easter either until I
was 17. of 18. Full knowledge of both
did not come to me till I 'went away to
school' with money I had earned work
ing in the hayneld and the apple orchard,
and then I read their history in
the 'Book of Days.' But I knew all
about Paas (I used to spell it Pees) and
cabbage night. I used to hide eggs in
the haymow for days, waiting for the
first, and the standing cabbages and the
winging gates of the neighbors used to
suffer on the second, I tell you.
Cabbage night! That's the title the
American boy applies to Halloween.
And a right lusty, sturdy savage the
American boy is like to be on that night
It must be confessed that the joys of
cabbage night, its breathless exertions
and runnings here and there in the darkness,
its pulling of bells and knocking
at doors, its lifting and lugging of gates,
its stretching of ropes across paths to
trip the unwary, all seem rather flat
and silly to the man whose hair is getting
gray and who is beginning to be
fat or rheumatic or perhaps both. But
they weren't flat and silly some 20 or
SO years ago, were they, old fellow? Do
you rememberwhat fun you had stealthily
tying two cabbages to Deacon Ellis'
front door knob on cabbage night
in 186? or 1868? How you then knocked
at the door and dodged behind the
big cherry tree in the yard where Tom
Waters was hidden before you? How
you then saw the young theological student,
who was "settin up" with the
deacon's pretty niece, when he opened
A LITTLE SERMOX.
the door? How he was so angry when
he saw the joke that he began to say
something that sounded very much like
a "big, big DV How you snickered so
loud that he heard you, and darting out
into the darkness caught you both and
dragged you into the parlor, where he
stood you, nearly helpless with mortification,
before his sweetheart, preached
you a little sermon, smiling the while,
which sounded very funny to the young
lady, but very serious to you? And how
at the windup he confessed that he had
himself done such things when he was
boy, but thought them rude and suggested
that in future you spend
een going about restoring unhinged
gates to their own and t'ie commission
of other similar good ikeds?
If that reminiscence be not one of
yours, then one somewhat similar probably
is unless yon were a city boy, as I
was not. I suppose there is no docbt
that town born lads havo quite as much
fun in their weak way and manner as
counrry lads, bet I must confess I have
never been able to understand how.
It is not patting it inaccurately, I
imagine, to say that Halloween, observed
according to the methods that
are time honored across the ocean, is a
new institution, comparatively speaking
at least, in America. It was brought
here by settlers who came latter than
tho Puritans, by immigrants who came
to better their condition and not for
liberty of conscience. In some sectiocs
where the population is largely made
up of this latter element the old English,
Scotch and Irish legends undoubtedly
obtain, yet it is extremely doubtful
if there is one-tenth of tho Halloween
superstition anywhere in the
United States that exists in the mother
country unless it is among tho negroes
of tho south, where, since the extreme
observances of the occasion resemble
those of the "voodoo doctors" so closely,
it has been completely assimilated
into the system of superstitions held by
the children of Africa.
A sort of half belief in Halloween
superstition has been widely disseminated
by the boarding schools of the
land, and it is safo to asmno that there
is far more of Halloween observance
among the children and young folks of
the rich and well to do than among
those whose parents work for wages
throughout the land. It is quito customary
nowadays for parents to plan
Halloween parties for their children, at
which many of the sports of tho season
are entered into.
Bobbing for apples, throwing apple
peelings over one's shoulder to see what
initials the peelings will form, pouring
melted lead into water for a similar
purpose and the like are favorito diversions
at these little parties. As diversions
they are harmless, but in all seriousness
the inculcation of superstitious at Halloween,
or any other time, for that matter,
should be avoided, for the human
creature is desperately inclined to be
superstitious, no matter how modern,
and there is nothing more torturing
in life than to bo a victim of some belief
in the significance of omens and
signs and presentiments, even if the victim
knows in his inmost heart that
there is nothing at all to justify such
belief.
As a study the folklore of Halloween
is most interesting. The origin of
the observance is unmistakably Druid-
'SisHaB:
iw.sn S'aUL.
jn? n isi.
two nAZL snrrs i threw bto the flame
ical, and, although the date was shifted
to that of All Souls' night when Christianity
usurped heathenism among the
Teutons, the Anglo-Saxons and the Celts,
there is nothing about its legends and
ceremonies that does not savor of the
pagan. Pulling the kail (or cabbage) to
find if one's spouse to be will be stout
or lean is one, and from this no
doubt came the hilarious phantasies of
the American cabbage night. Hazel nuts
and chestnuts play an important part in
English Halloween observances. The
poet Gray tells of this most delightfully
in these lines:
Two hazl csu I threw Into the flame.
And tOTOch nut 1 cvb a sweetheart's name.
ThU with the loudest bounce me Bare amazed.
That in J flame of brightest color
As bl&zea nut so marth7p&rtsion grow.
For 'twas thine own that did so brightly glow.
In the old days it was believed that
witches did travel abundantly on Halloween.
The fairies, too, did then disport
themselves most friskily, and spells
then worked that worked no other night.
The burning bf bonfires was general in
Wales and Scotland on Halloween, and
lads and maybe lasses, too, then went
out masked and dressed in garments of
quaint design.
-There were also many games on Halloween
in other times of which nothing
is preserved, save in tradition.
Some of these games were such a3 would
not be admissible now, for the refine
ment of those old days was much less
than that of today, no matter how they
may have excelled the present in other
directions. Those games which had for
their object the discovery of a future
husband's or wife's identity were naturally
most popular. Here is a recipe
for securing an answer to the question
(apposed to bo most important to every
girL It is from an ancient publication,
entitled "The Tree Fortune Teller:"
"To know whether a woman will
have the man she wishes get two
lemon peels. Wear them all day, one in
each pocket. At night rub the four posts
of the bedstead with them. If she is to
succeed, the person will appear in her
sleep and present her with a couple of
lemons. If not, there is no hope."
Here is one from the latitude of Chicago
It i adapted to city observance,
but it is not warranted: Fill
your mouth with salt and run around
the block, when your true love will of
a surety show himself.
Eva Lnvett has put this one into
rhyme. It is an old favorite with all
Halloween devotees:</text>
      </result>
       <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn82003389/1868-11-11/ed-1/?sp=2&q=Hallow+ALL+HALLOW+EVE&st=text&r=0.507,0.142,0.676,0.489,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>ALL HALLOW EVE.
The Sast of Octdber, the eve of All Saints I
Day, has been for ages a timeof festivities,
peculiar costumes and ceremonies, in the
old countries, but of these there are few
traces in our country. It is a season when
fairies and wood-land elves come out in
force, play pranks on passers by, dance
merrily on the bill sides, and perform fa
vors for those who have the good fortune
to meet with them and fall into their good
graces The weather had been very wet
and disagreeable for some days, but on
Saturday it cleared up cool and pleasant.
SIn "the good old days" the young folks
gathered in the evening to enjoy the plays
and stories of the time. One legend di
Srects the young girls who wish to know
who their future husbands will be, to go
to a grocery store and there steal a her
B ring; taking it out of the brine it must be
roasted without washing or cleaning, and
e eaten up. They must then go backwards
s to bed and drink no water. During the
Snight the future partner of their joys will
Sappear and offer them water from a clear
running brook. Many a bonnie lass bas
taken her supper of salted herring and
gone to rest, to dream that she was laying
Sin the shade of some favorite tree. with a
Smurmuring brook close by, the cool waters
of which were temptingly near her parched
lips. yet be3yond the most frantic efforts to
.reach it in her dreams. On this night
they pull the Yarrow and sleep on it, the
charm of which will bring them a vi.son
of their sweet-heart. Going to the fields
they pull nine blades of the plant, repeat
ing at each:
"All hail to the Yarrow, the wisest of
flowers,
SThon flairest of floweTrs to me,
I tryete thee to tell io,, before morn
Who my true lovec shall be."
SThey then retire to rest and must speak
no more until 'Ster they have slept. The
following legend I believe has never been
in print, ~althoughl it is quite current in
C the north of Ireland, where it is believed
by many to be true:
wAsHING IN TRE DEVIL'S NA1t
one Hallow eve night two young girls, liv
ing on the coast of Ireland, nearthe Island
Magee. went to a neighboring rivulet and
Swasheditheir linen under garment in the
r name of the Devil asking to be shown be.
fore lorning their future husbands. Re
tunrwiig to their rooms they spread the gar
ments out to dry and each placed on the
table a plate with bread and cheese for
the expected visitors and then retired to
bed. During the night they were awak
ened by a most terrible storm, with vivial
flashes of lightning, during one of which
the shadow of a coffin moved through the
room and stopped by the plate of the
younger girl and immediately after a
young man in sailor's clothes entered the
room and going to the plate of the other
cut some bread and cheese, and then dis
appeared but left his sailor's knife on the al
table. Before the year was out the young- of
eat girl died, and soon after there was a
storm and a ship wreck. One of the young
sailors who was saved fell in love with the of
other girl and they were married. Their ii
union was blessed with a son, and while pi
the wife was laying in bed, her husband
asked for a knife to out some bread. She bi
directed him to look in the cup-board. hi
In Heaven's name, where did yon get
this I" he asked holding up the sailor's w
knife while his face was pale and colorless ki
as death. After much urging she told him. bl
How dare you do such a thing 1" he cried 01
in a great rage that night we bada storm
and I was washed overboard, and then suf- of
fered the pains of the damned. No won- sa
der I felt the flames of hell when you were s1
working charms on me I" In his fury he a
stabbed her with the knife and then left w
the house and was seen no more. She re
covered after a long illness and her son
lived to be an old man. Some of his de- j
cendants are said to be yet living in Coun- p
ty Antrim. These are some of the quaint b
customs and stories of Hallow Eve which b
passing away brings as to, way t-w dim.e- nemlm elto.
by thiee B7Oyeh. ,l a thex aeltt
party i.l.e art ided. fm seartWorves
are deaIte. </text>
      </result>    
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn88064469/1913-11-02/ed-1/?sp=5&q=halloween+pranks+and+tricks&st=text&r=0.241,0.044,0.56,0.405,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>HALLOWEEN
ENTERTAINING
Keep the Children Amused and
Occupied, and They Will Not
Want to Play Naughty Tricks
on the Neighbors.
A ND now come the Halloween
elves and imps. Of these lat
ter we have. alas. too many
in almost every community.
Gates that disappear over Halloween
night and doors whose dented surfaces
bear eloquent testimony oD their on
slaughts are some of the evidences of
their existence and energy.
Just why the small boy or girl should
revel in mischievous tricks at this
season is a mystery. Perhaps it is be
2au e in every juvenile mind there Is
the inclination to impish pranks and
the traditions of All Saints' eve make
them for that time lawful amusement.
In some neighborhoods these childish
jokers are so numerous and so abun
dant that they grow to the proportions
of a pest. Neighbors who resept their
activities are unpopular, and policemen
who try to keep them within bounds
are looked upon as tyrants.
Parents who permit the promiscuous
playing of Halloween jokes are the
ones who should be held accountable.
They should provide for the yotngsters
some diversions that will keep them
indoors.
In neighborhoods where a big barn
or stable is available the children of
several families may unite in having a
co-tperative party. The owner of the
stable should be asked for permission
to use it, and after it is tidied up the
interior may be decorated with autumn
leaves, pumpkin jack-o'-lanterns, ripe
ears of corn with the husks and mot
toes cut out of paper.
The children may each contribute a
share to the simple refreshments,' and
It will be a jolly affair if the party is
a masked one. The masques may be,
cut out of muslin and the masquer's
costume need be nothing more elab
orate than a sheet, blanket, curtain or
coach cover draped gracefully over his
or her other garments and secured by
safety pins. At a certain hour dis
guises may be thrown aside. If one
or two older persons will help the
children they may be depended on to
plan for themselves just the kind of
party they want and suggest the most
satisfactory games.
I In one neighborhood where the dep
redations of the small boy had been
particularly annoying In years past a
teacher thought of the plan of pro
viding a ,jolly Halloween entertain
mlnt for the children.
It was given in the schoolhouse and
kept the youngsters pleased and
amused until 10 o'clock. welrn they
went home tired and happy with their
parents. who also had been invited.
The entertainament, included an ehbl
bition of the children's work, some
music and a stereopticon show. The
I childresn In the higher grades had
helped.the teachers in giving Hallow
een touches to the hall and school
rooms. There were decorations of cut
paper from the lower grades and pie
tnres in colored chalk on the black
board .All the children felt that they
had a hand in the affair C'ertain of
I the older boys were appointed as spe
cia.l ofl~Bers for the night to see that
boys went quietly home and that none
ing.eed. to cut "p .in the region of the
PctIheUiehe The success of the en
tertati.mnt: wa' se that it is to) be
repeated'- with the advsntage of the
experlpr d gatined.
In h r netgahliorhood 'the ladies
of a chuit'h got up n special Halloween
party. To tfljts they charged a small
admission fee. '.Tiey had Halloween
icake. ice cteam in fancy molds. al1
loween candies, all of which they sold.
Besides, they had a Halloween pie.
pn the order. of a .ack Horner pie: a
witch with a grab bag and other sea
sonable diversions There was music
to give flavor to the affair. and alto
getheurit was a most enjoyable func
tion, adding materially to the fund of
the ladies'. society by which it was giv
en. They found that the fug. which
,was of a shnp)e. wholesome kfid. was
enJeyed by even the meeost staid and
elderly of t'be congregation.
When giving-a Halloween party for
the tiny tots it is a Lped plan to have
it I.l' Be lte afternoon Bonrs Instead
of erten~ 'ql the moet backnlyed
Baltow sm gaj9 tricks will appeal
-ado Lt Mm 'aOthe beai. who
i~aadii~~ hw t them .s
HALLOWEEN TABLE DECORATION.
N effective decoration for the Halloween table is shown here. It t a
mammoth candlestick with a witch surmounting the handle and with
Halloween spooks fluttering around her. Surmounting the candle is
a white cat which holds in its paws the tiny ribbons to the ends of
which are attached the fortunes of the guests. These fortunes are bidden in
aide the candle and at a signal are drawn out by means of the ribbons. They
are humorous predictions for each guest's future. This quaint and pretty 4e
oration is made of pasteboard covered with crape paper</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84036207/1910-10-25/ed-1/?sp=6&q=halloween+pranks+and+tricks&st=text&r=-0.115,0.361,0.951,0.689,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>For the benefit of a juvenile reading
community it might be stated that the
night when "green lights burn and
witches ride abroad" is one week from
today, or October 31. The police will
be active and small boys should be on
the alert, as the horoscope man says.
It is well not to start anything until
sundown, and then to travel in large
crowds. The policeman of today is
more afraid of a large crowd of small
boys than a small crowd of large men.
The community it might be re
marked for the benefit of the small
hoy, lias an awful grouch on this year
and great care should be observed not
to get caught.
all it Vandalism.
Boys should remember that their
pranks are being referred to as van
dalism; the thumbs are down on them
in high places and that it is purposed
to make "examples" of many of them.
This thing of being made an example
of is far from pleasant and is at va
riance with the martial code which
should exist between youth and age.
Boys should always remember that
while they are inclined to turn a gro
cery wagon loose and let it run down
hill, that there are gray-haired men
in the community who never did such
a thing, and never will.
Good from Evil.
Hallowe'en Vandals make take con
solation in the fact that Dunn's re
port says glass factories in many
places will resume incident to Hal
lowe'en pranks. While this gives em
ployment to many worthy people, it
cannot be considered in the light of im
mediate economic welfare.
The burning of gates should never
he indulged in the case of poor wid
ows. Substantial citizens grow peev
ish at the prank and the practice is be
ing'generally discredited.
Altogether the Hallowe'en outlook
is not cheerful. It would be well for
boys to hold off, even on the soaping
of windows until the last night, so
that when everyone has forgotten
about it they might get by with some
thing.
There are a lot of good tricks the
authorities are not next to. One of
the best is throwing a lot of broken
glass into a doorway and making the
Inmates think the glass front is shat
tered.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn96088180/1918-11-13/ed-1/?sp=2&q=halloween+pranks+and+tricks&st=text&r=0.375,0.66,0.502,0.363,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>I have seen communities where
hallowe'en could pass and not a gate
or flower be disturbed; where John
nie and Susie could make a Jack-o-
lantern out ot a pumpkin, and play
ing their tricks at home have Just
as good a time as If turned loose
on the streets to give free rein to
their hoodlum Inclinations.
Not so the youth ot thla commun
ity; too long has their lust tor des
truction been Indulged to be content
with Jack-o-lanterns and hallowe-en
pranks In their own dooryards. John
nie Smith's only fun on hallowe-en
consists in the performance ot a few
such cute and original little tricks on
the neighbors as stealing Mr.
Brown's gate or demolishing Mrs.
Brown's flower bed. In these acts
he Is animated by the same spirit ss
the Germans In their devastation of
France, malicious destruction of
property, and without even the ex
cuse of war Is doing In his small way
what he can to Imitate them, and
still the bulk of the people, with the
exception of the victims, encourage,
laugh at and applaud him. Yet, no
doubt Johnnie signed a pledge In
school not to "wsste anything," but
If he has five minutes' Joy In laying
waste Mrs. Brown's flower bed, what
Imports it that she loses the labor
of months? It Is such fun to John
nie to watch the beautiful flowers
droop their unhappy beads at an un
timely death, while he strikes them
down In his insane glee! It It were
his mother's flowers demolished, or
his father's gate stolen, no doubt
Johnnie would receive his Just re
ward, but his parents connive at and
permit him to work bis evil deeds
secretly In the dark on the neigh
bors, Just as a Joke, you know, hop
ing that under cover of the darkness
he will escape detection. And then,
what fun for the Smith family to
laugh at the discomfiture ot the
Browns.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045217/1922-11-01/ed-1/?sp=9&q=halloween+pranks+and+tricks&st=text&r=0.441,0.342,0.376,0.272,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>MANY PRANKS
MARK EVENING
OF HALLOWEEN
i
„Most of Mischief of Harmless j
T
Kind; City I ohce Hear i
1 infr
vOmputiiiia. I

Jack o' lanterns and soaped win
dows, spilled garbage in the alleys, I
the curfew and the police—Hal
lowe'en.
Some played harmless tricks, wore
masks and carried brooms and jack
o' lantei us. others started fires in
the alleys and toyed with the police.
But thé kids were ali out Tuesday
night. It was a gala evening for
littlest kids, who stayed close to
home within call of their mammas.
Their pranks were harmless and they
had a lot of fun. Some of the bigger
Kids carried their ideas of a joke a
bit far and got. into trouble, say the
police.
Calls to the, police station were i
frequent during the evening.
"A bunch of huskies are in our
allcv, turning over garbage boxes, ash
cans and making so much noise the,
baby can't go to sleep —typical of
reports telephoned to the police sta
,1( "Say. who was the hornbre that
started this Hallowe'en ideaï" quoth;
a copper to the captain.
"I don't know, brother, but if
11
did I'd give it back to him," said the j
captain. j
Views of the police force varied
on she subject. A jailer said he d j
be darned if he'd have a kid who J
didn't have enough life to get outj;
and play Hallowe'en tricks.
"That's ail right for you: J"° u
don t have to chase em down
alleys." averred a copper just in offj
the beat with sweat in his whiskers. j
Two 1 ..»-year-old youths were taken j
to the police station for striking a
match to escaping gas trom a gas
pipe in First
the Masonic tempi
kllev nor b back
mile One vouth ran
<>ue jouth ran
and boarded a street car. S hen
caught he put up a fight and dared
all the police in the world to molest
him. À husky copper grabbed him
by the collar and the youth calmed
down.
The boys were sent home and their
names turned over to the probation
officer for fruther action.
Mrs. Minnie Gerber, 1826 Third
avenue north, reported to the police
that her automobile had been stolen
from the curb at Third avenue north
and Fifteenth street The car was
located a few minutes later by the
police when a bunch of boys were
discovered attempting to load a
tombstone on the running board of
the car in First alley south. One
youth was captured, who said that
he was only a "lookout" and didn't 1
know the names of any of the other j
boys. He wa< sent home by the j
police. The hoys who were driving
the car eluded the police and aban- 1
doned the car a few minutes later i
ou Thirteenth street between t'en-
tral avenue and First avenue south..
A popular prank with the kids and
an unpopular one with the town
folks is the soaping of windows and
automobile windshields, say the police.
This practice was begun several days
before Hallowe'en night and has
caused a great deal of adverse com
ment on a kid's sense of humor.
In the old days the kids saved
all their Hallowe'en stunts for the;
last night in October. This year
they have been going strong for
more than a week and have ash cans
scattered all over the city, the police
report.
A night of merry-making, evolved;
ages and ages ago. observed first, as
a religious ceremony, later established
as an evening of festival and mis
chievous pleasure seeking, continued
down through the years until it is
doubtful if the youth of today know
or care of the pagan saints of old for
which the occasion was evolved</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84024271/1948-11-04/ed-1/?sp=1&q=halloween+pranks+and+tricks&st=text&r=0.475,0.323,0.521,0.377,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Hallowe'en Pranks
Not Many; Mostly
Innocent Incidents
Witches and goblins sailed
forth Sunday, Hallowe’en, night,
which according to reports, was
mostly evidenced in small child
ren who began on Saturday mgnt
going around on their “trick or
treat” quests- Various small
pranks were heard of, but little
of a serious nature was report
ed- Sheriff Ellis E- Wynn said he
heard of no incidents over the
weekend.
Tail lights were torn from a
Durant-Belzoni bus, parked under
the wash rack at the bus com
pany’s present location* and a
bench used for customers to sit
while awaiting buses was re
moved, it was learned. Besides
this, none other than innocent
tricks were reported
One person told of the air be
ing let out of car tires. A few
fire crackers were shot off, but
in general Hallowe’en was re
ported to have been without
serious occurence.</text>
      </result>    
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83016810/1911-03-11/ed-1/?sp=1&q=Tower+Saved+Eiffel+Structure+Paris+France+French+Wireless&st=text&r=-0.245,-0.138,1.49,1.49,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>$2.40 PES lEABi
TOWER T0_BE SAVED
Huge Eiffel Structure Converted
into Wireless Station.
From its Top Messages Are Sent
5,000 MilesSoon to Be in
Touch With the United
States.
Paris.From the summit of the Eif
fel tower, 984 feet in the air, scien
tists communicate with ships nearly
5,000 miles out at sea. It is radio-tel
egraphy which makes it possible to
transmit to all vessels within that dis
tance a given time, say the hour of
noon, mathematically exact within the
tenth of a second, the speed of the
Hertzian waves being almost equal to
that of light.
Put in possession of the chronomet
ric time, the sailor determines the ex
act spot where the ship is at that
moment. He calculates the longitude
and the latitude with absolute correct
ness. The importance of this exacti
tude lies in the fact that it allows of
the correction of serious errors. The
best marine chronometers in use are
subject, after a few weeks or months
of navigation, to variations of two or
three seconds or more, and each error
of a second in time corresponds to
the exact position of the ship. A
metre is slightly more than a yard.
The method now used at the Eiffel
tower was first experimented with last
June. An increase in the power of
electric batteries and improvements
in other instruments enabled radio
telegraphic signals to be sent and re
ceived.
Certain wireless telegraph stations
In the United States, which have water
power at their disposal and are thus
able to produce larger quantities of
electric energy, had already sent elec
tric waves as far as Europe, where
they were registered by sensitive ap
paratus.
In transmitting the hour to ships at
sea the co-operation of the Paris ob
servatory is, of course, required. In
the silent observatory are the two
principal clocks regulated to the hun
dredth of a second, which were order
ed by Baillard, the director of the ob
servatory, from Leroy, the chronome
ter maker of the French navy. These
two clocks twice every dayat 11
The Eiffel Tower.
o'clock in the morning and at midnight
will signal the time to the four
points of the compass by means of an
electrical apparatus on the summit of
the Eiffel tower.
Exactly at 10:59 o'clock in the morn
ing and at 11:59 at night the astrono
mer on duty, with one eye on the tel
escope, watches the hand of the clock
and sends th fir,st electric signals to
the wireless telegraph station near the
tower. From there, immediately trans
mitted by radio-telegraphy, they travel
immense distances, warning naviga
tors and other wireless stations.
Then, exactly at the hour, and twice
again at intervals of two minutes, the
clockwork automatically establishes a
contact, by means of which an elec
tric manipulator in the Eiffel tower
sets up a discharge of Hertzian waves.
These waves, spreading through space,
reach the limits of the immense cir
cle of which the tower is the center,
influencing all the receivers 4n this
area and conveying to all, as it were,
the beat of a heart which is felt in the
pulsations of the remotest arteries.
In the wireless telegraphy station,
100 yards away in the Champs-de
Mars, the military authorities hold
sway. The station keeps Paris in
touch with the frontier, and even with
remote posts in Afrfca. It was the
great services rendered by wireless
telegraphy during the French expedi
tion to Morocco which led to the pro
vision of modern quarters to the wire
less telegraph corps in Paris.
These quarters are underground and
it is there that the engineer officers
and sergeants carry on. their experi
ments daily. On one door may be
read the impressive words "Danger to
life." The door leads to the first bat
tery, which has been in operation sev
eral years and gives upwards of 50,-
000 volts and a range of 2,500 kilome
tres.
And so the permanency of the Eiffel
tower is assured. Several times moves
have threatened to rid the city of a
monument which many regard as un
asthetic and cumbrous. As to wheth.
er the tower really is inartistic or not
opinions differ. But if it is considera
tions of utility will override considera
tions of art</text>
   </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn90059523/1903-10-25/ed-1/?sp=24&q=Eiffel+Tower+Doomed+Rocks+Wind+Paris+France+French+Gustav&st=text&r=0.369,0.307,0.345,0.25,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>THE Eiffel Tower must come down.
The authorities of Paris have so decreed.
This iron spire, the tallest structure in the
world, and the engineering feat of the last cen
tury, \.i regarded as a dangerous plaything.
When a high wind blows from the south the great
ribbed structure trembles like a frightened horse.
But let a stiff breeze come bowling down from the
north and the tower vibrates until the china rattles in
the cafes, and to those in the observatory at the apex the
sensation is that of a ship fossed by heavy seas.
The fact that the tower is more'sensitive to a wind
from the north than from the south is regarded as proof
of the structural weakness, and from this springs the
theory of danger of collapse.
It is almost twenty years since Gustav Eiffel began
the work of building his sky-scraper. The mark of com
pletion was set for 1889, Exposition year, and on March 31
of that year the tower was thrown open to the public. It
wa« the leading attraction of the big show, and it has
not since ceased to attract attention and coin.
The cost of building the structure was more than
$1,000,000. Of that amount the French government appro
priated $29L',000. Eiffel supplied the remainder, trusting
for his reimbursement to the receipts from admission fees
and other sources.
In this he was not uisappolnted, as the profits of the
first year were almost sufficient to make him whole.
The lease held by Eiffel will expire in next March, and
then, if the present plans of the city fathers are realized,
the work of razing the unique structure will be started.
The plan is to sell the tower to the highest bidder, the
purchaser to be given a certain time in which to remove
what Paris regards as almost a public menace.
Except as a curio and an Investment for its builder,
the tower has been somewhat of a failure.
Much was expected in the scientific world from the
metaphorical observatory, with its physical and biological
laboratories, all 954 feet above ground. But little has
come of this, the enterprise having taken on a rather
commercial aspect.
The Eiffel Tower will ever be considered a colossa*
feat of engineering.
Tlhese Stria! Ihxean F®ds ire nsudhes hM
.'v_V- Ir 'mJf.A?j -i?'^^t Vk^T*i^*v*
THE beanstalk up which Jack, the Giant Killer,
climbed to fame has been sung and pictured until
even little Emma and Annie and Jeannette and
Joe, sprawled there on the nursery floor, can tell
of its sturdy trunk, of its stout, ladder-like branches, of
Its leathery leaves, which the eager hands of their hero.
Jack, could not crush, though he clutched them ever so
tightly.
They can tell you that this fabled beanstalk was so
tall that "Oo! you jest couldn't see the top uv it, so you
couldn't."
DRINKERS IN TWO CLASSES
==Mlsery and L,Mxtuiry==
BOTH CLAIM THEIR VICTIMS OF LIQUOR
LONDON, August 17.
WOMEN who drink are classified by the experts
into two sections—misery drinkers and luxury
drinkers.
Speaking broadly, the misery drinkers come
from the very poor, the luxury drinkers from the rich.
But whatever the cause which first sends them to drink
the ultimate results are the same—a falling birth-rate, a
rising death-rate among infants and the physical degen
eration of the race.
Dr. Claye Shaw, a recognized authority, made it clear,
in discussing the matter recently, that the evil is not con
fined to the lowest order of society.
"My experience," he said, "is that among women of
fashion, women who have nothing to do but to amusa
themselves, there l a a growing tendency to take alco
holic stimulants, and the ill effects of that, both upon the
•women themselves and upon their children, are often very
■erlous
"There is a great deal of private drinking. I know
towns where it is a common thing for young girls to go to
a private counter in a confectioners shop and take a
glass or two of champagne or a glass or two of port.
"There are confectioners' shops in London where wo
men of position do the same thing. And at home there is
•adly too much nipping of spirits in private. It does not
etop at that. Many women drink cologne, many use mor
phia.
"Jt is the result of high living, and an emotional,
unnatural, excited way of life. All this leads to personal
demoralization and the weakening of character. Some
times it is a step towards the divorce court.
"The trouble is that the women have nothing to do
nothing to occupy their minds. The happiest marriages
The lower section consists of four columns resting
upon masonry 85 feet square and 30 feet high. These
curve toward each other, so that they unite as a slnglo
column 620 feet above the ground.
PARIS, October 10.
There are platforms at the 189, 380 and 906 feet levels,
reached by elevators as well as by Btairs. Beyond the
third platform a spiral staircase, which is not open to the
public, ascends to the top of the tower.
On the first platform, which has a floor space of 38,000
Bquare feet, or nearly an acre, there were four restau
rants at the time of the Exposition, and refreshments are
Btill served there.
The view from the top of the tower extends eight y
flve miles on a clear day. At night a searchlight gleams
from the eminence.
Seven thousand tens of iron were used in building the
Eiffel Tower.
Gustav Eiffel made a long leap over precedent when
he planned and built the spiral skeleton of Iron which
made him rich and famous.
The ambition of the Egyptians to pierce the sky with
pyramids carried them less than half as high as this
French engineer went on a comparatively fragile founda
tion.
The pyramid of Cheops 13 only 486 feet high; that of
Cephrenes 456 feet.
The best that Rome can do, with all her boasted
achievements in lofty architecture, is to point to the dome
of St. Peter's—a paltry 448 feet above ground.
London steps into third place in these Old World ver
tical achievements with her St. Pauls dome—36s feet up.
Campanile, the famous leaning tower at Pisa, did not
win fame because of the height of its arcaded colonnades
bo much as because of its obliquity, and yet when we are
told that this tower is thirteen feet out of plumb we
learn in the same breath that it is 179 feet high!
Stepping over to the New World to complete the table
of comparisons more ambitious figures are encountered,
and yet our best achievements are as pigmies in the
shadow of the tower that Eiffel built.
The Washington Monument ranks first, with its 555
feet of gleaming granite.
Second in order" is the quaint, broad-brimmed hat of
William Perm surmounting the heroic statue on the tower
of Philadelphia City Hall. This measurement is 547 feet.
And the sweet little enthusiasts are to be believed.
Odd as It may seem, however, the wonderful mind that
evolved Jack's beanstalk, with a giant castle the first way
station, did not compass the idea that it must have borne
wonderful fruit.
Its pods were surely longer than a man's body, and
each bean larger than a cocoanut. No better weapons
could be imagined for the giant, whose fierce, puffy face
is pictured peering over the ledge of his high domain,
than a handful of these big beans, weli dried, hurled
upon the head of daring interlopers like Jack.
are to be found among the middle classes—the backbone
of the race.
"In the lower orders a great deal of crime is, beyond
doubt, due to the drunkenness of parents. The Inhabitants
of Broadmoor, taken as a class, are not big, violent mani- I
acs, but feeble, degenerate imbeciles, damned before they
ware born by the habits of their parents.
"In the Bicetre Hospital at Paris 41 per cent, of the
imbeciles are the children of drunken parents.
"It has been proved by a French investigator that
alcohol consumed by the mother passes, as alcohol, into
the circulation of the unborn child. The infant is soaked
with gin or rum before it is born, and may develop all
kinds of malformations, physical and moral.
"A woman receives no alcohol when in jail, and Dr.
Sullivan has noticed that when a child is born in prison
that child 1b usually the best of the family.
"The drunken habits of parents' may or may not be
transmitted to the children. When drunkenness becomes
hereditary the family is doomed—erratic conduct in the
second generation, epilepsy in the third, Imbecility and
extinction in the fourth."
It is admitted by the scientists that a drunken father 1
has not nearly so bad a physical effect upon his offspring
as has a drunken mother.
In the north country towns the infantile death-rate is
terrible. Dr. Greenwood, of Blackburn, recently informed
the Town Council that 226 out of 1000 babies' born in the
borough did not live to be a year old. i
More than half the deaths in Darlaston are those of
children who have not reached the age of five. In Lei-
cester, out of an average of 60 deaths each week, 20 are
those of children. In Blrkenhead 178 out of eery 1000
children born die before they are a year old.
The offsprings of drink are insanity, pauper sm epl
lepsy and feeble-mindedness. In London there are 2000 epi
leptics and about 100,000 paupers, and all over the country
there are 110,000 certified lunatic*.
TfflE ST. P^ULGLOBE, SU2s TJ)AY, OCTOBER 25, 1903.
Within a stone's throw are-two business blocks that
tower higher—but these are, nevertheless, not towers.
Tho Trinity Church spire 4n New York has caused
the crooking of many a neck, yet its height Is only 284 feet.
The Bunker Hill Monument stands 221 feet above the
historic sod that undulates about Its base.
It may be said, in justification of all of these beacons
of history and architecture, that they stand for bo much
more than mere height that they possess that In sufficient
degree.
The Eiffel Tower possesses the sole distinction of altl
tude. Barren of other claims upon the public attention,
the need of outstripping—virtually doubling—the elevation
of any other tall structure is apparent.
Scattered over.lreland and Scotland, or,Jiere %nd there
on the Islands of Corsica and Sardinia, are to be found
the ruins of some of the towers of prehistoric times.
These, like those of our cathedrals .and public build
ings of to-day, were built for purposes of utility.
The old round towers ot Ireland, as well tta the
"brochsT of Scotland, were used as places of refuge or
defense in time of war, as wateff towers and as resort for
the recluse.
The architecture was at first plain and severe, while
In later years appeared parapets and pinnacles richly
canopied.
These towers were never mbfe than 132 feet high, with
the average perhaps 80 feet.
In remote times the Moslems' built towers of stone
that they used as minarets. The finest of these belong
to the thirteenth, century, notably the Mlnan of Kootub,
at Old Delhi, which was the wjonder of ail the tribes that
gathered about it.' This towei^ was 250 feet high, built of
massive blocks of limestone and marble.
Not since the days of Babel, if, indeed, before, has the
building of a tower for the mere pride of building it been
essayed. Confusion of tongues Svas the result then.
Coming down to the age «f a*»ial playthings, modern
ingenuity seems to have spelled for itself a lesson—one
less severe than that of Babel, bat, nevertheless, a lesson.
Having ventured past the point of practicability and
safety, the monument erected'by Gustav Eiffel to tho
genius and daring of man faHa; before the force of the
elements, while the dust of ages-icontlnues to settle upon
the sloping sides of the pyramids.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1900-05-20/ed-1/?sp=43&q=Feet+Tower+Eiffel+Paris+France+French+Worlds+Fair+Exhibition&st=text&r=-0.034,1.052,0.433,0.314,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>the CHAMP DE MARS.
rtOtf THE DFFBL ToWKIt T O THE
PALACE OF F.:.K«TKI("ITY.
jvis, M»r 1-— The Champs de Mars, the home
/fvV u lar demonstrations since the great Revo
fctJja ITS 9. and the happy hunting ground
Z"p-e&t exhibitions; offers this year a splendid
vg t with its two long rows of palaces on either
f and in the background the beautiful vista
('"tie F"^* 1 5 cmamental Chateau d'Eau. or
Mkt Fountain! flaf.ked on either side by the
iesS elejraxt Palace of Electricity, the great
k (or "clou." as it is called here) of the Ex
-ettlcn. The spectacle is truly magnificent.
Qt the ISSi) buildings which were here noth-
it tl I

near the
1 cut ti
gi
Tiere is little to be said of the exteriors of
gjes^ two palaces on either side of the Champ
c- Mars. T^">.:.- a. way from the Eiffel Tower
Ml M
•i" first ha'.f c* the left line is the Palace of
H;srs and Metallurgy. Like all the other build
fc?T= en the Charrr de Mars, it is constructed
ti iron, cover*"? with wooden laths and faced
r
with plastf r. Th-> ornamentation is extremely
_.
light, white being the prevailing tone. The dome
consists of an imrr.vns-; tiara resplendent in imi
taticn precious stune:-— a novel and nappy form
cf decoration. The second half, leading to the
Pu.iac-e of Electricity, is occupied by the Palace
tf Threads and Textile Fabrics. It consists of a
!:r.e of raJ>'-i arches, forming the outside of a
covered gallery, given up to restaurants, some
thing similar to the constructions that were here
in the same place in l vV A fine central porch
It is
I
_ iring
_.
th that of Let I i
ad In
		
En-
ration is in good
icted
th< rin all their
these two
AT THE FEET OF THE TOWER.
FOREIGN PAVILIONS CLUSTERED AWAY
FROM THE BUB DBS NATIONS.
Round about the hus^ ff>.-tf f> .-t of the EfTei Tower
will be found the pavilions of I antrtefl
which lid not find a place in the Rue dcs Xa
tions—the Swiss chalet, built completely of wood,
surrounded with balconies and terraces, like the
great Alpine chalets. It is not an official pa
vilion for receptions, but a meeting place for
the Swiss visiting Paris; the pavilion of San
Marino, the little republic dovetailed into the
kingdom of Italy, containing cereals, wine, oil,
honey, lace, embroidery, pictures, furniture, uni
forms and various works of art highly creditable
to a country of only five thousand inhabitants;
the pavilion of Siam adds its Oriental stamp to
the peculiar architectural icedoin< Morocco
is divided into two distinct arts the Imperial
Pavilion and the annexes, containing restau
rant, cafes and shops. The Imperial Pavilion is
a reproduction of one of the imperial kiosks of
the ancient Fez palaces, erected by the side of a
Tetuan minaret. Picturesque paintings in warm
colors impart lite an African Orientalism to
the general quaintness of the buildings. Then
near the Woman Palace is the Pavilion of the
Equator, a two storied building in Louis XV
style. A tower surmounted by a cupola crowns
the edifice, the whole of which, after the fair is
over, will be taken down and sent to Guayaquil
to serve as the town library. The interior, fur
nished with Louis XV furniture, contains the
chief products of the Republic of the Equator,
such as fruits cacao, coffee, rubber, sarsaparil
las, quinine, tobacco, vegetable ivory minerals
and splendid woods; sugar, carpets, stuffs, lace,
embroidery, palm fibre, and the plaited straw
hats so well known as Panama hats.
Among the many constructions clustered here
mention must be made of the French Alpine
Club, containing botanical and geological collec
tions and exhibits of the best mountaineering
necessaries, besides a panorama of the Alps and
excellent photographs of the scenery; the Auto
mobile Club; the Touring Club, open to all its
members; the Chateau Tyrolian; a pavilion for
exhibits of Russian alcohols; one for the history
of ceramic art; branch buildings for business
purposes of the three great banking establish
ments Credit Lyonnais Society Generate and
Comptoir d'Escompte and several high priced
and fashionable restaurants
Foreign Photos. Carbons,
H M< ITOHS,
OI.l) BMGiaSH I'ltlM's, ■BUOTOmk
i:\(.UAVIM.s.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83040198/1899-02-03/ed-1/?sp=7&q=Eiffel+Tower+France+French+Paris+Exhibition+Worlds+Fair+Ladder+Clouds&st=text&r=-0.247,-0.045,1.483,1.483,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>A LADDER FROM THE CLOUDS
Bach Will Be the Appearance of the
Eiffel Tower of Parts When
Painted.
The Eiffel tower, say the gentlemen
of esthetic temperament, must go.
The Eiffel tower, say the gentlemen
who know the law, must stay for some
years yet. The Eiffel tower, say the
esthetes. Is ugly, discouraging to the
eye and an all-round nightmare. "Scaf
fold I cries the carper. "Down with it
It has no place in esthetic Paris,"
"Impossible! objects the law. "When
the company took a lease of it they
got it for a term of 20 years.. You
can't break the lease, and the time is
nowhere up.
"But, urges the esthete, "look at
the shape, look at the size, look at the
color! Is not the whole thing hideous"?
If we can't destroy it we can at least
improve it and lessen the offense to
our senses."
And so the Eiffel tower is going to be
metamorphosed. It has. been in color
a reddish brown, and it is the color to
which the gentlemen with the fine ideas
have long objected. They have called
the tower a shameless creation and re
peatedly ridiculed the commonplace
tone of hue. And now they have pre
v ailed, and the lower is going to be a
thing of beauty, so far as that goes.
Silver white is the color agreed upon,
and it is urged that when the army of
workmen have finished their painting
the huge structure will look really not
so bad after all. Ilalf a hundred men
will be employed on the building, work
ing hard every day for two months.
And 50,000 kilogrammes of paint will
be used up before the Eiffel tower has
finally lost its brickdust coat and finds
itself arrayed in the poetic covering
which the esthetes have advised. Two
coats of paint will be applied and the
brushes will be busy.
It has been objected that the tbwer
has always had the appearance or hav
ing been cast up in inartistic form by
a careless earth. The tower has seemed
to rise awkwardly from the ground,
the critical have said. Why not give
it such an arrangement as would sug
gest the idea of dropping from the
clouds? That would be a pleasing fan
cy, and if the huge tower were lighted
at regular intervals it would present a
picture as of a brilliant creature of the
clouds, and all the world would be lost
in admiration. These plans were sug
gested when the exposition of 1900 were
tinder discussion, and they have been
adopted. A ladder from the clouds.
That was tbe idea. 'And with that the
esthetic taste, was forced to be sat
isfied.
The Eiffel tower has long been the
universal bed lamp of Paris. The great
candle in the top would be sadly miss-d,
even by those who have fought agair.&t
the continuance of the structure. That
ever-swaying lantern is one of the won
ders of the French capital. Y. Her
aid.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85032018/1894-01-31/ed-1/?sp=15&q=Eiffel+Tower+Paris+France+French+Worlds+Fair+1900+Exhibition&st=text&r=-0.435,0.356,1.608,1.608,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>tj Happily all Paris is not so pessi
mistic as my friend, and the architects
are busy with their plans. All the
ground comprised in the exhibition of
'89 is to be included, as well as the por
tion of Cour la Heine that will inclose
the Palais 1' Industrie and its surround
ing gardens. We are to have an addi
tional bridge across the Seine which
will open a vista from the Place de la
Concorde straight through to the palace
of electricity, which is to be the cen
tral feature. Our rulers are greatly
bored about the Eiffel tower; but as
the concession was granted for twenty
years it has got to stand; but the arch
itects say consolingly that the 7 will
try and hide it as much as possible.
The sight of it vexes poetio souls,
and Francois Coppee, the author, who
is, by way of being, sthetio, wrote
a formal protest to the government at
the time of its erection to request that
the plan should not be carried out on
the ground that the Eiffel tower, being
ugly and ungainly, and furthermore
being visible from his windows, inter
fered with his flow of inspiration.
However, the tower was built never
theless, and, although we are deadly
tired of seeing it about, Coppee con
tinues to write, so evidently his flow
ol inspiration was only impeded and
not permanently plugged up. Further
more, we are to have a branch exhibit
at Versailles, which will rouse that
sleepy little town from its chief ou
pation of listening to the grass grow
ing in the streets. In the splendid
park of Versailles, on either side of
the grand canal, is to be the retro
spective history of gardens throughout
the ages.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn87060190/1889-05-07/ed-1/?sp=4&q=Eiffel+Tower+Paris+France+French+Expo+Exhibition+Worlds+Fair&st=text&r=0.253,0.018,0.324,0.234,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>At tho ontranco, spanning the gateway
witu the vast archways of Ite base, rises tho
gigantic Eiffel tower, 'MO metres high. Pass
ing underneath it tho Central gardou is
i cached. This has a monumental fountain
BASE OF EIFFEL TOWER,
ia tho middlo, and is surrounded by build
ings containing exhibitions of flue arts,
boUos lettres, tho liberal arts, and various
departments of industry.
Those buildings stand on parallel lines and
ore crossed in their axis by a high gallery
manaounted by a doma which leads to th
hatt of machinery. Tho cost of tho build
ings in tho Champs do Mars, exclusivo of tho
Mffel tower, has been about (4,000,000, and
it is intended that they shall remain as per
aaaent structures. The total outlay author
ised for tho entire exposition U 38,600,000, of
wttch $000,000 is hold aa a rcerve fund.
The earthworks required a removal of
700,000 cubic foot. Tke drains and water
pipes of the Camps do Mars were lengthened
hf about two miles, and more than 40,009
ems of iron and steel wero u&ed by the
holders. The hall of machinery is 1,309 feet
long and 150 feet high, covered with a roof
f iron, wood and glass, having a span of
380 feet in tho clear, the greatest ever at
tempted. A gullory extends around tke in
terior for the display of tho lighter classes of
machinery and from end to end run four un
ferofcen linos of shafting for distributing the
Beotivo power. Tho powor is dorived from a
proup of steam engines placed in one of
the touts, tho bollors of which transform
into steam forty tons of wator per hour.
The total energy is about 400 horse power.
TJio chief architectural feature of the ex
position is, of course, tho Eiffel tower, as
wore the Crystal Palace at London In 1851,
the iron lighthouse at Paris in 1807, tho groat
THE EIFFEL TOWZ& VBOX THE BEINK
rotunda at Vionna in 1873, and the Trocadero
palace at Paris in 1878. This is the loftiest
structure eyer rahedjjy Iman, being about
064 feet high. The Washington monumont
now stands second, 55.5 feet. The Cologno
cathedral is 501 feot. Tho tower of Babol
was probably CS0 high. Moro than 7,000
tons of metal were us?d in building tho
Eiffel tower. Tho first sod was turned in
excavation for its foundation on January
28, 1887, and the whole work was completed
on March 31, 1889.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn91068084/1889-04-26/ed-1/?sp=5&q=Eiffel+Tower+Paris+Exhibition+1000+Feet+High+France+French+Worlds+Fair&st=text&r=0.121,1.156,0.579,0.419,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>NEARLY 1000 FEET HIG&
The Great Eiffel Tower at the
Paris Exposition.
How the Colossal Structure, Just
Completed, was Erected.
The great Eiffel tower at the Paris Exhi
bition has just been completed, and a de
scription of the colossal structure, with an
account of the way it was built, and a sketch
of its constructor, will bo appropriate at this
time. It is scarcely necessary to say that the
U
mm

Cologne
Cathedral,
511 ft.
The Eiffel Tower,
9S4 ft. The Great
Pyramid,
480 ft.
Eiffel tower is by far the highest structure in
the world. It presents a decidedly unique ap
pearance, too in general outline not unlike a
stack of four gigantic muskets with their
butts well and solidly spread and their bay
onets joining at their tips.
The Eiffel tower stands in the Champ de
Mars, almost on the left bank of the river
Seine, just in the rear of the Quai d'Orsay,
and in fact a part of its foundation is sunk
through an old arm of the river, which lias
been filled in these many years. Its base
covers a plot of ground 328 feet square, or
nearly two and a half acres in extent.
GUSTAVF. EIFFEL.
It Ls really at the base a group of four tow
ers, each nearly fifty feet square, placed at
the corners of the plot of ground, and in
clining toward each other as they rise at an
angle of fifty-four degrees. Each tower con
sists of four columns, bound together by
trusswork, and each column rests on a
masonry pier which is so built that the weight
of the column rests upon it squarely and not
at an ancle.
As the tower is 0S4 feet high. it will be
seen that the matter of providing a solid
foundation was one of great importance.
There was a lot of boring and digging befon
the spot upon which the tower stands was
finally selected.
The foundation rests upon a thick stratum
of sand and gravel. It may be well to say.
for the benefit of those who think sand is a
rather treacherous sort f ground, that a bed
of sand and gravel, away under ground, is
pretty solid stuff. One of the towers of the
Brooklyn Bridge rests on that sort of base.
The foundations of the two piers of the Eiffel
tower farthest from the Seine rest on sand
and gravel about twenty-five feet below the
surface of the ground. These foundations
were laid in open excavations, and consist
first of great solid platforms of beton, six
feet thick, and next of four stone piers which
rise to the surface to receive the iron col
umns. The foundations for the two piers nearest
the river were not so easily laid. It was
necessary to go thirty-five feet below the
surface of the ground, end this was sixteen
feet under water. So caissons had to be
used, as they were in building the Brooklyn
Bridge piers.
A caisson is in effect simply an enormous
iron box, without any cover, turned upside
down. The method of using it is to dig the
earth out from under it and allow it to
gradually settle as the excavation pro
gresses, meanwhile building the pier on top.
When the required depth is reached the cais
a .n itself is filled up with the beton, and it
forms the bottom layer of it a foundation.
A shaft is left running through the pier
auove for entrance and exit as the work goes
on, and the air in the caisson and shaft is
compressed to whatever is necessary to keep
the water out of the bottom. It is the prin
ciple of the diving bell modified.
Work on the foundations was begun on
January 28, 1887, and at the end of June they
were completed. Then began the labor of
setting up the innumerable pieces of iron of
which the tower is composed, and it went on
at a vapid rate, for each individual piece
came from the works of M. Eiffel, at Leval-lois-Pere
cut to its exact dimensions, fitted
and drilled, so that no modification was neces
sary at the place of operations. Up to a
height of about fifty feet the workmen re
quired no scaffolding to work upon, as each
pier supported itself, although each leaned
toward the others. Then an artificial support
had to le provided, as above that height, un
til the first platform was reached, the center
of gravity of each pier would fall outside of
the base.
And so piece by piece the towers grew,
and at length reached a height of 140 feet.
Then four enormous horizontal trusses were
put in place to connect the four piers. These
were nearly 140 feet long and weighed a
good many tons, and hi order to place them
in position it was necessary to erect an ex
tensive false work, or scaffolding. "When
these trusses were in position, and the con
necting beams to form a flooring were in
place, the workmen ha1 a great solid plat
form, nearly 15U feet above the ground and
upward of 1 oJ feet square, to work upon.
These four inclined piers and the four big
connecting trusses form the solid groundwork
of the tower. There is nothing particularly
unique in the detail of construction. The
work is simply a system of trusses and braces,
in which the material is so placwd as to make
a strong and light structure. The four great
arches which rise between the piers, imme
diately under the great horizontal trusses,
are largely ornamental in character. They
serve to round off what would otherwise be
an angular outline, but do not support any of
the weight of the structure.
Above the lower platform two four-corner
piers incline toward each other at a
sharper angle. The iron columns are lighter
and the spaces in the system of bracing are
larger. High above the first platform, nearly
400 feet from the ground, a second series of
horizontal trusses binds the four piers to
gether and forms the basis for a second land
ing. These two platforms are glorious places
St. Peter's,
433 ft. Rouen
Cathedral,
470 ft.
Statue of Wash- Column
Liberty, ington Vendome,
301 ft. Monument, 148 ft.
500 ft.
from which to view the city of Paris. They
are so large that even very timid persons
standing on them will lose all fear. The
lower one is nearly half an acre in extent
while the upper one is about one-third that
size. From the platform a view of the coun
try for forty miles around may be obtained.
Above the second platform the four corner
piers gradually approach each other and at
length unite in one pier, at the top of which,
nearty a fifth of a mile from the ground,
there is a covered observatory, and above
this rises a slender mast. Doubtless many
thousand people will see Paris and ever so many
square miles of surrounding country from the
observatory during the summer. They will
not have to walk up, for a gigantic elevator
runs up through one of the piers to the very
top. This elevator is of peculiar construction,
for the carriage or truck, travels upward on
a spiral track, while the car itself rises
vertically, or rather as nearly vertically as
the angle of the pier will allow.
While the Eiffel tower was a stupendous
conception, and will stand as completed
the marvel of modern engineering, no new
principles are involved in its construction.
In fact, to an engineer, the most wonderful
thing about the tower is its simplicity. The
way for the Eiffel tower, both in conception
and execution, was paved, after a fashion,
by the work on the Garobit viaduct and the
Taraes bridge, both of which were built by
Eiffel. In fact, the construction of bridges
and viaducts, without the use of scaffolding or
false work, by making the several parts
balance themselves as the work progresses,
owes much to this French engineer.
Gustavo Eiffel is a master of construction.
It is said of him that he combines within
himself the practical knowledge of the Eng
lish engineer, the audacity of the American
and the science and theories of the French
man. He was born at Dijon, France, in 1S32,
and was educated at the Central School of
Sciences and Arts. He it was who first made
practical use of compressed ah in cassions in
the building of bridge foundations, in the
erection of the great bridge at Bordeaux.
TOP OF THE TOWER.
M. Eiffel has been a busy man, indeed, these
many years, but he found time, when the
statue of Liberty Enlightening the World was
to be set up in New ork Harbor, to design
the skeleton framework which support the
gigantic figure and at the same time firmly
holds it to the granite pier on which it stands.
A glance at the illustration will show to
what extent the Eiffel tower overshadows all
the famous tall structures of the world. In
comparison with its 984 feet Cheops is dwarfed
at 40. The Washington Monument is little
less than 500 feet high, and the point of .he
flame of Liberty's torch in New- York Harbor
rises barely 300 feet in the air.
The fees for ascending the Eiffel tower are
five francs (1) to the cop, three francs
(sixty cents) to the second platform an 1 two
francs (forty cents) t. the first. The three
platforms will hold 10,900 people</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83025121/1889-04-02/ed-1/?sp=8&q=Eiffel+Tower+France+French+Paris+Worlds+Fair&st=text&r=0.246,0.555,0.544,0.393,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>THE EIFFEL TOWER
A Msht and Sensation for lisitor to
1arls
In view of the assurance of a
creditable representation of Hawaii
both in productions and person
agesat the Universal Exhibition of
this year in Paris a few facts rela
tive to the EiffeUower culled from
a late English paper may be of local
interest
The tower is named after its pro
jector Mr Eiffel now President of
the French Association of Engineers
He is famed in part -for the design
ing of a great bridge at Bordeaux
Although the Eiffel tower was orig
inally the conception mainly of an
ambition likened to that of Ameri
cans by the English paper referred
to for having the highest structure
in the world it was also early as
sumed that it would have uses in the
interest of science It is claimed
and anticipated that it will be very
raluable for observatory purposes
owing to the perfect clearness of the
air at its summit
The tower is to be one thousand
feet in height At the date of the
description here drawn upon it had
attained an altitude of 738 feet or
162 feet higher than any other build
ing on earth There were 180 men
employed then in its construction
100 preparing the lifts at the base
and 80 riveting the perfectly fitted
parts at top To avoid fatiguing the
workmen aloft in descending several
times a day for food a restaurant is
fitted up at a height of about 400
feet There are to bo four perman
ent restaurants for the refreshment
of visitors on the first stage of the
tower
A spiral stairway runs from the
ground to the summit of the tower
but it is believed that few if any in
experienced heads will be able to en
dure the strain of going round and
round or looking down from the
giddy heights Therefore there are
to be mechanical lifts to the top
four to the first stage two to the
second and thence one to the sum
mit the crown of observation The
final lift will have a capacity of 65
persons I1 ares will be 6 francs to
the first stage and 5 francs to the
top to be reduced on Sundays to 1
franc and 3 francs respectively No
visitors are allowed during construc
tion except on Sundays owing to
danger of accident from a hammer
or bolt falling from aloft Mr iffol
pays a weekly visit to thoworks The
workmeu have to endure severe cold
at the summit whore the thermome
ter sometimes registers several de
grees below zero
The panoramic view to be obtained
of the beautiful city of Paris and
environs froin the top of the Eiffel
tower must be loft to the readers
imagination until assisted by ac
counts from the Hawaiian Commis
sioners Col Spalding and Hon J
A Cummins or unofficial visitors
from these isies or descriptive writ
ers in the foreign press after ex
periencing the sensations of the
sublime ascension and prospect</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85033162/1900-05-18/ed-1/?sp=3&q=Paris+Exposition&st=text&r=-0.509,-0.635,1.619,1.619,0/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83016810/1911-03-11/ed-1/?sp=1&q=Tower+Saved+Eiffel+Structure+Paris+France+French+Wireless&st=text&r=0.656,1.027,0.359,0.26,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>TOWER T0_BE SAVED
Huge Eiffel Structure Converted
into Wireless Station.
From its Top Messages Are Sent
5,000 MilesSoon to Be in
Touch With the United
States.
Paris.From the summit of the Eif
fel tower, 984 feet in the air, scien
tists communicate with ships nearly
5,000 miles out at sea. It is radio-tel
egraphy which makes it possible to
transmit to all vessels within that dis
tance a given time, say the hour of
noon, mathematically exact within the
tenth of a second, the speed of the
Hertzian waves being almost equal to
that of light.
Put in possession of the chronomet
ric time, the sailor determines the ex
act spot where the ship is at that
moment. He calculates the longitude
and the latitude with absolute correct
ness. The importance of this exacti
tude lies in the fact that it allows of
the correction of serious errors. The
best marine chronometers in use are
subject, after a few weeks or months
of navigation, to variations of two or
three seconds or more, and each error
of a second in time corresponds to
the exact position of the ship. A
metre is slightly more than a yard.
The method now used at the Eiffel
tower was first experimented with last
June. An increase in the power of
electric batteries and improvements
in other instruments enabled radio
telegraphic signals to be sent and re
ceived.
Certain wireless telegraph stations
In the United States, which have water
power at their disposal and are thus
able to produce larger quantities of
electric energy, had already sent elec
tric waves as far as Europe, where
they were registered by sensitive ap
paratus.
In transmitting the hour to ships at
sea the co-operation of the Paris ob
servatory is, of course, required. In
the silent observatory are the two
principal clocks regulated to the hun
dredth of a second, which were order
ed by Baillard, the director of the ob
servatory, from Leroy, the chronome
ter maker of the French navy. These
two clocks twice every dayat 11
The Eiffel Tower.
o'clock in the morning and at midnight
will signal the time to the four
points of the compass by means of an
electrical apparatus on the summit of
the Eiffel tower.
Exactly at 10:59 o'clock in the morn
ing and at 11:59 at night the astrono
mer on duty, with one eye on the tel
escope, watches the hand of the clock
and sends th fir,st electric signals to
the wireless telegraph station near the
tower. From there, immediately trans
mitted by radio-telegraphy, they travel
immense distances, warning naviga
tors and other wireless stations.
Then, exactly at the hour, and twice
again at intervals of two minutes, the
clockwork automatically establishes a
contact, by means of which an elec
tric manipulator in the Eiffel tower
sets up a discharge of Hertzian waves.
These waves, spreading through space,
reach the limits of the immense cir
cle of which the tower is the center,
influencing all the receivers 4n this
area and conveying to all, as it were,
the beat of a heart which is felt in the
pulsations of the remotest arteries.
In the wireless telegraphy station,
100 yards away in the Champs-de
Mars, the military authorities hold
sway. The station keeps Paris in
touch with the frontier, and even with
remote posts in Afrfca. It was the
great services rendered by wireless
telegraphy during the French expedi
tion to Morocco which led to the pro
vision of modern quarters to the wire
less telegraph corps in Paris.
These quarters are underground and
it is there that the engineer officers
and sergeants carry on. their experi
ments daily. On one door may be
read the impressive words "Danger to
life." The door leads to the first bat
tery, which has been in operation sev
eral years and gives upwards of 50,-
000 volts and a range of 2,500 kilome
tres.
And so the permanency of the Eiffel
tower is assured. Several times moves
have threatened to rid the city of a
monument which many regard as un
asthetic and cumbrous. As to wheth.
er the tower really is inartistic or not
opinions differ. But if it is considera
tions of utility will override considera
tions of art</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84026749/1907-03-10/ed-1/?sp=47&q=eiffel+tower+attraction&st=text&r=0.482,0.288,0.462,0.334,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>p M T 1 1t
t f fand
iiJ
if TTlfr T r
T
r cam ill let 1 ewer rfriiii rfriiiid
d Fleets of the Reputl Reputlpe
pe Be Dire ci ed and andiliCont
f
iliCont i


J nH
i
j GIGANTIC war wareye wareye
eye that th a twill twillsweep will willsweep
sweep the whole of ofFrance ofPranceher
France Pranceher her fron frontiers fro1Zjers
tiers jers her chains clzaillsof clzaillsoffortresses of offortresses
fortresses and her herseaboard herscaboardsllch
seaboard scaboardsllch such Is Isto isto
to be the I further furthermission furthermisJion
mission of Ithc the fa famous famOlls
mOlls Eiffel Tower Toweri Towerof
i of Paris ParisThis Par J JThis
This struct strllcillrc strllcillrcere lire
4 e ere r e c t c d a as s the thechief thechief
chief curiosity of ofthe ofthe
the Paris Exposi Exposition E 4posi 4position
tion has outlived outlivedits
its 11 usefulness in other respects and has hasbeen hasbeen
been made the central point of the great greatwireless greatwireless
wireless signal system of the French army armyand armyand
and navy
From the top of the tower which is
984 feet from the ground roll1td officials of the thearmy thearmy
army may direct military operations op ratio1Zs in any anyLift allYLftt
Lift up your eyes and behold them that come from fromthe tromthe
the NorthJer aclll 0 0URLNG 0D
FlUNG the army manoeuvres last fall fallthe fallthe
D the various corps were directed from fromthe fromthe
the now station Later fleet movements movementsin mO mcnts mcntsin
in the Englislrchannel El lis1 chRnnel and the Mediter Mediterranean M diter diterranean
ranean wore ordered ord 6dwithout without a hitch in the samo samoway sarnotvaJr
way wayQuite Quite lecently the scope scoP of communication communicationfirm comunicatio1f
firm f m the tower towmlms has been Cxf rlendc1 ended so that no nOtY nOtYmessages v vmessages
messages are exchanged e changed with London and Ber Berlin Berlin
lin on the one onG side and with Tunis and Algiers Algierson Algierionthe
on onthe the African coast on the other otherTte otherThe
The work of equipping it for signal pur purposes purposes
poses is now going on and it is expected to in inEtal instal
Etal there the most complete coml lete system s stem of wire wireless wireleastelcir8P1ly
less leastelcir8P1ly tdegrapny in the thewodd thewoddne world worldThe
The French Frenchare are pleased with the idea of 1C 1Cbining re retaining
taining the architectural curiosity curiosi ty and their theirjeamty tbcirFanity
jeamty is tickled hy the plan to make it the theriost theost
riost ost wonderful war eye on the globe globeIndeed glober
r Indeed the enthusiastic people pcoJ le confidently confidentlysrpect confidentlyb
b srpect ect in a short time tim to see 5e airships arriving arrivingt
1t t and nd departing from this great steel stom stomfcn stomin
fcn airship airshipstntion station nearly 1000 feet above earth earthBuilt earth1nt
Built 1nt by the th famous engineer Gustavo Eif Eifr Eifrrr
r
rrr I
part of ortlze the Republic and even for consider considerable cOlZsijerable
able distances ovei tle tile frontier in adjolnlng adjolnlngcountries adj illi1lg illi1lgcOlilltries
countries Its naval fleets In the thelYledi thelYledierrmzetlll Medi Mediterranean
terranean errmzetlll the Bay Ba of Biscay the English EnglishChannel EllglishClza1l1zel
Channel the North Sea or the Baltic B ltic will willbe willbc
be In constant touch with the directing directingauthorities directilZgauthorities
authorities In Paris ParisShould ParisShould
Should France and England become becomeallies becolleallies
allies in some future conflict direct com communication commtl1licat
mtl1licat munication on with London can be maintained maintainedfrom mailltailledfrom
from the Eiffel Tower Southward from fromit
it waves of warning anJtSfypmmand Jm1lZmzd will willfloat j
float into d Algeria 19cria and Tunis From this rc rcmarkable rcmarkable
markable tower may issue orders that wilt wiltchange willdt willdtczange
change the 7i of Europe v vfel
czange map ap i iI iI iIel I I
fel the tower was completed in March 1889 lSS9jn lSS9jntime in intime
time to tOSCITe serve as 13 one of the notable features featur 5J of ofthe oftlte
the exposition of that year ear It was the loading loadingattraction leallingattraction
attraction of that big show and has never neversince neversinceceased since sinceceased
ceased to draw visitors and coin coinIt coinIt
It cost considerably over 1000000 to build buildtho buildtho
tho tower for which 7000 tons of metal were wereused wereused
used Of the cost 292000 was voted by tha thagovernment thlgovernmont
government while the engineer supplied the therest thereat
rest The profits for 1SS9 alone nearly paid nid tha thacost thacost
cost
Some idea of its height height984 984 fcot feotway niay be begained begained
gained from a comparison with other structures structuresof
of the world Tho Washington Monument at atWashington atVashington
Washington D C is 555 feet tall the broad broadbrimmed broadbrimmed
brimmed hat of William Penn on Philadel Philadelphias Philadelphias
phias City Hall is 547 feet above the pave pavement pavement
ment the dome of St Peters in Rome rises risesto risesto
to only 448 feet while the great pyramid of ofCheops ofCheops
Cheops is but 486 feet high highFrom highFrom
From the top of the Eiffel Tower on onjlclear onjlclearday tclear tclearday
day one can see about eightyfive mUei At Atnight Atni
night ni ht a searchlight from this eminence stabs the thesurrounding thesurrounding
surrounding darkness darknessAt darknessAt
At its base this wonderful tower covers coversnearly coversnnarb
nearly twc and a half acres of ground</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1900-05-20/ed-1/?sp=36&q=eiffel+tower+attraction&st=text&r=0.098,0.019,0.883,0.639,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>GETTING ABOUT IN' PARIS.
Till: ELABORATE TRANSIT SYSTEM IN
THE CITY, THE EXPOSITION GROUNDS
AND PROM THE SUBURBS.
Paris, May 12.
Visitors to the Paris Exposition will find theni
selves well provided for as regards means of
locomotion both in Paris and in tin Imposition
itself. Tli. Oare Saint-Lazare, the terminus of
the Western Railway, in combination with the
Chen in de Fer de Ceinture, or bell railway, will
convey pass ngers to a new station especially
construct d for the Exposition at the northwest
corner of thi Champ de Mars and close to the
Seine For those who prefer to bfgin their
visit at the Esplanade dcs Invalides a second
station has been erected, connected with the
first by a covered line extending along the river
front of th>- Champ do Mars and the Eiffel
Tower. Although the line is under the direction
of the Western Railway Company, which pos
i the Newhaven-Dieppe route from Eng
land, n can also be made use of by passengers
over any other company's lines. Tho Care dv
Nord, terminus of the Northern Railway, which
owns the* Dover-Calais and Folkestone-Boulogne
routes from England, has a direct service over
the Ceinture Railway to the Champ de Mars.
Other companies' lim-s arc similarly in touch
with the World's Fair.
Tr:u..~it In the city and its suburbs by means
of tramcars has also received increased accom
modation, both in quality and in quantity. A
short time ago a streetcar on one of the city
lires was in such a dreadful state of dilapida
tion, dirt, and -and— dirt, that the pasßengers
formally complained to the Public Prosecutor,
with the result that one fine morning the Chief
ol' Police and his men paid the company a visit
and seized the movable home for microbes. A
careful examination of the car and its uphols
tery went to show, according to the official
scientists, that the cushions and car were not
only the homes of objectionable insects, but also
regular domiciles for the germs and bacilli of
ev< ry known Infectious disease.
The- effect of the consequent standal has been
to cause a general cleaning and overhauling of
all tramcars and omnibuses, and the introduc
tion of numerous new cars so there need now
be do fear of contamination by microbes. In ad
dition to the new lines of tramway in the city
which art- already in service, there are no fewer
than twenty-two new lines connecting Paris
with its suburbs in course of construction. These
will complete tho means of suburban communi
cation, and no place in the outskirts of the city
will be without its direct service.
MAKING SUBURBS AVAILABLE.
The railway companies are putting on a quick
er train service at more frequent Intervals;
therefore those visitors who wisely take rooms
out of Paris Instead of paying exorbitant prices
in the city will find every convenience for quick
transit to and fro.
For those who live in the outskirts and near
the river Seine, at Meud< n, St. Ck.ud, BcUevue,
Sevres, Boulogne, Auteuil, Suresnes mention
should be made of the rapid service of small
Steamboats which ply every ten minutes or
quart.r hour between Suresnes and the Pont
Royal. The landing stages nearest to the Ex
position are Pont de la Concorde, for the grand
entrance by the Porte Monumontale; Pont dcs
Invalides, for the esplanade of tho same name;
Pont de l'Alma, for the pavilions of tho United
States and other nations, as well as for "Old
Paris"; Punt d'len.i, for tho Champ de Mars,
Eiffel Tower and Trocadero Palace.
The river trip by boat from the Pont Royal,
In the heart of Paris, to Point dv Jour (Auteuil),
where the Ceinture Railway has a station, will
be much frequented, for a most remarkable
panoramic view is to be had on both sides of
the river of the Exposition buildings- and their
annexes.
On one side, after passing the Louvre Palace
and the Tuileries Gardens, are to be seen the
Place de la Concorde, with the chief entrance or
Porte Monumental,.; the new bridge, Pont Alex
andre 111, beyond which appear the Petit Palais
and the Grand Palais: between this and the
next, the Pont de l'Alma, are the conservatories
of the horticultural and arboricultural sections,
as well as the many theatres or side shows
which go to make up what will be known in
future as the Rue de Paris; "Old Paris" is built
along the quay between the Pont de l'Alma and
the footbridge which follows— a temporary one
for the season; just beyond, on the same side of
the river, is a group of pleasure craft, and, im
mediately after the grounds and palace of the
Trocadero, given to French and foreign colonies.
Returning from Point dv Jour the panorama
on the right is even more diversified and inter
esting. Here are passed successively the Im
mense buildings of the Champ de Mars, together
with the Palace of Optics, Woman's Palace, the
Eiffel Tower, the Palace of Costumes and the
"Round the World" panorama, the Pont d'lena
forming the connection between the Champ de
Mars and the Trocadero; the constructions dedi
cated i" the army and naval exhibitions of all
countries, reached from the opposite shore by
Clio temporary footbridge already mentioned;
pavilions, containing heating and ventilating ap
paratus and hygiene in all its branches; after
the Pont d'Alma, right along the Qua! d'Orsay,
which is already nicknamed the Rue dcs Na
tions, are the pavilions of all the foreign Pow
ers, some of them most beautiful and sub
stantial structures.
NEW-YORK TRIBUNE II.USTKATKD SUPPLEMENT.
That of the United States, situate. l between
those of Austria and Turkey, merits special
mention, for it is not a pavilion, but a veritable
palace, higher than any other on the Qugay, and of fine architectural proportions. It
consists of a massive quadrangle, from the midst
of which rises a high dome of (esthetic outline
and almost as grandiose as the Pantheon. On
its summit the national eagle spreads out its
wings and holds In Its claws a ribbon upon
which may bo read: "United States of America."
The facade, on the river side, is composed ol
portico or triumphal :ir< h, ornamented with
Corinthian columns, and crown d by a s ulptural
group representing the Goddess of Liberty In
the chariot of Progress, drawn by four horses
led by a man on each side. Under the archway
and in a line with the columns is an equestrian
statue of George Washington.
The whole palace, even in its smallest details,
has been constructed by Americans with Ameri
THE UNITED STATES WEATHER BUREAU STATION
can materials—a most wonderful feat, unique In
Its way, when It be remembered that everything
has had to be shipped thousands of miles and re
shlpped to Paris.
The entire height of the building from the
quay is IGS feet. The dome Is GO feet wide, and
the allegorical group of sculpture over the por
tico is placed at a height of 70 feet. Some Idea
may be obtained from these measurements of
the stately proportions of this imposing monu
ment. At night the symmetrical outlines of the
palace and Its architectural details will be fairy
like in the light of the electric lamps which
trace Its chief structural features. All National
functions and official receptions will t;iK' j place
in this palace, which is a striking ornament
even among the mai y wonders of Parisian
ai chitect ure.
Leaving the United States palace and passing
the scarcely less remarkable Italian Pavilion, at
the corner of tlie Pont dcs Invalides, the pano
rama of tin- Exposition buildings <>n the Espla
nade dcs Invalides unfolds itself, having for
connection with the right bank thi new bridge,
Alexandre 111. with its prolongation by the new
Avenue Nicholas 11 to the Champs Elysees.
A truly wonderful promenade, during which
will be seen representatives of all peoples, the
whole set in a dazzling Ham.- of architectural
construction white and gold and pale green and
n any colored, but all uith the unmistakable,
original, individual seal and style of their na
tional mind and genius.
LOCOMOTION INSIDE THE GROUNDS.
Ah to means of locomotion inside the Expo
sition, everything necessary has been provided
or. the left bank of the Seine. Ready communi
cation between the Esplanade dcs Invalides, the
pavilions of foreign Powers and the Champ de
Mars i:; supplied by the electric railway and
the movable platform. There will also be the
"fauteuil roulant," a kind of bath chair on
pneumatic bicycle wheels, pushed by an attend
ant, which, in the colonial section at the Troca
d. i... will replaced by the Madagascar "fllan
zanes."
Amateurs of the wheel, whether automobilists
or bicyclists, will find two bUMttM coach houses
(or stabbs which is it?>, here called "garage
one on the left bank, near the quay, at the en
trance of the Esplanade dcs Invalid- a.-.d Urn
other on the right bank by the s:d- of the gar
d. as bordering the petit Palais, neat th< champs
Elysees.
Too much attention cannot be called to tlu
excellent system of "correspondence" tick
means ol which a cross Journey anywhere
the fortifications can be made by taking two
trams, or two 'buses, or one of each, for the
price of one Journey six cnts! Care, however,
must be taken to ask for the "corr- ■poadence"
when paying the fare, and to give it up to the
Inspector when getting into the second con
veyance.
No reference has been made here to the new
underground railway, the MPtrripf.litan, for the
simple reason that there is no likelihood of lt.s
being ready for at least three months. From
the exhibition point of view, its chief utility
would have been to take sightseers direct from
the Place de la Concorde station to the Exposi
tion annex at Vincennes. whore the American
Machinery Hall is situated. Its opening is fixed
for the end of June. It will thus coincide with
the date at which the Exposition itself will be
completed— that is, all the constructions finished
andraw backs appears to be the want of electrical
power, which will not be given generally until
June 1.
Whatever ma> l>> the real cause of the delay
(and it is n<>t far to seek), the result is deplor
able for every <.m interested in the undertaking.
whether as an exhibitor or merely as an intend
ing visitor. The one loses because he es not
get the amount ol publicity and advertis
for his goods which h. had a right to expect,
lie h;is paid a high rate for spate and COB
sions to turn to a possible profit during six
months, whereas, owing to some inexplicable
negligence or want of foresight, he has only
three months in which to balance his expendi
ture and returns. The other, the visitor, having
heard of thy backward state of preparation,
takes a preliminary trip through Switzerland
Germany, Italy, to the Rhine or the Tyroi before
venturing a visit to an incomplete exhibition.
Both combine, with one result— loss to exhibitors
and l<> all those in every station ol life and occu
pation who cater in ar:y way for th.' Exposition
and its public.
Although It Is only a side show a very hand
some one -outside the Exposition grounds on
the right bank of the Seine, "old Taris" opens
its doors on the 7th lnst. to give Parisians and
foreigners a foretaste of Exposition joys. As a
faithful reproduction of some old parts of the
city In the time of Henry II It will probably
prove to be a decided attraction. G. L B.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1924-01-11/ed-1/?sp=19&q=eiffel+tower+attraction&r=0.16,0.064,0.637,0.231,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>EIFFEL TO BE LAID
UNDER FAMED TOWER
Designer of Famous Paris Land
mark to Have It as Monument
to Memory of His Work.
By the Associated Press.
PARIS, January 11.— Gustave Eiffel,
the noted French engineer, who died
recently at the age of ninety-on®, will
bo burled eventually under tho tower
bearing his name —one of the most
conspicuous landmarks of the French
capital.
The great skyscraping skeleton
structure, a thousand feet high,
built as one of the attractions of the
1900 exposition and now to serve
as a monument to Its designer, owes
meeting of the Grand Lodge of New
York In New York city on May 6. He
has also received Invitations to ad
dress the Grand Dodges of Pennsyl
vania. CalifonOa. and Connecticut, but
the full details of his tour have not
been decided upon.
Sir Alfred is a distinguished Eng
lish parliamentary- journalist, and was
"doyen of the lobb:-" when he retired
from active Journalism at tho end of
1923.
its prolonged life to wireless teleg
raphy. After the structure had lost
Us value as on attraction, Paris be
gan to ask for its destruction, find
ing that it was not a particularly
esthetic ornament.
Then wireless came and the tower
was found to be Just thd thing for
a wireless station. It was used
throughout the war for the dissemi
nation of governmental Information
and for the capturing of stray wire
less messages from the enemy coun
tries.
According to popular belief, though
history has yet to confirm it, the
tower saved Prance during the first
battle of the Marne. Interception of
wireless orders sent from German
headquarters to von Kluck's *rmy Is
credited by this legend with having
given the first news of the movement
of the enemy that enabled the French
to outflank von Kluck and entirely
redress her fortunes, greatly imper
iled by this Oermkn campaign.
SOON TO KNOW RESULT.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83025308/1891-06-17/ed-1/?sp=1&q=eiffel+tower+attraction&st=text&r=0.037,0.099,1.515,1.097,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>COMMERCIAL WVAB.
Threatened by a German Alarmist
World's Fair in '96.
BxERr, June 16.-With referenceato the
proposed German World's fair. to be held
in 1866, Mr. Von Siewans, the great electri
oian, who is a leading member of the com
mittee of projectors, talking with an Asso
ciated press representative to-day, said they
will make a solid showing of what they
can do in the way of manufacturing, with
out an Eiffel tower or similar attraction.
"In addition," he said, "European nations
are becoming aware that they must con
solidate commercially against American
aggression. America is not only shutting
out many of our products by prohibitive
tariffs, but she also threatens our trade
with mouth American republics, and even
with Africa and Asia. Power naturally
makes America aggressive and Europe
must take a share of her interests or be
pushed to the wall. If America keeps on
as now we shall have to go to a commercial
war. We will retaliate."</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86072192/1899-07-23/ed-1/?sp=22&q=eiffel+tower+attraction&st=text&r=-0.056,-229.286,1.111,460,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>A CONGRESS OF
HUMAN FREAKS
Paris, July 19.—Besides the exposition
proper, with its thousands of attractions,
official and private, there will be countless
annexes or counter attractions, many of
which will receive fully as much attention
from the visitor as the legitimate exhibits.
For many months the promoters of these
freak exhibits have been searching the
world for Ideas, and when these have been
put into execution the result will be a col
lection of architectural monstrosities, the
like of which tho world has never seen. It
Is difficult at this time to decide just how
many of these strange propositions will
turn out to be Impracticable, but each pro
moter who has secured option on land is
confident of success, and if all succeed
there is scarcely a law of nature that will
pot have been doited.
When France built the Eiffel Tower she
turned up her nose at the world. England's
response was the conception of the Wem
bley Park Tower, while America replied by
building the Ferris Wheel. "Anybody can
pile one beam upon another,” they said,
"but we have built a structure ns high U3
your tower, and the wonder of it is that it
goes round instead of standing still."
Then France put on her thinking cap and
the result is that she has devised and is
now completing a building that is to spin
round like a majestic top. The height of
this revolving tower will be something over
400 feet, which will be divided into twenty
three stories, each story being given over
to some attraction. There will be a dance
hall, a vaudeville theater, beer gardens and
restaurants so that the visitor will have
no need to leave the building from early
morning until late at night, and oil the
while this immense structure will be turn
ing round and round, at the rate of about
three miles an hour. Architects who have
examined the plans ere satisfied that there
will be no danger of collapse, and that the
continued revolutions will be attended by
no disagreeable sensations.
Already arrangements have been made
for the construction of M. Besancon's ar
tistic balloon that will have a seating ca
pacity of more than one hundred persons,
not including a brass band, and that will
be held captive at an elevation of more
than two thousand feet. This balloon will
be the handsomest specimen of its kind
launched Into Bpace, as It is to be decor
ated with twelve allegorical figures repre
senting the months of the year. As the di
ameter of the balloon will bo 33 metres and
the clreumserence 103 metres, each figure
will measure about seventy-five feet. In
this balloon those who are looking for new
sensations will be carried to a point, hun
dreds of feet higher than captive balloon
ever went before, and from this point of
vantage they may watch the carrying on
of photographic and meteorological experi
ments to the accompaniment of a brass
band.
The big wheel of Paris, which is forty
five metres higher than the wheel at Earl's
Cotirt. London, has been completed for
some time, and it will undoubtedly be one
of the great attractions of the exposition.
It Is not only a wheel, like the Ferris
Wheel of Chicago, but it is a series of
wheels, and contains many features that
were lacking in the American Invention.
For Instance there ore numerous cafes and
restaurants, a casino and a concert and
dance hall similar to those that will be
seen In other parts of tho grounds. In fact
the new wheel is on illustration of how
great a "big wheel” may be.
Hair lifting experiences appear to be In
order at the Paris exposition, and not the
least of these will be the gigantic umbrella
that has been invented by R. E. Sherman,
of Chicago. This Invention, which resem
bles an umbrella In its form, is a steel
structure over 350 feet in height. To each
rib of the umbrella a car capable of seating
fifty people will be attached, and these cars
will be lifted from the earth to a point even
with the top of tho structure where they
will be suspended in midair long enough to
give a magnificent bird’s-eye view of the
grounds and the city beyond.
Another “clou,” ns the great features of
the exposition ore called, will be the
mareorama which has been invented by M
Hugo d’Alesi. This will consist of a large
ocean steamer In which the passengers will
make a voyage from Marseilles to Con
stantinople: that is to say on imaginary
voyage, since the vessel will not move for
ward at all. the illustration of sailing be
ing produced by a mechanical arrangement
that will give to It every motion of pitch
ing and rolling. In fact the Illustration is
carried out so perfectly that actual sea
sickness will result in the case of passen
gers who are subject to this ill.
Tho vessel will be surrounded by foaming
and boiling water, which will be thrown
against the sides of the ship in regular
■wells, while at the same time, on all sides
of the vessel will unroll canvasses fifty feet
In height, painted to represent perfectly the
scenery during the voyage. To the rear
will be seen the port of Marseilles and oth
er views of the shore of France; then the
open seas, followed by the Algerian and
Tunisian coasts towards which the vessel
soems to be steering. No detail that would
add to the reality of the illusion will be ne
glected.
The passengers may walk about or sit
at ease in the steamer chairs on the deck,
which will reproduce that of a genuine
steamer with the minutest accuracy, with
all the accompaniments of masts and rig
ging, smoking and vibrating funnel and a
crew executing various mnneuvres at the
command of an experienced captain. The
mareorama will be 131 feet In length, 112
feet in width and 75 feet in height. It will
bo different In mechanical structure from
tho rocking ship described In this newspa
per last Sunday.
Everyone has heard of the gigantic globo
on which the surface of the earth is to be
pictured in minutest detail, the gigantic
telescope that Is to bring the moon within
n milo of the earth, the Inverted Eiffel
Tower In which the visitor may descend a
thousand feet Into the earth, and the mov
ing sidewalks that will carry one to every
section or the grounds In such a manner as
to make walking practically unnecessary.
But these are commonplace Incidents
compared to many of the spectacular fea
tures that have been arranged for, the arti
ficial volcano that will rival Vesuvius at
Its greatest eruptions, .with a realistic pre
sentation of the literal hell of Calvin and
Knox in the center of the mountain; the
Palace of Electricity, with all the marvels
that Its name can suggest, or the pneu
matic lined projectile in which courageous
persons may be dropped a thousand feet
Into a hole in the earth.</text>
      </result>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <id></id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>/</id>
	<rel></rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>/</id>
	<rel></rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <id></id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>/</id>
	<rel></rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>/</id>
	<rel></rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
</topics>
