<topics>
  <topic>
    <id></id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1903-11-01/ed-1/?sp=33&q=Subway&st=text&r=0.662,0.314,0.48,0.347,0/</id>
	<rel>rel=1</rel>
	<text>Tumbling Into the ''Open Ditch" Dog Marfr Crazy bjf llv plosions—*
The Victims of "Sulncay Knee" Nmrom Escapes of Horses.
As far back as history or kgraf go-»s. man
has always beea anxious to know how it feels
to die, without dying. Men have permitted
themselves to be "partially killi'd." for the pur
pose of Aescfihtag the sensation.-? which th^y
experienced. They have tilled th-ir lungs with
water. They have eaten of the llradlj poppjr.
They have grasped the stinging electrode. And,
last of all. they have tumbled into the subway.

However the Bterchaats of this city may op
pose an "open dit. h." there are many philo
sophical citizens who regard it as a blessing.
Here they are able with ease to make the
plunge into the unknown themselves, or be
content to watch others Jo it. HVre they may
watch various mental phenomena, whkh are of
the greatest value to psychology, and obtain
data, for example, as to why an absent minded
man fali-s into the subway head tirst. whereas t
frightened woman simi>ly jumps in.

According to the records of the BapM Transit
Commission, there have been just nineteen men
aril women who have tumbled into the subway
since it was begun. There have also been
thirty-two horses \vhi> h have either made a
complete dt scent to the subway's bottom or
partially made the leap. Numberless cats have
tumbled into the great tr.-nc h, and several dogs
have been made crazy by the bl.usting. In addi
tion to the.se unfortunates, many H trkmites
living in bOMK-ave assert that at one time
they contracted the "subway knee," and that
M of the Creqoent explosions of dynamite
beneath their honic-s their legs had a tendency
to double up.

Although explosions and cave-Ins have some
times LlUWll •.•ath, DeTerthetoM there has been
a humorous H well as a pathetic side to the
subway work. Ike average New-Yorker, who
h.is bc-?n c: isaMed by Kuropean anthropologtsta
as the "Homo patiens," and who accoßUno
hin.^-:f to new situations so quickly that
the "out-of-towner" calls him blase, has also
come to regard the subway In hie more com
placent Btooda a? a J<>y forever (if not a
thin* of beauty). Should he be aboard a sur
torest by the nay. When we left them at Lon
lon I expressed my thanks, adding that I was
agreeably rarprised to find them so open and
pleasant, in rlew of their traditional stand-off-
Lshness.

\V"ll, I h !<-irt ceased laaghing jrH at his
reply. ''Mi.' exclaimed he, *we don't mind in the
least talking to Americans. There's little chance
of our seeing then again, you know.''
face ear aftor making fortune that day in a
rise of Yeast com num. and the car stops with
a sudden jolt, he will most likely say:
"Another wagoa knocked into the subway."
Should he he ensconced In his own ar:n chair,
with hi wife resting h.-r head upon his shoul
der, and ihe chillren playing about his feet, and
he should be thrown halfway to the ceiling by a
sort of seismic sho> k, he would gather his fam
ily about him again and say:
"The house has slid into the subway."

Or at the club, if he is discussing the purity
of politics with an Independent Democrat, and
a rock should break into the room and his con
versation, he might quietly remark:
"Merely a high ball from the subway."

On a Sunday, should this patient citizen at
tend charcfa In upper Broadway, and the
preacher should contrast the evil life with the
good life, and should admonish his audience to
chooae wisely in view of the consequences, and
should go BO tar a.s to speak of the bottomless
pit, there would be more than one mind In that
church which would involuntarily think:
"He meani the subway."

Of .til the accidents that have come to the
notice of the Rapid Transit Subway Construc-
tion Company there were none which evoked
lea sadness than the ezpiosfoa which was al-
leged to hive driven a ball dozen dogs crazy.
According to one story, the firing of a blast on
Broadway, betw« n Long Acre Square and the
cir l-\ shook up a woman's bird and animal
store with such terrific violence that after she
had ta< rsett recovered from the shock she found
one of the parrots, which had been a resident of
i rh* ago, laying:
'T.ace t.; thee!"
Some Belgian hares w^r? so stunned that they
died, and the fear crossed the woman's mind
that if these had been the only Belgian hares In
existence the species would have become ex-
tinct. But the maddest of an who lived in the
block, po sh^ said, were a half doz<>n dogs. They
kept digging as if to di« sUbwaj of their own.
and in oth«r ways showed s!gns of mental at ■■r
nition. The woman brought suit against the
contractor for $50,000.

In spite of all the erudition of physicians and
Burgeons, there was nothing known of the "sub-
way knee" until the winter of 1901. At that
time some of the residents of I^-nox-ave. com-
plained of a flexibility of the knee, which at
times was disconcerting, if not dangerous. No
matter what one's ideas on religious matters
might be, he was likely at any time to get down
on his knees as if in prayer. hould he per-
chance n.eet his debtor and see his opportunity
of getting that $5,000 which he had long ago
given up as lost, he might suddenly find the
situation reversed, and himself instead of hi*
debtor in an imploring attitude.

The majority of those suffering from the "sub-
way knee" traced its origin to the frequent
blasts in the subway In front of their homes.
They said that the violent vibrations had loos-
ened their joints, and although they might have
posed for more pious persons than they really
were, nevertheless they preferred stiffer legs.
They said they would even prefer a "house-
maid's knee" to a "subway knee" if they could
only get it without being housemaids.

At one time in Park How there was hardly a
day that some horse did not put his foot
through the planking of the wooden roof, or a
wagon wheel did not sink in a crack, or both
horse and wagon fall clear to the bottom of the
trench. On May 8 of this year 'here were two
such accidents within a few hours of each
other, and within a few feet of the same
place. Near the bridge entrance a wagon broke
through the subway roof, but the driver by
leaping, was able to save the animals from fall-
ing through. Two hours before that 4. coal
wagon had disappeared over the side of the
subway in front of the Potter Building, and
had been finally rescued by means of a hoisting
engine and tackle. According to the contractor
for the City Hall section of the subway, there
have been eleven horses hauled out of the
trench since it was first begun.

One might think that a horse would be sure
of serious injury from such a tumble. Yet some
have had what seemed to be hairbreadth ex-
periences and escaped with only a few scratches^
A trolley car once bunteJ a team of horses at-
tached to an express wagon into .he subway in
Fourth-aye. between Eleventh and Twelfth sts.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>/</id>
	<rel></rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <id></id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>/</id>
	<rel></rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>/</id>
	<rel></rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <id></id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>/</id>
	<rel></rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>/</id>
	<rel></rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
</topics>
