<topics>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-new-york-city-subway/selected-articles</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1903-11-01/ed-1/?sp=33&q=Subway&st=text&r=0.662,0.314,0.48,0.347,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>SOME INCIDENTS OF SUBWAY CONSTRUCTION.
Tumbling Into the ''Open Ditch" Dog* Marfr Crazy bjf llv plosions—
The Victims of "Sulncay Knee" Nmrom Escapes of Horses.
As far back as history or kgraf go-»s. man
has always beea anxious to know how it feels
to die, without dying. Men have permitted
themselves to be "partially killi'd." for the pur
pose of Aescfihtag the sensation.-? which th^y
experienced. They have tilled th-ir lungs with
water. They have eaten of the llradlj poppjr.
They have grasped the stinging electrode. And.
last of all. they have tumbled into the subway.
However the Bterchaats of this city may op
pose an "open dit. h." there are many philo
sophical citizens who regard it as a blessing.
Here they are able with ease to make the
plunge into the unknown themselves, or be
A IIOIISE THAT SIvIPPED INTO THE SUBWAY.
His harness and the wagon alone prevented him from falling to the bottom, but the harness clicked
him to dealh before he could be rescued. A trolley car pushed him over the brink.
content to watch others Jo it. HVre they may
watch various mental phenomena, whkh are of
the greatest value to psychology, and obtain
data, for example, as to why an absent minded
man fali-s into the subway head tirst. whereas t
frightened woman simi>ly jumps in.
According to the records of the BapM Transit
Commission, there have been just nineteen men
aril women who have tumbled into the subway
since it was begun. There have also been
thirty-two horses \vhi> h have either made a
complete dt scent to the subway's bottom or
partially made the leap. Numberless cats have
tumbled into the great tr.-nc h, and several dogs
have been made crazy by the bl.usting. In addi
tion to the.se unfortunates, many H trkmites
living in bOMK-ave assert that at one time
they contracted the "subway knee," and that
M of the Creqoent explosions of dynamite
beneath their honic-s their legs had a tendency
to double up.
Although explosions and cave-Ins have some
times LlUWll •.•ath, DeTerthetoM there has been
a humorous H well as a pathetic side to the
subway work. Ike average New-Yorker, who
h.is bc-?n c: isaMed by Kuropean anthropologtsta
as the "Homo patiens," and who accoßUno
hin.^-:f to new situations so quickly that
the "out-of-towner" calls him blase, has also
come to regard the subway In hie more com
placent Btooda a? a J<>y forever (if not a
thin* of beauty). Should he be aboard a sur
torest by the nay. When we left them at Lon
lon I expressed my thanks, adding that I was
agreeably rarprised to find them so open and
pleasant, in rlew of their traditional stand-off-
Lshness.
\V"ll, I h !\<-irt ceased laaghing jrH at his
reply. ''Mi.' exclaimed he, *we don't mind in the
least talking to Americans. There's little chance
of our seeing then again, you know.'"
face ear aftor making fortune that day in a
rise of Yeast com num. and the car stops with
a sudden jolt, he will most likely say:
"Another wagoa knocked into the subway."
Should he he ensconced In his own ar:n chair,
with hi wife resting h.-r head upon his shoul
der, and ihe chillren playing about his feet, and
he should be thrown halfway to the ceiling by a
sort of seismic sho> k, he would gather his fam
ily about him again and say:
"The house has slid into the subway."
Or at the club, if he is discussing the purity
of politics with an Independent Democrat, and
a rock should break into the room and his con
versation, he might quietly remark:
"Merely a high ball from the subway."
On a Sunday, should this patient citizen at
tend charcfa In upper Broadway, and the
preacher should contrast the evil life with the
good life, and should admonish his audience to
chooae wisely in view of the consequences, and
should go BO tar a.s to speak of the bottomless
pit, there would be more than one mind In that
church which would involuntarily think:
"He meani the subway."
Of .til the accidents that have come to the
notice of the Rapid Transit Subway Construc
tion Company there were none which evoked
lea sadness than the ezpiosfoa which was al
leged to hive driven a ball dozen dogs crazy.
According to one story, the firing of a blast on
Broadway, betw« n Long Acre Square and the
cir l-\ shook up a woman's bird and animal
store with such terrific violence that after she
bad ta< rsett recovered from the shock she found
one of the parrots, which had been a resident of
i rh* ago, laying:
'T.ace t.; thee!"
Some Belgian hares w^r? so stunned that they
died, and the fear crossed the woman's mind
that if these had been the only Belgian hares In
existence the species would have become ex
tinct. But the maddest of an who lived in the
block, po sh^ said, were a half doz<>n dogs. They
kept digging as if to di« sUbwaj of their own.
and in oth«r ways showed s!gns of mental at ■■r
nition. The woman brought suit against the
contractor for $50,000.
In spite of all the erudition of physicians and
Burgeons, there was nothing known of the "sub
way knee" until the winter of 1901. At that
time some of the residents of I^-nox-ave. com
plained of a flexibility of the knee, which at
times was disconcerting, if not dangerous. No
matter what one's ideas on religious matters
might be, he was likely at any time to get down
on his knees as if in prayer. hould he per
chance n.eet his debtor and see his opportunity
of getting that $5,000 which he had long ago
given up as lost, he might suddenly find the
situation reversed, and himself instead of hi*
debtor in an imploring attitude.
The majority of those suffering from the "sub
way knee" traced its origin to the frequent
blasts in the subway In front of their homes.
They said that the violent vibrations had loos
ened their joints, and although they might have
posed for more pious persons than they really
were, nevertheless they preferred stiffer legs.
They said they would even prefer a "house
maid's knee" to a "subway knee" if they could
only get it without being housemaids.
At one time in Park How there was hardly a
day that some horse did not put his foot
through the planking of the wooden roof, or a
wagon wheel did not sink in a crack, or both
horse and wagon fall clear to the bottom of the
trench. On May 8 of this year 'here were two
such accidents within a few hours of each
other, and within a few feet of the same
place. Near the bridge entrance a wagon broke
through the subway roof, but the driver by
leaping, was able to save the animals from fall
ing through. Two hours before that 4. coal
wagon had disappeared over the side of the
subway in front of the Potter Building, and
had been finally rescued by means of a hoisting
engine and tackle. According to the contractor
for the City Hall section of the subway, there
have been eleven horses hauled out of the
trench since it was first begun.
One might think that a horse would be sure
of serious injury from such a tumble. Yet some
have had what seemed to be hairbreadth ex
periences and escaped with only a few scratches^
A trolley car once bunteJ a team of horses at
tached to an express wagon into .he subway in
Fourth-aye. between Eleventh and Twelfth sts.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85038615/1904-10-09/ed-1/?sp=27&q=New+subway+Subway+York&st=text&r=-0.006,0.847,0.731,0.529,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>WORLD'S GREATEST EFFORT TO SOLVE CITY TRANSPORTATION PROBLEM
Tlie New York Subway tlie
Greatest Thing of Its Kind
Ever Undertaken.
NO OTHER COMPARES WITH IT
?\Vhat lt Is Expectcd to Do in
Solving tlie Most Difiictilt City
Transportation Problcm.
By Bassett Staincs.
ll?pNEW lollK, Oct. S.?There are grealor
fiiglnnorliig work's going on In tho world
to-day, For cxample,, l.lm constructlon
of the A.isouun dnm and the other lrrlga
?'.lldrj w-orks on lho Nilo, whlch, a? thclr
erentor, iHIr Wllllam Gnt-stln, prottdly
hiitisir, wlll llve ln tho uso and obser
vntlon of umiiklnd long nfter ihe an
cletit inoniiment.i of tho Egyptlans hava
illsappoared beiieath Ihe Biinds of the
Nublan deserl. But of Its klnd lho New
Toik siihwny Is the grentcst thlng yet
done, and It is o.Iso the greatest en
ghioerlng entcrprlse of any klnd ln tlie
1 "1111011 States to-day.
It wlll be opened Ihroughoul nrnily
the whole of Its length In the course of
Ihe preKi-nt ninnth, If slrlkes do not fur?
ther delay Ihe completlon of tlie work.
31 Is prnctlf-ally ilnlshed from the resl
'lgri-at. buslness soctlon Around City Hall,
foinn work ls stlll going on farther down*
town townrds the Battery, and nlso nt
the northern extremlty of Mmiliattiin
nnd on the Iiiooklyn oxleilslon,
Will Exceed All Others.
Time was when the Gothard and Mont
?'cnls. tunnelH wero held to bo conslder
nlile iioles In the earth. They nre merc
rabblt burrows In comparlson wlth the
Vitst sliaft whlch has been drlven long
glttidlnally through the Inland ot Man
hnttan.
Or take, Instead, the greatest oxcava
tlons made by vanlshed civlllznilons.
?Great as ure tlie ca%*es of Elephanta and
llie tomples of ICarnak nnd of Ahooslm
1'rd on the Nllo bank, the floor space. of
tlie statlomtof tho New York subway.
t.-iken togother, ls greater than that of
any two of them, and when the Jirook
lyn nnd under-the-r-ver tunnels to be
made are completed, such ttatlonal areas
wlll oxcecd in comblncd space nll the
rock-lu'wn templcs of the anclent world
Itoown to archaeology."
Thls Is the statement. of an cngineer
conhected with the work who happens to
be glfted wlth a poetlc imaglnatlon. But
none tho less hc possesses that preclslon
of dctall whlch properly belongs to hls
jji-ofcEslon, for he -has computed that
the carth whlch has been, or wlll be,
excavatcd In the making of the subway
iimounts to exactly .1.700.2SS cublc yardsf.
Tho rock lunneled ainuunts to half a
sullllon yards; the rock excavalc-d, to
more than double that quantliy.
Some Striking Figures.
Here nre some other figures whlch
Kpeak for thcmncivea us to the nioighl
fii'dii of the work:
Stee! usc-d ln the structurc, 75,000 tons;
cost iron, a mere trifle ot' 10,000 tons;
c-oncrete, far over 500.000 cublc yards;
water proollng, more than 700.000 cublc
yards; brlck. 20,000 cublc yards; vauit
ifglit-, over 7,000, each shedding Its
beams for a radlus of many yards;
total length of track apprbac-.hes, aiout
oto.Wi) feet. Theso figures do not ln
clude the great Brooklyn extcnsi^i by
way of the Battery tunnel, which ls al
ready under way: or- other >chemcs for
ihe exlenslon of the subway sorvlce,
tlthcrlmooted or ln actlve procoss of ex
ccutlon.
The Ptolcmles and tho thlrd Rameses
bullded monum?nts In their day, but
they did nothlng so vast as thls.
"f'n the days of the Caesars," sald u
New 'York englneer. "Pliny tells us It
took thlrty thousand men eleven weary
years to cut a tunnel three and a half
inlles long. To-day, employlng less than
twelve thousand men, the New York
masters of enginecrlng mechanlcs have
made a tunnel eqiial ln capaclty to one
of over flfty mllcs ln length llke that
of Rome, to. say nothlng of some ten
mllcs of elevated structurc ajid the ex
cavatlon of extra areas for nndergvound
s'tatlbns."
True, there are olher underground roads
In the. world; but, compared wlth thom,
thls one ls as "all Lombard-street to a
Chlna' oran'ge." Tho famous "twoperiny
tube" In Lopdon, for oxumple, about
oovers the dlstanco from the Battery to
Forty-sccond street, where the real
journey to tho end of the. llno is hnrdly
bcglnning.
Its Appalling Dimensions.
lt has been carefully est'imnted by en
plneers that lf the subway were a Blngle
tunnel slx feet hlgh ahd threo feet wide,
lt would reach from New York to Chl?
cago. The part exeavated through tho
tiolld rock would reach from the metropo
lis to Cleveland. "Three mllllon-cublc
yards of hole"?that is how one man
conneoted wlth the work summed lt up.
Wlille the excavatlons aro going on.
mllllons of ftet oflumbcr are, belng used
to prop up the streets so'that tue ordl
nary trafllc-can go on. All the englneers
engaged ln the. cnLerprlse are impressed
bv Its magnltude. and cannot help stop
ping now and then to Indulge in the
welroV.st klnd One of them' says that this tlmber ?n
ployed in the "falso work" would bulld
no fower than ten thousand two-story
framo houscs: whlle another asserts that
the rock talten out by the tunnel would
niako a respc-ctablc imltatlon ot the
Great Wall of Chlna, naniely, a struc
ture threo feet thick, slx feet hlgh, and
about flve hundred mlles long.
There -ls no. doubt a.bout lt?the New
York subway ls the greatest thlng of
Its kind 'that manklnd has yet done.
Was a Big Job.
Tho city of New York declded to have
tho subway constructed by contract and
leased to the contractdr for-flfty yearn
for nn annual rental of rather more than
the interest payable by tho city on the
bonds Issued to provide means for tho
constructlon. It is -hardly credlble, but
lt ls the fact that ot all the great con
tracting englneers ln the world only two
could be found to put ln blds for suoh a
vast. work. They were .lohu B. McDon
ald ahd Andrew Onderdonk.
McDomald askied for $35,000,000 In a
round sum. That was about the tigure
e-tlmated by tf>o cnglneer of tho Rapid
Transit Commisslon, "Wllliam Barclay
Paraona. Onderdpnk wanted JS9.300.W1
and certaln concesslons. lloDonald got
the job. and has carried lt outln a
manner that has met wlth the' enthu
slostic approval .of' many dlstingulshed
englncers who have Inspected hls w,ork.
"Rapld transit"?the elusivc dream Of
Xew Yorkers for so many years?wiil
be something more than a mere phrase
when tho subway ls runnlng full-blast.
It Is provlded by contract that local
tralns must run at an average-speed ot
not less than fourteen mlles ,an hour.
Including statlon stops;. whlle. expresses
must make thlrty mlles an hour. This
will easlly brlng people from Klngs
bridgc. at the northern polnt of Mnn
hnttan. down to the Clty Hali.In ..flfteen
minutes. Vlsltors from "out of town'-'
will no longer bc able to say. as; they
n.lways .do say howadays, "Come to
our clty and wc'll teach you how to
travel."
Close to the Surface.
IJnllko most underground roads, the
New York subway runs close to thesur
fnce. Throughout most 'of-tho length
fi-om the Battery to Harlem, lt ls only
four or flve feet below the street levelj
This makes tho excavation about twenty
feet ln depth. and the 'platforms of the
statlons are wlthin slxteen and elghteen
f.-et of the surface. The steps down from
the street to' the statlon are thus fewer
in number, as a rule, than those. up to
the present elevated statlons. Tho
problem of ventllatlon?always a- dltH
cult ono Jn underground Tallroads?ls
mucli slmptlfled by this nearncss to the
street, and- the fotil. atmosphere that
chokes the1 passongers.ln.JJohd'on's "two
penhy tub*-" need not be.feoreid.
The largesfstatioii on .the subway ls
the' Brooklyn -33ridge statlon. whlch. ls,
really the down town tcrminal. Its net-!
work of tracks rlvale the avera'ge ter?
minal In a falrly large city, iund a few
fest above lt rolls Interminably the
-hcavlest street tr'allic bf tho-!clty. in?
cludlng.many ele'ctric tar lines.. Stcal
beams, flve feet thlck, ho.ld. up tho lri
mense'weight of thls traflic.
From thls .fitation. at the .Brooklyn
Brldge' clear up to Thlrty^thlrd street
the hub of the linlverse-t'o. many New
Yorkers?.the subway oonsists of a four
track llne runnlng ln..- a slrigle tunriel.
Two tracks aro for expresses. and two
for' locals. It ls arranged that exprejs
tralns wlll run.-on expre'ss. tracks only,
and Iocal tralns on local tracks?an ex
celleht system; whlch dqes not now pre
vair on tho elevated rallways of Now
York city.
Have Double Tracks.
The road conslsts of. two doublo-track
tunn.els above Thirty-fourth streot, whlch
pass.on elther slde ot the.exlstlng,Park
avenue street rallway tunnel, but at a
tower.level. ManHattan,1s, lndeed.be
comlng honeycombed- ln' all' dlrectlons,
and the end of the tunn'elllng ls not yet
ln slght. New .Yorkers- ara llvlng ln
thlrty storles and; travolllng in three?
In tunhels, street /cars,' and elevated
tralns.
The subway follows Broadwny lo' One
Hundred and Fourth' street and there
dlvides into two llnes?ono on the East i
Slde and the: other on ;the West Slde.
At' two polnts before reaohlng One Hun?
dred and Fourth street .tho tunnel has
to'pass.urider tlie elevated rallway... and
the task'of holdlng'up the great-welght
of that gtructurc.;.whlle the tunnelllng
was golng on r was one. of the most'dirti
cult that-: the'-. ongineers had to face.
Downtown. they.dlved under"a Park.row
newspaper, offlce with such- a small jnnr
gln to sparo'that th'o erids of the presses
actually.projected over the tunnel, and
yet Were abl.e to keep.-runnlng 'wlthout
aiv hbu'r'a ioss of'-tlme. Another. tlck
llnh problem 'was to runMinderrieathi the
vaults of th'o New York postofflcc wlth
?Dut disturblng tho work golng on thero.
But lt' is not only tho underground
work of whlch tlio siibwoy englneers
have good' reason to be' proud. From
Ono Hundred andFoiirth'to One Hun?
dred and Sfxtee'nth. s't'roets ttiey havo
carried the llno on a- slngle "solld -con
crete arch ln an open cut, wlth a span
of forty-'two'. feet. This Is. technlcally
regarded as orie of th'o best pleces of
work of its charactcr everdone. At tho
end of this out comes the long, deep
dip known as-Manhattan Valjey; whlch
ls crossed'on an Imrnense elevated-steel
vladuct In -order to m'alntain the,' giVdo
of the llrie. From-Ono'Hundred and
Flfty-flfth street to Ono Hundrfcd and
Nlnetletli street tho' tunnel had to be
bored entirely through solld rock, and
this part of tho'work alono ls sald to be
the longest double-track railroad tunnel
ln tho' Unlted States.
Thousands at Work,
On an average the nrmy of subway
laborers has conslstod of about ten thous?
and inen durlng the. past four years,. and
the cost of cxcavatlng .toolc lip about
ono-thlrd of the entlre contract prlce of
$iS,Cup the gi-en.t part of the tlme. If it had
beeii drllled by band, the engfueers doubt
whether liio work could liavo boen dono
In a rtuartor of a centnry. Thero has
beon no such dlfflculty' In any prevtous
work of the kind. Tho Hiibways of J./011
doii and Pnrls Were cui. through clay.
and that of Boston through earth.
Many unexpected dtttleu+fles were met
with ln'the cptirso of tlie work. Ouc was
the Intorferejice, wlth' the dralnagc of
the clty?ninnlng suddenly up agnlnirt a
network ot sowers whlch scemed to el-;
Tectu'ally bl'ock the path. These wer*
problonis sufflcleiit to turn nn englneer's
hair gray. In one place, merely;as a
llttle alde lssuo of their business, tbe
makers' of the subway hud to change
tho system of drainago of a largo dis?
trlct, maklng tho sew.ers dral'n Into tho
East rlver Inctead of tho Harlem rlvor.
At another place they had to tear up
a network of street. car tr.u-ks and relay
them.
Tho subway will not bo a dark', mis
erablo. stuffy place, llke the London
Underground Railwny. It Is clenh and
whlto (throu_4hout, nnd wo -Ihorouglily
llghted by clcctriolty that It Is os .brlght
as' day everywherc. Tho statlons aro,
ln many cases, real works of art, and
all of'them aro con'vonlenl and coiiifort
able.
Tho glgnnllo. pow'er-liouso on Flfty
elghth and Flfty-nlnth streets, whlch
Plans Already Underway to Ex
tcnd tllc Underground Transit
in Manhattan and Brooklyn.
PROBLEM FOR ENGINEERS
Many of These Had to bc Dcalt
With in the Grcat Work?-The
Tracks and Stations.
vltall-/.ei tlie thlrd rall, ls a slnictur.
ot whlch tho tno.kcrs of the subway afo
Justlv protifk It has a frontoge of 300
feot' on Blfiventlt avenue and extends
wstward for nearly *0J feet, whlle tho
helght Is 12.1 feet. lt Is thifs one of tho
largcst buildlngs In Now York, und. ono
of tho Inrgest' power hous^s ln tho
world. The welght of the steel frame
work alono ls about. .12.000 tons. Tho to?
tal genernllng capaclty of the plant l?
about 130,000 horsc power. The thlrd
rh.ll system of elcctrlcal propulsion i 1*
to bo usod throughout.
Now Practically Complete.
The su'oway Is now practically eom
pieted throughout the entlre length of
Mnnhnttan.. It ls a great wOrk grcatl.v
done, .but It mu.it not be supposed that
lt has solved the vexed nuestlon of
trnnsportatlon ln the motropolls. En?
glneers and trairte. mann.gers fnmillnr
wlth enndltlons ln New York ibelleve that
it wlll bo at best merel.v a temporary and
partial relief to th* present unbcarablo
congcstlon of traflle. Thero wlll stlll, lu
all probablllty, ibe a jvast army ot
"strnp-hangr.rs"?on the subway Itseir,
as well as on tho elevated' and sur
fnce llnes. Other subways wlll havo to
.be bullt, nnd plans for them arn already
belng tcntatlvely prepared and consid
ered.
The Brooklyn .'oxtenslon iruns under
the East rtver' to Joralemon street,
Brooklyn. The Rapid Transit Commls
sion has already authorlzed an exten
skm of thls 'Brooklyn road to Prospecu
Park, and South Brooklyn has also be
gun to clamor for a branch and ls
ilkely to get It.
Tn many parts of Gr-eater New York
the publlc ls agltatlng for an extcn
slon of the orijrinal scheme of tho sub?
way). ;Tho iRrooklyn gxiterinlon i^ider
the Eant rlver. was not a part of that
origlnol scheme. wlilch ,\va8 doslgned
only to rellevo tho congestlon ot traflle
in Manhattan and the Brohx.
Other Work Under Ground.
The rallroad companios, especially ,the
Pennsylvania, nre also doing much tun
nelling lu Now York at the present tlmo,
and aro connccting. thoir systems with
tho subway. The Rapld Transit Board
has grautcd to lho Pennsylvania* ...ew;
Jersey and New York Rallroad Com?
pany and to tho Pennsylvania, New York
and Long lsland iRailroad Company.
jointly, frunchlses for a tunnel system;'
passing from VVeehawken, N. .T., acrbss
tho North rlver, rlght iinder Manhattan
lsland (along Thlrty-second and Thlrty
tlilrd streets),-aud thenco Into tho Bor
ough of'Queehs. There ls to be. a doublo
tunnel under the North rlver. Thls Penn?
sylvania extenslon will cost anout $?0,
000,000, and wlll be provldcd wlth what
has been descrlbed nt. "the most mas
sive rallroad depot yet concelved of."'
Four ftill-slzed city blocks have been
torn down to make way for it, and from
thls statlon threo tunnels wlll extend
under tho .East rlver Into ...e Horough
of Queens. Tho Pennsylvania wil. h??s.
havo direct communicatlon, .wlthout the
rilct of flodls, not only with Manhal-.
tun, but wlth the cxtromlties of Long
lsland. Tho, big statlon in the center
of Manhattan ls tb bo connccted wl/.h
the subway and the Grand Contval sta?
tlon.
Needs Not Yet Met.
They aro dolng great things ln New
York city to-day to brli'ig Father ICniri>
erbocker's chlldren down to work wlth?
out packhig thom llke herrlngs ln /a
barrel. .But, though tho dollars aro be
irig pourod out by the mlltlon every
month for the lmprovement of trahspor
tation' fa'cllltles, tho provlslon ls stlll
inadequate. to the need, and ls Ilkely to
remaln so for. many years to come.
Jt .ls Imposslblo to glve any exact fig?
ures on thls polnt of the relation of tha
provlslon to tho need. Even the dally
carrylng capaclty of the subway cannot
bc detormlned by ostlmate. Th? offlclnls
ln charge of tho enterprlse wlll each
glve you a dlfforent guess, all of whlch
aro away up Into the mllllons. Tho
vaflatlon ln these estlmatos ls explatn
ed by' the fact that some of them' are
based on tho seatlng capaclty of tho
cars whlch wlll be run, whlle others
aro foimdod on the demonstrated carry?
lng capaclty of tho elevated aud surraco
cars, with half their passeogers hanglns
on to straps in tho "rush hours."
(Copyrlght, 1W4, .by Bassett Stalnes.)</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030193/1911-05-25/ed-1/?sp=20&q=Subway&st=text&r=-0.139,-0.064,1.278,1.278,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>The Interboroug'h Offer Completes the City-Owned Subway. The Brooklyn Rapid Transit
Company Asks the City to Build Subways as Terminals for Its Elevated Railroads.
The Brooklyn Rapid Transit Company Proposes More Elevated
Roads for Brooklyn. The Interborough Builds Subways There.
WHAT THE INTERBOROUGH PLAN DOES FOR BROOKL YN
y TERBOROUGH.
20
EXISTING SUBWAYS
PROPOSED SU8WAYS,IM MEDIATE C Off STRUCT ON,
INTERBOROUGH AND CITY MONEY.
ocxxxxxxEUWRE EXTENSIONS TO SUBWAY SYSTEM.
wmmm SUBWAYS under constnuctoy.
ALL TO BE OPERATED BY iTERBOROUGH
FOR A SINGLE S CEiT
If V--. X A
m m (CV 4 11 S J x U
The Brooklyn Rapid Transit Company Offers to Reduce Fares to Manhattan at the City's
Expense, But Refuses to Reduce Fares to Coney Island at that Company's Expense.
This map shows what the Interborough Company has offered to
the City as a comprehensive subway plan. The lines shown in heay
broken lines can be immediately constructed and placed in opera
tion for a single five-cent subway fare in connection with the present
subway, the bridge Loop, and the Fourth Avenue Subway. The total
construction cost will be $198,788,650, of which the City pays
$110,320,150 for construction and the Interborough $88,478,500. The
Interborough supplies all of the equipment, which makes a total
contribution by the Interborough of $140, 824, SCO. The City's expen
diture under this plan is $58,000,000, leas than called for by the
Brooklyn Rapid Transit Company's plan.
The Interborough's plan establishes a universal five-cent subway
fare from Fort Hamilton, Coney Island. Shetpihead Bay, East New
York. Ridgewood, Wocdside, Coona, Astoria and all parts of the
Bronx. The Brooklyn Rapid Transit Company's plan establishes a
ten-cent fare within the Greater City ard for a great many of the
people in Queens, Manhattan and the Bronx a fii teen-cent fare to
Coney Island. The Brooklyn Company claims that it will make a
great saving to Brooklyn people by extending its lines into Manhat
tan, thus avoiding a double fare.
The Interborough Company, by going to Brooklyn for the
people with its numerous lines with a single fare, save more then
the Brooklyn Company claims to save, because on the Interborough
there will be a single fare to reach from every point in Brooklyn to
every point in Greater New York.
If the Brooklyn Rapid Transit Company is so interested in re
ducing the expenditures of the fare-payer, why do they insist in
A their proposition that for a short ride from Brooklyn to Coney
'""'md the lare must be ten cents
The Interborough has adopted the principle that a single five
cent fare paid on the subway system shall carry a person from one
end to the other of the Greater City of New York. On the other
hand, the Brooklyn Rapid Transit Company's plan proposes to
perpetuate a two-and three-fare system.
The Brooklyn Rapid Transit Company's proposal is that it will
spend less than $21,000,000 for construction in improving its eleva
ted lines in Brooklyn and placing third tracks thereon if the Greater
City of New York will pay about $168,000,000 of the taxpayers' money
for subway construction and connect it with the out-of-date eleva
ted lines in Brooklyn, provided further that all the receipts on the
Subways built by the taxpayers' money shall be used by the Brooklyn
Rapid Transit Company in establishing for all time a dividend on
many of the unprofitable elevated lines in Boooklyn.
The Interborough's plan proposes to extend the present City
Subway so that all the people in Brooklyn, including the outlying
districts, will be given a five-cent subway fare from one end to the
other ofthe Greater City of New York. If the Interborough's plan is
adopted by the City it will save $58,000,000 of the taxpayers' money
that the Brooklyn Rapid Transit Company's plan calls for, and this
$58,0C0,000, will construct the lines shown on this map to Rich
mend, to Jamaica and to Flushing, and if these lines are construc
ted there would still be $30,000,000 of the taxpayers' money saved by
accepting the Interborough's plan.
The Brooklyn Rapid Transit Co. advertises that it will take only
$73,500,000 of City money to construct the rapid transit lines which
it has been showing in heavy black lines on its advertising maps.
The misleading character of this talk about cost can be seen read
ily by lookinar at its offer of April 25th. in which it was stated that
the City's requirement of new capital would be $73,500,000 for the
lines then proposed.
Since that date and on May 1st the Brooklyn Company added
to its so-called original lines:
1. The Jerome Avenue extension to Jerome Park Reservoir.
2. The Southern Boulevard extension to the Bronx River.
3. Lines to Astoria and Corona.
4. The Nostrand Avenue extension.
5. The Livonia Avenue extension; and
6. The Fourteenth Street Tunnel to East New York.
But not a word has been said about the additional cost of these
lines. Every day since they were added the Brooklyn Company has
stuck to its original figure of $73,500,000. More than this, and still
further showing the deceptiveness of their advertisements, the
Brooklyn Company are placing upon their advertising maps in black
lines the following lines which they have riot even yet agreed to put
in their offer:
a i The Southern Boulevard line extending as far as Pelham
Bay Park.
(b) The Utica Avenue extension; and
(c) The Tunnel to Staten Island.
And still they seek to lead the public to believe that all the black
lines will cost the city only $73,500,000.
Now the facts are that the cost to the city of the lines first
mentioned by them will be $118,000,000.
The cost to the city, with their additions of May 1st, will run
up to $168,000,000.
The grand total cost to the city of their layout as advertised
will run up to $188,500,000.
rMfcall.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045487/1915-09-25/ed-1/?sp=31&q=New+York+Subway&st=text&r=-0.309,0.152,1.618,1.618,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>NEW YORK SUBWAY CAVE-IK
J i i irTMn Ssammnim 1 1 BJ
i.imuil nil I JJ f
frrngaww 7y
This shows the cave-in of the Seventh ave. subway at New York, in
which seven people were killed arid more than 100 injured. The cave-in1
cfollowed the premature explosion of a large blast of dynamite. Rescuers,
are shown in -the bed of -the. subway searching for victims. The construc
tion work gave way for a block, dropping three crowded care into chasm.
-o o-
WHAT WAS THE CAUSE-THEN7
Three physicians sard that Albert
$nd Joseph KIrsch, three and two
years old, had ded of ptemaine poi
soning anxl attributed it to the ice
cream which their father had bought
.them at a store at 2452 Cortez st
An inspector .from the health de
partment took a sample of the cream.
Several days later Kirsch visited tp.e
city hall to find out the outcome''of
the test He was told the sample had
-been destroyed.
Another sample was obtained and
tested. Dr. P. 0, Tonney said no poi
son was found, i</text>
    </results>
    <result>
    <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045487/1915-09-25/ed-1/?sp=31&q=New+York+Subway&st=text&r=-0.309,0.152,1.618,1.618,0/</id>
    <rel>1</rel>
    <text>SERIOUS SMASH-UP IN NEW
YORK SUBWAY TUNNEL
New York, Sept 29. One of the
most serious accidents in the his
tory of the New York subway sys
tem occurred early today when two
trains collided underneath 142d st,
the Bronx.
Three men received injuries which
are expected to prove fatal. The
trains took fire and, in fighting the
flames, 20 firemen were overcome by
the dense smoke which choked the
tunnel. 100 passengers on a train
following those which collided were
thrown into a panic and fought the
guards until the doors were opened.
They then walked seven blocks back
through the smoke-filled tunnel.
The injured men are all subway
employes They were removed to the
Fordham Hospital There it was stat
ed that they had a small chance for
recovery.</text>
   </result>
   <result>
      <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1918-08-02/ed-1/?sp=6&q=subWay&st=text&r=0.484,0.3,0.379,0.274,0/</id>
      <rel>1</rel>
      <text>Father Knickerbocker Lost at Times Square
As New Subway System Goes in Operation
THE "H"?THE CITY'S NEW SUBWAY SYSTEM
New York now has a double subway line traversing the city from north to south?the West Side, or Broadway line, and the East
Side, or Lexington Avenue line. They are shown in the above map, with the link between them, across Forty-second Street, forming the
cross-bar of the "H." Connection between the two lines will be made through the Forty-second Street shuttle.
The broken white lines indicate the old subway lines. The solid white lines show the new lines, parts of which have been in
operation for several weeks, but arc now joined with the old lines by the Forty-second Street shuttle to form a complete system. Only
express stations are indicated on the map.
Thousands Unable to Solve
Complexities Presented by
the *'H" in 42nd Street,
and as a Result Are Carried
Far in Directions Opposite
toThose They Wished to Go I
Shonts Says Traffic Conges-
tion in New York City Ten
Years Hence Will Be
Worse Than Now, Despite
All the New Improve?
ments and Facilities in Use
?Continued from page 1
spired and fnmed in their efforts to
make their directions heard above the
din of the hosts of inquirers. Their
ffforts were in large measure unavail?
ing and hundreds merely roamed about
the stavtion in search of some kind of
a train. Many gave it up and returned
to the street?when they could find
the way out.
People who wanted to go to the up?
per Eaat Sido and The Bronx could not
be made to understand that they
should take a shuttle train to the new
Lexington Avenue station, and some of
them found themselves at Brooklyn
Bridge or oth?er southern points on the
old subway before they discovered
their mistake. The reverse situation ex?
isted with marry who desired to go up?
town on the West Side, but. could not
solve the riddle of the shuttle service
at Times Square.
Transit officials expect a good deal of
confusion for a few days until passen?
gers grasp the significance of the new
routes and learn that a change from
the upper East Side or the upper West
Side line, to reach extreme points on
either side of the city downtown, means
a transfer at the nt:w Grand Central di?
agonal stations and the use of the shut?
tle service.
The confusion may be more serious
to-day and to-morrow when the rush
hour crowds start for work, but Inter?
borough officials said last night they
expected to clear up the situation in a
day a two when the through express
service on both new lines will be in
complete operation.
Shonts? Gloomy Forecast
While the scramble was going on at
Times Square President Shonts of the
Interborough. speaking at the Astor
Hotel, predicted that transit conges?
tion would he worse ten years hence
than it is now, despite the completion
of the new subways. _ Although it was
the biggest moment in the history of
New York transportation, Mr. Shents
said, the increase and concentration of
population in the city during the next
ten years would mean a return of con?
ditions on the transit lines worse than
they are now.
"So the phenomenon of crowded
cars," said Mr. Shonts, "is due to
causes quite beyond the control of
transit corporations. It is due to the
growing concentration of people in
great cities."
The Interborough president also
made a plea for increased fares on the
transit lines. He followed Oscar S.
Straus, former chairman of the Public
Service Commission, who said the ques- j
tion of six-cent fares was bound to
come up for serious consideration soon,
and that the city officials and members
of the Public Service Commission
should have the courage to errant the
increase, provided the condition of the
companies warranted it, even though it i
were not a popular move politically.
"The public official, be he President, j
Governor or Mayor," said Mr. Straus, j
"who has not the courage to act in an j
emergency in the face of political dis-1
approval is not fit to hold office."
Hylan as Motorman
Mayor Hylan, accompanied by other?
city officials; the Public Service Com?
missioners, Interborough officials, sub?
way engineers and a large party of
distinguished guests, made the first
trip on the new lines which marked
the opening of the "H" section. The
special train of ten cars left the diago?
nal station at Grand Central at 8:45
p. m. It ran down through the old
subway, made the loop at the Battery
and then passed up the new Seventh
Avenue line to Forty-second Street.
Headed by the subway band, the offi?
cial party marched from there to the
Astor Hotel.
Mayor Hylan acted as motorman of
the new train. Chairman Charles Bulk
ley Hubbell of the Public Service Com?
mission said afterward that if the
Mayor managed and operated the vari?
ous activities of the city government as
weil as he operated the train there
could be no complaint from the citi?
zens. Although the Mayor never was a
motorman he at one time piloted a
locomotive on the old B. K. T. elevated
lines, and that experience may have
helped him last night.
Before starting ?the train the Mayor
pushed a signal button at the station
which notified every other station on
the new lines that the "11" section was
in operation. A flashlight was then
taken of the Mayor standing at the
signal board with President Shonts,
Chairman Hubbell and Frank Hedley,
?general manager of the Interborough.
Chief Engineer Daniel L. Turner, of
the Public Service Commission, and
Chief Engineer George H. Pet-ram, of
the Interborough, a few minutes before
had walked down the track to the point
of actual connection between the old
and new lines and driven the last spike
which linked them together.
Speaker** at Exercise?
The official party reach"?) the Astor
Hotel at about 9:30, a little behind the
??chedulcd time. The speakers included
hairman Hubbell, who presided;
Mayor Hylan, Mr. Straus. Mr. Shonts,
Alfred K. Marling, president of the
Chamber hi Commerce; George Mc
Aoeny, former president of the Board
of Aldermen; William It. Willcox, for
mer ehairrnan of the Public Service
ommission, and Adolph S. Ochs.
A/t'-r paying a high tribute to the
ork of Mr. Hedley for
in making the new subway
possible, Chairman Hubbell
o?;.'"*; Mayor Hylan, who sat on
platform beside President Shonts.
?Mayor ?aid that he bad never
Btad the pleasure of enjoying a
ride a subway and sitting be?
ll'' Pres?d?-nt Short? all in the imme
gniftf, il*- -?aid th? hands and the
coring crowd at the Autor made him
sink for a moment that he was bark
n the city campaign of last fall. When
he reached the platform, however, and
?aw Commissioners Kracke and Whit?
ney there he realized that it wa? not
trije, he ??aid.
AM irUl?? m* tti&h. tt^uta to
the great engineering fent which had
been consummated by the opening of
the new lines. He said that although
he had opposed some things that had
been done in connection with the con?
struction of the new subways, he was
glad to be the chief magistrate of the
city at a time when one of the most
important sections of the new transit
lines was opened up.
People Deserve New Service
"I am sure the people of the eity
will be glad to know to-morrow that
the service on both the West Side and
East Side subways has become a fact,"
said the Mayor. "I have opposed from
time to time some of the things that
have been done in connection with sub?
way construction. I opposed the pres?
ent dual subway contracts because I
believed they would not be the best
thing for the people of the city, but
others in control thought differently,
and they prevailed.
"I have sometimes thought that the
transit corporations have been short?
sighted. The people put their money
in the construction of these subways,
and they are entitled to the best pos?
sible service. I am glad, however, to
be the chief magistrate of the city at
a time when this most important link
in the new transit system is opened
up."
Commissioner Hubbell introduced
former Chairman Straus as "the wiz?
ard of conciliators." Mr. Straus said
the "H" did not stand for what some
people might believe it to be-when
the word was not spelled out but that
it had been so called because it was
opened in the administration of Mayor
Hylan.
The former chairman said there was
a time when the Public Service Com?
mission and the city administration did
not get along very well, but he had had
a 'talk with the Mayor, and the latter
agreed with him that such a situation
should not exist?and the trouble
ended. He said it was due in large
measure to the change of front of the
Mayor and the hearty cooperation of
the city officials with the commission
that the new lines were finished and
opened at this time. Mr. Straus then
took up the question of the 6-cent fare
and discussed it wi'th all seriousness,
as a probable war necessity.
Prediction by Shonts
President Shonts followed Mr. Straus.
Referring to transit conditions to be
expected in 1928, the speaker said:
"This day marks a most important
chapter in the marvellous story of New
York City's rapid transit. But, much as
has been accomplished and stupendous
as are the figures by which we attempt
to tell the story of New York's trav?
elling hosts, the end of our undertak?
ing is not even in sight.
"In ten years there is every reason
to believe the city will have increased
to a point which will make the traffic
congestion of 1928 greater than that of
1918. History will repeat itself. Fol?
lowing every increase of transit facil?
ities in New York has come added pop?
ulation and greater congestion. Im?
proved facilities are one of the causes
of the city's added growth. If popu?
lation stood still we could catch up to
its demands. But it does not stand
still."
In regard to increased fares Mr
?Shonts said*.
"But the war has changed all these
calculations. In place of earning the
returns indicated large deficits have
arisen and larger ones are in sight.
How shall this situation be met? We
contend that it is an emergency and
should be treated as an emergency and
not by a method which will leave a
permanent effect upon business, upon
consequent movement of population
and upon property.
Two Methods Presented
"These deficits can be met in only
one of two ways?either by a higher
fare, throwing the burden upon the
people who actually get the benefit of
the increased service, or by taxation,
which will fall upon the already over?
burdened real estate owners, which
will result in increased rents, increased
grocers' bills and increased cost ol
living generally to all the people who
work and spend their incomes in New
York. Wherea3 if it is met by higher
fares not only would it lall upoti
those citizens of New York who re?
ceive the benefit of the service, but
also upon .300,000 daily visitors to the
city, who pay 500,000 fares a day and
who do not live in New York and do
not help pay her taxes.
"So while the proposition of in?
creased fares in the city aroused op?
position at first, I cannot help but be?
lieve that serious 'hought will con?
vince every unprejudiced student of
the question it is fundamental^
better for the interests of the city that
the situation which now confronts us,
and which is of a very serious and
i critical nature, should be met by in
j creased fares rather than by taxation
How to Reach Your
Destination on New
"H" Subway Lines
The opening of the Lexington Ave
nue subway last night having completed
the transformation of New York's old
I subway system, which was shaped like
the crank of a Ford, into the new "II"
system, the Public Service Commission
has iHHued a pamphlet to instruct a
i public accustomed to the crank to the
intelligent une of the "H." The two
upright? of the "H" are known as the
Werft Side subway and the East Sida
subway, while the crankshaft of the old
subway from the Grand Central station
to Times Kquare forms the crossbar of
th? "H."
A (Shuttle acrvice ?will t>e operated
?long the crossbar while through trains
will run along the uprights of the "H."
The righthand upright or East Side
?ubway is composed of the old subway
from the Battery and Atlantic Avenue,
Brooklyn, terminals to tho Grand Cen?
tral station arid the Lexington Avenue
extension to the northward.
Thnot th? pi?. ?r?nd Cf?BUai exfijrcB? ?U
tion, but a new one known as the Diag?
onal Station, which is on a lower level.
The old one will be used solely for the
shuttle service to Times Square.
North of the new Grand Central sta?
tion, the East Side subway turns into
Lexington Avenue, continuing to and
under the Harlem River into the Bronx,
with express stations at Eighty-sixth
Street and at 125th Street and local
stations as follows: Fifty-first Street,
Fifty-ninth Street, Sixty-eighth Street,
Hunter College, Seventy-seventh Street,
Ninety-sixth Street, 103d Street, 110th
Street and 116th Street.
Near 136th Street the line forks to
form the Jerome Avenue branch and
the Pelham Bay Park branch, but the
point of transfer for trains on these
two branches on the East Side, subway
is at the 125th Street station, the
equivalent in this respect of the situa?
tion existing as to the Broadway and
Lerfox Avenue branches at Ninety-sixth
Street on the old subway. The West
Farms trains in the East Side subway
will continue up Jerome Avenue to
149th Street, where they are to be di?
verted to the West Farms branch.
Most of the West. Farms trains car?
rying passengers for that branch and
for the White Plains Road extension
will use. thi6 route; the rest will be
operated over the West Side subway.
The Pelham Bay Park branch is only
partly finished, its completion having
been delayed by governmental demands
for labor and material.
If you take a subway train on the
Jerome Avenue branch (elevated rail?
road trains also will be operated over
this line above 162d Street) it will con?
vey you down through the new Lexing?
ton Avenue subway to Forty-second
Street and thence direct, via the old
subway, to the Battery or to Brooklyn.
If you take a subway train on the
West Farms branch (elevated trains
are operated over a part of this line)
designated for the East Side subway,
it will leave this branch at Mott Ave
ruie-149th Street and proceed south?
bound as indicated in the preceding
paragraph.
For the present, the Pelham Bay
Park branch will be operated only to
and from the Third Avenue station.
Service on this branch will proceed
through the. new Lexington Avenue
subway and so on downtown via the
old subway. The first station reached
on the main line, after leaving Third
Avenue station, is 125th Street, the
point of change for Jerome Avenue and
West Farms branches.
If you wish to go from East Side sub?
way to the Queensboro subway, trans?
fer at Grand Central station to Queens?
boro train on the lower level.
If you take a train on the old sub?
way in Brooklyn or at the Battery or
other stations in Manhattan, it will
convey you uptown through the old
subway, south of Forty-second Street,
then through the new Lexington Ave?
nue subway, and, accordingly as the
train is designated, to one of three
branches in the Bronx- the Jerome
Avenue branch, to the West Farms
branch ("West. Side subway) and the
Pelham Bay Park branch.
If you take a train designated for
I the wrong branch, change cars at 125th
Street.
If you wish to go from East Side
subway to the Queensboro subway,
change at Grand Central Station to
Queensboro train, lower level.
If you wish to transfer to the Third
Avenue elevated railroad, transfer
from West Farms branch at 149th
Street and Third Avenue.
If you desire to reach a point on the
West Side subway, transfer to shuttle
at Grand Central Station, and re
transfer, at Times Square southbound,
for points on new Seventh Avenue sub?
way and, northbound, for points on old
subWay north of Forty-second Street.
The left-hand upright of the "11" or
West Side subway consists of the old
Broadway and Lenox Avenue lines
from Times Square northward and the
new Seventh Avenue subway, which
joins the old subway just north of a
new Times Square express station,
which replaces the old Times Square
local station close by.
North of Times Square, the stations
are the old ones to which the public
has become accustomed. South from
Times Square on the Seventh Avenue
subway the first station reached is the
Pennsylvania express station, between
which and the Times Square station
shuttle trains have been in operation
for more than a year. Other express
stations are at Fourteenth Street and
at Chambers Street.
Local West Side Stations
The local stations are Twenty-eighth
Street, Twenty-third Street, Eighteenth
Street, Christopher Street-Sheridan
Square, Houston Street, Canal Street,
Franklin Street and Cortlandt Street,
Rector Street and City Hall (going to
the Battery) and Park Place, Fulton
Street and Wall Street (on the Brook?
lyn branch 1.
If you take a train on the Broadway
branch, West Side subway, it will con?
vey you down through the old subway
to Forty-second Street, 'hence direct
down Seventh Avenue, Varick Street,
West Broadway and Greenwich Street
to the Battery or through the Park
Place-William Street branch to Wall
Street.
If you wish to go to Brooklyn or to
any point on the old subway south of
Forty-second Street, transfer from the
West Side subway at Times Square to
tl shuttle service across Forty-second
Street and retransfer at Grand Central
Station, southbound, to train desig
nat'^d properly for destination you
wish to reach.
If you wish to go from the West
Side subway to the new Lexington
Avenue subway, north of Forty-second
Street, or to its Pelham Bay Park
branch, transfer to the shuttle train at
Times Square r.nd retrarnfer, north?
bound, at Grand Central Station, to
train properly designated for destina?
tion you wish to reach.
If you wish to go from '.he West Side
subway to the Queensboro subway,
transfer to the shuttle train at Times
Square, and retransfer at Grand Cen?
tral Station to the Queensboro subway
train on the lower level.
West Farms Train
About half the trains on the Lenox
Avenue-West Farms branch will be
routed through the West Side subway,
similar to present operation. (From
Mott Avenue or stations further east
on this branch the most direct way to
reach points on the new Lexington
Avenue subway or on the old subway
south of Forty-second -5tr.*et, or on the
old subway in Brooklyn, is to tak?> an
East Side subway train direct.) Such
trains will bo switched from the West
Farms branch at Mott Avenue and
14yth Street and proceed directly down?
town through the East Side subway.
If you take a train on the Seventh
Avenue subway with Brooklyn as your
destination it will be necessary to go
to Times Square, change to a shuttlo
train and transfer again at the Grand
Central Station to a southbound train
properly designated for your destina?
tion. For points in Manhattan south
of the City Hall, east and west side
subways offer practically the same fa?
cilities.
Going uptown, if you take a train
on either the Park Place, William
Street or Battery branches of the Sev?
enth Avenue subway, on the main line
of the Seventh Avenue subway or north
of Times Square on the old subway, it
will take you up the Broadway or West
Farms branch, according to which train
you take. From the West Farms
branch access may be had as hereto?
fore at Mott Avenue and 149th Street
to trains on the Jerome Avenue branch
of the East Side subway to trains of the
Third Avenue elevated line at Third
Avenue and 149th Street and to trains
of the White Plains Road extension at
177th Street.
All passengers who can avoid doinp;
so are urged not to transfer from one
upright of the "H" to the other, but to
utilize through train service to the ut?
most in the interest, of efficient service.
??H??IW?^?????Ml?^??l. ?I??I.?MII?.?MM?</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030272/1913-12-28/ed-1/?sp=17&q=Subway&st=text&r=-0.236,-0.1,1.472,1.472,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>NEW YORK, SUNDAY, DECEMBER 28, 1913 Copyright, 1913, fcj the .'nu Printing PuMlsalim Aatoclntu.
NEW YORK CITY TO GO FORWARD ONCE MORE
STIMULATED BY GREAT NEW TRANSIT SYSTEM
Fortunes Greater Than Those Created
by the Present Subway Expected to
Result From the Demand for Prop
erty Along the 324 Miles of New Lines
11 r imw.win k. mocam..
halrataa of the Public Scrxlce
Commlmlon.
As Tar n 1 can judge the real entitle
outlook for tho year 101 1 if more promising
than It hag lieon fur ninny yearn. This
I say In vtaw of the tremendous trniif It
improvements which the city of New
Vork is now making ami Ihe efiect of
which bhould ho felt during the year 101 1
I ho construction of sulrwuys and ele
vated railroads invariably bus liroiiKht
about, a large increase, in the value of
ie.il property. esieciully In territory
previously deficient in transportation
lacilities The dual system or rapid
transit wo expect to see in complete
operation hy January 1. 101" The Inter
vening three years, therofote, should
bring about the development of muny
hitherto neglected sections of tho city,
as well uh increased values in sections
iilivudy built up. If we could bee to-day
tho figures wliich will npvear on Ihe as
sessment books four years hence I urn
sure they would startle even the moitt
optimistic of real estate oierutor's.
We know what a stimulus Ihe existing
subway proved to valuations in Man
hattan and The Bronx, uud we have every
reason to believe thut history will rewat
itsslf when tho new lines now under
construction are completed and placed
in oieratioii, Tho existing subway all
told has only ubmit t-evenly-live miles
of (.ingle track The new com miction
alone of the dual system will add XM
miles of single track to the existing lines,
lint system will embrace the existing
-ithway, the existing elevated lines in
Manhattan and The Bronx and the ex
isting elevated railroads in Brooklyn,
with a total or '.'Wl miles of single tniek.
With the 3:l miles of new construction the
whole system will have a trackage of
miles, which will lie divided fr operation
between the luterborottgh Rapid Transit
lompany and the New Yoik Municipal
K-iilway CorHjration
llefote this -Vslein can be placed in
operation the city of New York and the
two operating companies wilt have ox
Iwiided moie than tMn.mw.uni) for con
struction nnd equipment Even in Ihe
linancial capital of the riche-t nation or
ihe world, where transactions involving
millions are of coiiimou occurrence, this
i a stupendous total for disbursement
within four short years, ll i- more than
one-third of the national debt, and it is
about tho cost of the Panama Canal
Suoh an amount of money invested in a
publin improvement anywhere in the
world must be followed by great benefit
t the surrounding prorty
When the existing subway was built
its two branches in 'Ihe lirnux, viz., the
Broadway division und the Iamiox avenue
division, projected largely into unde
veloped territory A study of the real
estate vulues of vacant lots in this terri
tory for the year louo, four years prior
to the opening of the subway, shows the
increase in valuations brnuuht about by
t lie opera; ion of the subwuy Comparison
of these values with Ihe assessed valua
tions in 1907, a little more than two years
alter the subway begun operation, shows
Mil astounding increase In the territory
opened up bv the Broadway brunch
valuations between Kt.'tli street and
spuyten Duyvil from iwmto Itw; increased 1
about MtCluo.tiOo. 'I lie normal increase of i
he previous seven years was estimated
.it lhO.000, which, subtrai ted I rum ihe
IW7 valuations, shows the increase due'
to the building of the Midway to have
been about JUV.'ou.imni. 'Ibis was an in-1
i tease of KM er cent in seven years,,
l roerty ueveIo'd ly Hie i.enox avenue
blanch made a similar showing. The
aggregate increase for the seven yeurs in
the district lrom tho llurlem Kiver to
brum I'ark (.vacant lots) woa about
Jlt.soo.ono, As the normal increase for
the previous seven years was estimated
at JlU.WO.OOO, this showed an increase of
XII.SW.ooo apparently duo to Ihe building
of the subwuy. 1 nee no reason why a
similar increase in values should not
billow the opening up of the dual system
in undeveloHid or partially developed
sections.
1 am glad to be able to state that con
struction work on the dual system is pro
gressing rapidly. There is now under con
t met ion newly $eo,0oo,ouo worth of work
nail before the new year is two months
old this total will be increased to more
than HOO.OUO.OOO. This means that more
than half of the work which the City of
Vw York is to puy for in I lie new system
is already under contract. This work is
being done by eighteen different con
tractors who employ all told a daily force
ol about 7,000 men. For tho year 101S up
'o tho 15th of December the City of New
nrk had paid these contractors a total of
nearly $15,000,000, so that the new work
i- already putting into circulation more
i ha u $!,noo,00n of new money every month
I he average expenditure for 1014 will be
e en larger, so thut the construction of
this groat work is already proving on im
portant factor in tho employment of labor
and tho promotion of the general pros
perity. While the dual system will extend rapid
transit facilities lo many undeveloped
sections, it will also relieve present con
'.Mioii in most of Ihe developed portions
of the city. Even streets in the old city
ol Vow York, away down in the financial
district or Manhuttan, will be tunnelled
to miiliu space for the tracks which will
i.njiat.i under rivers and over miles of
and to tho remotest districts of Brooklyn.
Queens and The Hronx. The system will
have two grand divisions, one to be oper
ated by the Jnterboroush lUpid Transit
i ompany and the other by the New York
Municipal Hallway Corporal ion. Iu tho
Interborough territory important uddi
"e will bo made lu ihe subway and ele
v.ited lines it now operate. I'ho nib
y runs lrom 1 lall iish and Atlantic
venues in Brooklyn under the East Hirer
to Manhattan and up tho Kut Side of
.Manhattan Island to Forty-second street
at the Grand Central Station, where It
turns westward and runs through Forty
seoond 'street to Broudway ut 'limes
Square, and thenco continues up Broad
way to Ninety-sixth, where it divides into
two branches, the westorly branch con
tinuing up Broadway and across the Har
lam River to Von Cortlandt I'ark or
342d street and the easterly branch run
ning out Lenox avenue and other afreets
to Bronx Park or 180th atreet. The line
from Brooklyn Bridge to Nluety-slxth
street la a four track road upon which
both express and local trains are operated,
Ihe dual system plans call for the exten
sion of this subwuy from Forty -second
street at the Grand Central Stutlon, up
Lexington avenue, un Mast Side thorough-
faro, to tho Harlem Hiver as a four truck
road, Hero the line, will diride Into two I
branches, ihe westerly branch running
through Moll, JUver and It tome avenues
to Wood lawn road and the easterly brunch
through Southern Boulevard und West
Chester uvenue lo l'elham Bay I'ark Each
of these branches will be u three track
road.
On the West Side, beginning nl Tunes
Square, there will be an extension down
Seventh uvenue, Vuriek slieef. West
Broudwav and Greenwich stieet to the
Battery. This also will lie a four track
lino from Tunes Square to I'.irlc pl.ic".
where two tracks will divcige to lliooklyu
und the other two continue on to the
Battery uud u junction wllji tho existing
subwuy loop under Battery I'ark. The
two truoks diverging ut I'ark place will
oontinue through I'ark place under the
Post Oflloe building to Beekiuun street,
through Beekman street to William street
and down William st reet to Old Slip, where
they will enter tho tunnol lo bo built
under the Eust Iliver to Clark street,
Brooklyn, and a connection with tho ex
isting subway near Borougii Hull, Brook
lyn, The subway which now ends at
Flatbush and Atluntio avenues will also
be extended out Flatbush avenue to
Eastern Parkway uud through Eastern
Parkway to Buffalo uvenue. This will bo
a four track road. 1'rom Buffalo fcvenUe
au extension will be built thiough Kasi
Ninety-eighth street to blvonia avenue
and out blvonia avenue to New Lots road.
This extension will be a three track line.
Front this brief sketch of the routes it
will be seen that the additions lo t ,ie exist
ing subway will more than double lt
pie-ent facilities, By the building of the
Lexington avenue line north or Forty
second street and joining It to the e: isting
subway south or thut street the 'liter
borough will have for operation n com
plete, four track lino up and down the
The Spirit of New York
East Side from Brooklyn Bridge to the
Ifnrlem Hiver. Similarly by building the
Seventh uvenue subway south of Forty
second street und attaching it to the
existing subwuy in Broudway north of
that street the company will have a com
plete West Side lino from I'ark place to
Ninety-sixth street. Instead of having
four trucks bet weed Brooklyn Bridge
and Ninety-sixth street, us ut present,
the now system, therefore, will have eight
truoks between those points, practically
a duplication of tho existing subwuy.
In 'I'he Bronx ihe existing brunches of
the subway have only two trucks each,
although in places there are three tracks,
but for operating purposes ihey may be
considered two truck lines As Ih.i now
line up Jerome avenue and the new lino
out .Southern Boulevard und Westchester
avenue will have three tracks each, It is
apMirent that these two branches of the
Lexington uvenue subway alone will nunc
than double Ihe present subway facilities
lu The Bronx, lu uddition, however, Ihe
dual system plans ,i for the extension
or tiie Lenox avenue branch of the exist
ing subway from isuih stieet out White
Plums, raid lo 2 list street, very near the
northerly city line. As tills ulso will be n
three track road the three new subway
hues iu I'he Bronx will provide s total or
nine trucks, us ugaiiisi I our on i he existing
subway. The subway facilities ulon
therelore, iu tliat borough will be more
than trebled,
Extensions to the elevuted railroads
operulod by the luterliorough Company
will further amplify the facilities of those
important agencies of transportation. At
present I hero urn two elevated lines on the
West Side und two on the East Side of
Munhuttun The West Side lines ure tho
Ninth nnd Sixth uvenue systems. Whilo
both art operated from the Buttery to the
Harlem Hlvou at l.Vith street, they are
cm te lines only south of Fifty-third
street Norlhofthal point Ihereureonly
three tracks u-cit iu common by trains
from both lines, The Ninth avenue lino
now bus a third truck for express service
Public Service Commission Pushing Work
on Entire $360,000,000 Improvement
About Which Centre Hopes of All
Realty Owners in Greater City
extending from Christopher stieet on the
south to IIHtli street on the 1101 th Under
the dual system plans this third track will
he extended lo Bulleiy place on the south
uud lo iMlh street on the north, mi that
through express service will lie possible
for the entire length of the present line,
In addition the Ninth avenue linn will bo
connected at 15Mb street with tho pio
poscd elevuted branch of tho Lexington
avenue subway in .lerome uvenue, which
will be used jointly by elevated uud bub
wuy trains. When this is done travellers
on tho West Side elevated roads will bo
enabled lo go from downtown .Mauliatlun
to Woodlawn roud without chanvnof cars.
Of the East Side elevated roads the
Second uvenue line ha- no third Hack
whatever The Third uvenue line has u
third track from Forty second stieet In,
(he llurlem Iliver at With street The
I necessity for switching express trains lo
the local tracks south of Forty-second is
one of the grout defects of present opera
tion. Under the dual system this wilt be
remedied by the extension of the third
track from Forty-second street down to
City Hall There will also be a third track
added to the Second avenue line for its
entire length below the Harlem River
The Third avenue line will be third tracked
also ucross the Harlem and as far as Pel-
lia 111 avenue An extension of this lino will
also be built from the present terminus
north through Webster uvcnuo to Gun Hill
1 road and through Ouu Hill road to White
I'liiin- road, where a junction will be made
witli the extension of tho Lenox avenue
I subway to 311st street. This extension,
like -loroiiip avenue, will lie used jointly by
subway ami elevated truins. so that when
I I lie system is completed it will bo possible
for a piiKfecugor to travel on tho elevated
line or the subway from tho City Hall lo
:isi street without chunge or cum and
lor n single raie.
i The InterlKiioiigh lines will also l
extended into the Borough of Queens,
which up to the present time lids never
enjoyed rapid transit except such as is
possible through the Pennsylvania tun-
i uels. The city is now building for opera
tion by the Intcrborough, witlt trackage
rights also to the New York Municipal
Hallway Coiporation, two important lines
in Queens borough Both begin ut Queens-
Isiro Bridge, and ono runs north
i through Second avenue to Oil mars ave
ntle, Astoria, and the other through
Koo-evelt uvenue to Corona und Flush
i lie. and each will be a three track ele-
v.i led ruilroud. 'Ihe Ititerborough com
pany will extend the Second avenue ele
vated line to uud over the Queensboro
Bridge lo connect with these new lines,
over which it will oKrate elevated trains
I l rom the Second avenue system. The
city alo is building an extension to the
I Steinwuy tunnel from its piesent terminus
in Long Islund City to the Queensboro
Bridge plaza. This extension also will
join the new Queens lines so that tho ln
iterborough will be enabled to run trains
from the .Steinway tunnel to Astoria
nnd to Flushing. The Steinwuy tunnel
al-o will be extended lai the .Manhattan
ide through Forty-second street to
Times Sqiiaie and u junction with the
existing subway, so that eventually it will
be possible for train- starling ut un
Cortlandt Park to pass through the Stein
way tunnel and over tne new lines lo
A-toiia and Flushing
Tne mere statement of Ihe extent to
which the luterliorough lines are to be
eviandeil i-. siifticienl lo convince any
me that the dual system will work n
i evolution in transportation facilities iu
i lie field now covered by that system.
No one can now predict the full ex
lent of the benefits which will follow.
Il will icm.iin for uctual operation to
-bow the degree of benefit which this
i great improvement will confer.
In the Brooklyn field no less of a traffic
revolution will follow the completion of
the dual system This territory is now
served mainly Wy the lines of the Brooklyn
liupid Tiaiisil Coinpanv This company,
under the name of the New York Municipal
Itiiilw iv Coiporation, has madeii contract
with the City of New ,urk to connect it
existing lines witli new lines lo ls buill by
the city and to operate them as one sys
tem At present the Brooklyn elevated
railroads cover in.", miles of single track.
I'lnler Ihe dual system the enmpuny will
have for otorut inn HI Millie of single track.
The lliooklyu elevated roads now enter
Williamsburg Budge Cnder the new sys
tem they will Imve additional entrances
iliioiub two new tunnel.', under the East
Kiver nnd ov er the Manhattan Bridge A I
pieent(.ill such lines tei initiate at Ihe
two bridge- named, so thai passengers
mii-t pay another faro to leach uny other
pal I of Manhattan The dual system will
provide the lliooklyu company with two
tiewsudwuys in Manhattan through which
the entile Unfile ut the Brooklyn elevated
railioads can ls dirliibuted without the
payment of an additional tare, One of
Ihse subways i- the Centre street loop
and Ihe oilier the Broadway subway, Tho
Centre street loop is ulready completed
from the Manhattun end or the Brooklyn
Biidge north through Centre street to
IMiincey stieet extension, uud through
heluncey street extension to the Williams
burg Undue, with a spur at Canal street
connecting with the .Mitnliuttuii Bridge,
I Ins .pur is now lieing connected with t tie
Brooklyn Bridge and will soon bccxlondrd
down Nassau slieei to Broad street, and
a conneclion with the proposed tunnel
under the East Hiver from Whitehall
street, Manhuttan, lo Montague street,
Brooklyn, and u connection with the
l'ouilli avenue subway in Brooklyn.
The Broudwuy subway will also lie con
nected with this tunnel lino und will
extend up Trinity plate uud Church
Nlieel lo Veey street, through Vesey
Mi eel to Bioiidvvay and up Broadway
to Forty-second stieet ut Times Square
'and thence up Seventh uvenue to Flfty
iiiiilh street From Cunui street lo
I'oi l y. second sheet Ihis subway will be
a four track road. At Fifty-ninth street
two tracks will terminate and two tracks
.will continue eastward through Fifty-
ninth and Sixtieth streets to nna over tne
Queensboro Bridge and n connection with
the new rnpid transit line! in Queens
llOI'OIIR.I.
The Centre stieet loop subway is the
11 1 si part of the dual system to be placed
iu operation. Since August 4 lust the
Brooklyn company bus been opcratiiw
all its elevated trains coining tmiu ui-s
Williutiiburg Bridge through this sub
way For this purpose only the two
westerly tracks In the loop subway I
being used, und the other two tracks will
remain idle uiililhe conneclion with the
Hiool.l.-n Undue is completed 'I he pre,
cut operation, however, has greatly re
lieved the ciusli on the Brooklyn Biidge,
L'OllllMUtll uu
Hctvnd</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030272/1910-10-05/ed-1/?sp=5&q=Subway&st=text&r=0.069,0.641,0.866,0.627,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>The Subway Store at Gimbels GimbelsTwo
Two Stories High Below the Street Level
I
I II IIi
i This Subway Store Is So Totally Unlike Any AnyOther AnyOther AnyI AnyOther
Other in the World that You Will Never NeverRealize NeverRealize NeverRealize
I Realize that You Are in a Basement at All I
I II I When we planned the Gimbel Store we spent spentmonths spentmonths I Imonths
months over the problem of making a Basement BasementSalesroom BasementSalesroom j ji
i Salesroom as bright and cheery as any aboveground above aboveground I Ii
i ground section sectionWith sectionVith sectionVith
Vith the help of the ablest architects in Amer America AmerI AmerI Amcrica I
I ica we succeeded succeededGone succeededGone succeededGone
Gone are the lowhanging ceilings the dim dimlights dimtights dimt
t lights the deep shadows the stuffy atmosphere and andthe andthe i ithe
the musty corners of the oldfashioned old basement basementGone basetl1entI
I
I Gone are the oldfashioned old methods of basemerit base basement basement
ment merchandising the collection of odds and andends andends andends
ends and unpleasant trash the slipshod careless carelessservice carelessservice I Iservice
service the general air of cheapness pushed to toits toI
I 3 its worst worstYou worstI worstYou worstYou I
I You will look in vain for any of these at Gimbels GimbelsOurs GiJTIbelsOurs Gimbelsj
j Ours is a big bright handsome store of ofI
I
TWO selling floors occupying a space of over one onehundred onehundred onehundred
hundred and fifty thousand square feet feetPowerful feetPowerful feetPowerful
Powerful pumps working through an elaborate elaborateventilation elaborateventilation elaborateventilation
ventilation system change the air in the Subway SubwayStore SubwayStore SubwayStore
Store completely every ten to twelve minutes Even Evenwith Evenwith Evenwith
with the throngs of the past few days the air is isalways isalways isalways
always as pure as it is outside and the temperature temperaturenever
never more than four degrees higher higherua a triumph in inventilating inventilating inventilating
ventilating engineering engineeringAnd
And in the Subway Store you will find broad broadvarieties broadvarieties broadvarieties
varieties of almost all lines I of merchandise carried carriedin I Iin
in the upper floors duplicated in the less expensive expensivegrades expensivegrades expensivegrades
grades every pennys worth Reliable every pennys pennysworth pennysworth
worth a full measure of value every ounce and inch inchof inchof inchof
of it good clean inexpensive but worth having havingThe havingThe havingThe
The same service the same ideals the same samestandards samestandards samestandards
standards prevail in the Subway Store as else elsewhere elsewhere elsewhere
where in this house and everything in it is NEW</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1904-09-04/ed-1/?sp=25&st=text&r=-0.306,0.051,1.63,1.18,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>It is the subway station at Twenty-third-st and Fourth-ava. Behind the brick pillars at the left Is
the basement of a building In Fourth-aye. This basement now has a fine, light front on the sub
way, and will be rented at a high figure as one larye shop or several small ones.</text>
     </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1922-08-28/ed-1/?sp=1&st=text&r=-0.023,0.177,1.017,0.736,0/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn82014760/1861-10-31/ed-1/?sp=3&q=Halloween+Hallow+Hallowmas&st=text&r=0.001,0.563,0.366,0.265,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Mean are olroulated among tha floating pnputa
tton every day.besides thelarge number served
to regular subscribers. Advertisers will late
note accordingly.
Alt Hallow Ke.
To-night Is it!) IUItoto Tee, or Hallow n'en,
as being tlie vigil or ove uf Ml Hallow Day
Tbe Jlomlsh Church designed this day to bo
held In boner nf all those taints who had not
particular days appointed for them, but Ittloes
not appear that All nallowD,iy,or Its eye, oro
ever marked by very particular observance
In the Cathollo ohurchj novertholess. there
Is Boarooly any tlmo more distinguished by the
common feoplo of many portions uf the Brlltsh
Kinging of bells was one of tho modes of
celebrating Hallowmas m tngiana in umos piuii.
It whs a Itoman Oathn.lo practice, being da
signed In aomo way to flvr the souls or de
parted Christians. For this reason, Queon
Elizabeth prohibited It. It was also A custom,
a few centuries ago, to have a cake oaken on
this eve for overy member of the family, ns a
tout mass cake or soul cake. It was oomposod
of natmeal, and seoded; and pasties and fur
mety were Incidental to tho samo evening. In
families of good condition, a quantity were
hfllrnn unit ant nn on a board, liko tbe shew-
bread In old pictures In tbo Bible, to bo given
tp visiters, or distributed among the poor.
Thero was a rhymo for tbe ocoaslon A soul
cako a soul cake 1 Havo mercy on uu uuns
Man snult lor a soul-oaks I" Poonle went from
parish to parish o soulinj. as they oalled II,
that Is, begklng In a kind of ohant for soul
oakes, or anything to in ike them merry on this
eve.
Essentially oonnooted with all these oustom
are thoso bettor known ones which Burns has
so well and so faithfully described In his peem
of Halloween.
J.an I'll In twa wl1 tentlo ec,
Wha 'twas ihe wadna tell,
But this Is Ji ck and thli Is m,
She says Into hersel';
He b.eetod owre her, and she owre him,
A ihey wad ne'er mlr part,
Till fuITI ne started up the lum,
And Jean hid e'eu tiir h'art
To see't that night.
Nuts, besides being thus used for divination,
are crackod and eaten, and hence, In tho north
of England, AH Hallow Evo Is often oalled A'ul
crack Night. Apples are also extensively eaten,
tMd nimunmnt nt fruit havlnc: nrobahlv some
reforenoe to the heather, charaotor of the day,
as that or thanksgiving rortne proauco oi uie
aiann tha fortnn telllnc customs desorlbed
by Burns, besides the above are for tho girls to
pull stalks from a oorn-stallc, and ascertalii.lrom
tho presence or absenoe of the top pickle, an
Interesting point In their moral history for a
sntitartr 'amain to co to a kiln, and throwing a
blue clue Into the pot to wind It, expecting that
era finished It will oe neia duos, wnen, oy id
nuirim' who holds, a rcsuonse will ba obtalnod
dlsoloslng the name or the future husband to
eat an npple at a looking-glass, expecting to see
a vision ot the future husband peeping ovor the
shoulilor to sow liomp seea in uie yarn, say
ing, Hemp soed,1 s.iw thee, hemp seed, Isaw
thee, and her that Is to be my true love oome
after me and draw thee," expeotlng that, on
looking over the ahouldor, a vision will be ob
tulncdof the future spouse In the act of pulling
growrl hemp to win three weohta o' naetblng
In tho baru, expeotlng to see a like vision to
fathom a barley staok thrice, expecting at last
n afflhnita vrnur mistress to dlnashlrt sloeve
In a rivulet at the meeting point of the lands of
three proprietors, ana men nargit oyiue ure
tn iirr. triistlnf to see nuoh a visionary person
come In ani turn the other side to pull sulks
of dece.eed oabbages, blindfolded, without
choice, and augur, from their stralghtnes or
crookedness, the figure of tbo futuro spouse,
r-nn. tnt. Aut-rn urninn (innra u lull iuui. luo
fortune she will bring, and from the taste of
the heart, her temper Anally, to set threo
dishes on the door, one empty, one with oloan,
and one with foul water, and oause the oompany
to Bpproaoh them blindfolded and dip In a hand;
when he wh' dips In the empty one is expected
to remain unmarried, he who dips in tbe foul
one to ratrry to a widow, and he who dips in
tho clean one to marry a fem.ilo not hitherto
married. The whole of these rites are as
familiar io the Welch, Irish, and Northumbrian,
as to the Ayrshire peasantry. Many of them
are also praotlsed In Englandon St. John's Eve,
t. uo.,1 nf Jtinn.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84027008/1866-10-31/ed-1/?sp=4&q=HALLOWE%27EN+Hallowe%27en&st=text&r=-0.232,-0.073,1.465,1.465,0/</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85066387/1899-10-29/ed-1/?sp=23&q=Halloween+soul+souls&st=text&r=0.644,0.913,0.698,0.505,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>is
Halloween,
Halloween.
Look
Out
'lor Your
ior Yonr
Future
Spouse
THE very mention of Halloween calls
up visions of ghosts and witches
and all kinds of uncanny things. It
ls the one night ln the year when
J^ even the uninitiated, if they are
brave enough, may converse with
spooks and hobgoblins, and may also, if
they try hard enough, send the immate
rial part of their being prancing through
space on all kinds of errands. It Is safe
to surmise that the latter privilege is not
often taken advantage fot. It is hard
enough to keep soul and body together
without hunting up excuses to separate
them. But the grand object of all the
mystic rites peculiar to Halloween is to
find out who one's future spouse will be
—that Ing a very Important question
with those who have never had one.
The most infallible of the many Infalli
ble ways by which a girl may get a
glimpse of her future husband is to re
tire in silence. That alone is hard
enough, but that is not all. She must lie
there, speechless and in the dark, until
Just before the stroke of 12, when she
must rise and, standing before the mir
ror, it an apple while combing her hair.
If she doesn't see her "future" peeping
over her shoulder it's because she is des
tined to be an old maid, or she was too
scared to look.
Another way that does not .-equire so
much courage is to write the alphabet
on twenty-six little slips of paper, one
letter on each .-lip, and then urn them
face down in a basin of water. This done,
go to bed backward and in silence. Si
lence seems to be the main requirement
in ail these endeavors to coax one's af
finity to make himself, or herself, known.
Next morning some of the letters in the
basin will be found face up and the name
thus revealed will give the desired infor
mation.
A more comfortable custom is to wet
tho sleeve of a shirt and hang it before
the fire to dry. Then lie in bed and watch
lt until midnight, when the apparition of
the future husband or wife will' appear
and turn the sleeve.
If a girl has two lovers and cannot de
cide which one to choose, she may let
fate settle the matter in the following
manner. Eat an apple and then, naming
two Of the seeds, stick one on each cheeK
and bay:
Pippin, pippin, I stick thee there.
j stick thee there.
That which is true thou mayst declare.
The one that stays tho longest is the
must faithful lover, and therefore the
most desirable.
There la a custom ln Wales on Hal-
loween of building a huge bonfire, and
wher. the fire i--: almost out each member
of the party gathered about it throws in
a white stone, marked for future identi
fication, lv the morning a search is made
in ti.e embers and if one stone is missing
It Indicates that the person who threw
it In will not live to repeat the perform-
ance the next All Lints' eve.
Many of the customs mentioned by
Robert Hums are now- obsolete, but one
stii: in vogue is that of pulling kail or
cabbage stalk. A young couple are blind
folded and then, taking each other by the
hand, they go into the garden and each
pulls a stalk at random and they return
to th.c fireside, where their prizes cause a
great deal of merriment. As the stalk is
long or short, straight or crooked, so
shall the future husband or wife be. The
quantity of earth sticking to the root in
dicates the amount of wealth and the
taste of the pith the kind of temper "tie
must expect. Finally the stalks are
placed over the door, and the christian
names of the next two entering will be
the names of the future husband and
wife.
A custom that is quite common in this
count! aiso Is to ike three saucers and
fill c:.. with clean and another with dirty
water.' The third remains empty. The
part;. wishing to know his destiny is
blindfolded and led to tie hearth, where
the saucers have been arranged. If he
dips his finger in the clean water he will
marry a maid, but If in the? dirty water a
widow will knd him to the altar. The
empty dish signifies that a life of single
CARPET TACKS SAVED THE SHIP.
BUT CAPTAIN JOSHUA SLOCUM HAD A CLOSE CALL.
Captain Joshua^Slocum. in his solitary
voyage around tne world in the sloop
Spray, found a new and exciting use for
carpet tacks. He thus describes an en
counter with the Natives of Tierra del
Fuego:
Canoes manned by -savages from Fortes
que now came ln pu-teult. The wind fall
ing light, they gained on me rapidly till
coming within hall, when they ceased
paddling, and a bow-*ggcd savage stood
up and called to me, V Yammerschooner I
yammerschooner!" whati ls their begging
term. I said "No!" M»w. I was not for
letting them know that I was alone, and
6o I stepped Into the ctpln, and. passing
through the hold, came -put at the fore
scuttle, changing my Blkhes as I went
along. That made two kien. Then the
piece of bowsprit whioh >had sawed -oit
blessedness is in store for him.
Apples and nuts play a very important
part in the mystic rites of Halloween. One
way to find out If one's sweetheart is
true Is to place three nuts upon .lie bar
of the grate or on the hearth, naming the
nuts for the loved one. If a nut cracks
or jumps, look for another sweetheart
right away, for the one you have will
surely be unfaithful. If a nut burns that
Is a sign that your affection ls reciprocated.
but if two of the ruts burn together the
young lady making the trial may as well
begin preparing her trousseau at once,
for there will surely be an early wed-
ding.
Halloween parties must always be made
as weird and uncanny as possible, and
any one with original id< ie may give
them full scope on these occasions. One
very quaint affair that 1 recall may
serve as a model.
In the first place the Invitations were
most unique* Witches and goblins ran riot
over the card and the utmost secrecy in
regard to the approaching event was ex-
acted. Silence, too, was enjoined,, and
every one was veiled, and it certainly was
a very ghostly crowd that gathered
promptly at the appointed time in the
dimly lighted hallway. Suddenly the
sound of a bell -was heard, soft and- muf-
fled, as If it were high up In an old church
tower, and as it struck 9 the doors were
thrown open and the young people were
ushered into a veritable witches' den.
Death heads, made from pumpkins, with
a small lighted candle inside, grinned
from the mantel, the cornices and the
most unexpected places. Huge cobwebs,
In which were monster spiders, were
stretched across the corners and over the
mirrors. Immense bats with outspread
wings were apparently flying through the
air and great owls glared from every pos
sible resting place. In the fireplace, the
grate had been removed and in its stead
a large caldron was simmering over a pale
green blaze.
The hostess and her assistants were
witches, gowned in flowing black robes
and crownev with tall, pointed caps. In-
visible music of a weird character added
to the uncanniness of the scene. The
gentlemen were all in an adjacent room
and tbe hostess, taking a lady by the
hand, would advance with tier and knock
three times on the door with the small
broom she carried. In answer to her
knock a gentleman would appear, and
Offering the lady his arm retire to a dis
tant part of the room. When, in this
manner, the couples had all been paired
off the wltchefe wave,] their arms and
crooned in the most approved witch
manner and the screeching of the violins
outside became truly blood-curdling. Sud
denly, with a crash and a bang, the noise
ceased and the room was filled with light
When the light revealed the partners that
at Buenos Ayres, and which I had still
on board. I arranged forward on the look-
out, dressed as a seaman, attaching a line
by which I could pull It into motion.
That made three of us. and we did not
want to "yammerschooner;" but for all
that the savages came on faster than be-
fore. I saw that besides four at the pad-
dles In the canoe nearest to me. there
were others in the bottom, and that they
were shifting hands often. At eighty
yards I fired a shot across the bow of the
nearest' canoe, at which they all stopped,
but only for a moment. Seeing that they
persisted ln coming nearer, I fired the
second shot so close to the chap who
wanted to "}*ammerschooner" that he
changed hie mind quickly enough and bel-
lowed with fear. "Bueno yo via Isla,"
and sitting down in his canoe, he rubbed
his starboard cat-bead for some time. I
HERE ARE SOME ANCIENT CUSTOMS
THAT YOU WILL FIND MOST INTER-
ESTING TO EXPERIMENT WITH
fate had given each for the evening there
as a good deal of merriment. At a sig-
nal from the First Witch a couple went
Into the outer darkness to pull "kail"
stalks. Of course they had been prepared
beforehand and there was not a straight
one in the whole lot. After this ordeal
had been gone through by every one a
decrepit old hag. with a real, live owl
perched on her shoulder, entered the
room. On her arm hung a basket full
of nuts. Passing through the crowd she
gave each a nut and then.' standing by
the fireplace, she mumbled some unin-
telllgible Jargon and the room suddenly
became darkened again. Stooping over
the caldron she muttered an Incantation
and red fire Immediately blazed from Its
depths. She then tottered out of the
room, which again was illuminated as she
disappeared. The nuts, when cracked,
were found to contain a fortune, written,
on a slip of paper. For example, "You
will have many trials until the age of 30,
when good luck will come to you." The
nuts for the gentlemen were tied with
red ribbons and those for the ladies with
blue. .V
During the evening all sorts of games,
peculiar to Halloween, were added to the
programme. A stick was suspended hori-
zontally from the celling and on one end
was a short piece of lighted candle, while
an apple was stuck *on the other, and
the whole thing set whirling. A small
basket was then passed around in which
were a number of slips of paper. The
unfortunate who drew the paper with a
skull and cross-bones on It had to furnish
was thinking of a good port captain's ad
vice when I pulled the trigger, and I
must have aimed pretty straight; how
ever, a miss was as good as a mile for
Mr. "Black Pedro," as he it was, and no
other, a leader In several bloody massa
cres. He now directed the course of his
canoe for the island and the others fol
lowed him. I knew by his Spanish lingo
and by his full heard that he was the
villain I have named a renegade mongrel,
and the worst murderer in Tierra del
Fuego. The authorities had been In
search of' him for two years. The Fue
gans are not bearded. At
night, March 8, at anchor in the snug
cove at .the. Turn, every heart-beat
counted thanks. Hers I pondered on the
events of the last few days, and, strangely
enough, Instead of feeling rested from
sitting or lying down, I now began to
THE SUNDAY OALIi.
amusement for the rest by trying to get
a bite from the apple on the whirling
stick. Luckily for the girls, a man drew
the fatal slip, but before he had burned
his mustache off the First Witch took
pity on him and clapped her hands. Over
the door leading Into the dining-room a
dark, heavy portiere hung and at the slg
nal an apple rolled under the curtain and
went spinning over the floor. "It was fol
lowed by another and then ether, until
everybody had one. Knives were then
passed around and a merry half-hour was
spent In peeling the apples and throwing
the unbroken skin over the shoulder In
such a manner as to form the Initial of
the future husband or wife, In one of
the apples a needle was Imbedded in the
core, indicating that the finder would
enjoy a domestic or wedded life. Another
contained a pen. foretelling a literary
career, and in still another a tiny pencil
was buried, signifying a life devoted to
art. In a fourth a small piece of wood
was hidden on which the word "music"
had been written.
A few moments before midnight the
merry-makers were all taken out the
kitchen door and separated Into two
groups, the girls on one side and the
gentlemen on the other. At the first
stroke of twelve both groups started and
ran, one going one way and the other in
the opposite direction, all to meet at the
front door. The first couple to reach the
goal would be the first to marry— not each
other, necessarily— and the last to arrive
were doomed to a lonely existence
When the race was over, the breathless
feel .laded and worn; but a hot meal of
venison stew soon put me right, so that
I could sleep. As drowsiness came on I
first sprinkled the deck with the tacks
that my old friend Sambllch had given
me, and then I turned in.
Now, it Is well known that one cannot
istep on a tack without saying something
about it. A pretty good Christian will
whistle when he steps on the "commercial
end" of a carpet tack; a savage will howl
and claw the alr, and that was just what
happened that night about 12 o'clock
while I- was asleep in the cabin, where
the savages thought they "had me,"
sloop and all. They changed their minds,
however, when they stepped on deck, for
then they thought that I or somebody
else had them. I had no need of a dog;
they howled like a pack of hounds. I
had hardly uso for a gun. They jumped
pell-mell, some into their canoes and
some. Into the sea, to cool off, I suppose,
and there was a deal of free language
over It as they went. I fired the rascals
a salute of several guns t when I came on
deck, to -let them know that I was at
home, and then I turned in again, feeling
sure that- 1 should not be disturbed any
more by people who left In bo great a
hurry.
laughing crowd was summoned to supper,
and there another surprise awaited them.
The decorations in the dining-room were
red. even the tablecloth being of the same
brilliant hue.' Over the center of the
round table a huge owl. with outspread
wings, was suspended from the ceiling.
In its claws it held the ends of four long
red ribbons, the other ends of which were
held in the corners of the room, near the
celling, by bats, lizards and spiders. The
shade on the lamp was red crepe paper,
THE BOERS AS THEY REALLY ARE,
By MISS SANNIE KRUGER, NIECE OF OOM PAUL KRUGER.
Continued from Page Twenty-one.
the wedding customs. The suitor takes
the girl of his choice to some lachergoot
(confectionery). If she refuses the gift
that ends the courtship. If not he sits in
the midst of the coffee-drinking family
for an hour or more. Finally' he Is left
alone with the girl of his choice. T But the
wise tant according to custom puts a
limit on the length of his visit.- She marks
the wax candle with a needle, meaning
that i the visit must only last until the
candle burns to the mark.
I s could tell you of many more quaint
customs, but It was not for: that- I under
took this task. Rather _to convince you
that i a Boer girl ls not a semi-savage.
on which had been applied owls and bats
of some black material. The punch was
red, so was the frosting on the cake—
which, by the way, was crescent-shaped
and surmounted by a tiny doll, dressed all
in red. as a witch. The souvenirs were
also small witch-dolls for the ladies and
owls for the men, both of which, on In
vestigation, proved to be bonbon boxes.
In Ireland, the observance of Hallow
een assumes. In many respects, a religious
character. It is a custom In many dis
My English always surprises people Into
comment. True, I speak with less accent
than most Boer girls, having a natural
aptitude for languages and having trav
eled so much.
But the rising generation of Boers are
ail well educated. Both English and
Dutch are taught In the schools. Oom
Paul understands English as well as I do
myself. Many times when 'playing or
dancing for him I would forget and make
some remark in English. He would al
ways chide -me for it, saying. "I could
speak English as well as a rooinek (red
neck— Dutch for Englishman), but I never
forget I am a Boer."
Like all Boer girls I am an excellent
■hot and I fervently wish that I were
trlcts to bake what are called "soul
cakes" on that day, which are given to the
poor, who go from door to door begging.
The gift of a cake is always accompanied
with a request to pray for the souls of the
dead. The recipient of these "soul cakes"
is generally very profuse In his promises
to pray dnd calls down the blessings of
heaven on everything he or she can think
of. Another custom is to burn a lighted
candle in every wind in the house,
which gives a very picturesque effect
along the country roads.
There ls a custom among the poorer
classes In England, also, or begging on
Halloween, for what Is known there as
"dole bread." In several districts a fan-
tastic arrangement, called "Old Hob," ls
carried about from house to house, ac
companied by a crowd of young people,
singing doggerel begging rhymes. Old
Hob consists of a skeleton of a horse's
head, mounted on a broomstick, and with
a sheet wrapped about and concealing the
person who ls carrying It-
Shaw, in his history of the Province of
Moray, considers the festivities of Hal-
loween as a sort of harvest-home rejoic-
ing— a thanksgiving for the safe ingather
ing of the produce of the fields. What
ever may have been the original motive
for this "gathering together of the clans"
on the eve of All Saints, the young people
who make merry nowadays have only one
object In view— to discover, lf possible,
their affinity, to find that mysterious he
or she for whom we are all of us con
tinually seeking. Sometimes these "affin
ities" are a little careless and don't pair
off just right, so the boys and girls who
try their fate on this next Halloween
must not neglect the warnings and
prophecies which that night of mystery
will surely bring.</text>
      </result>
	  THIRD ONE
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83016810/1911-03-11/ed-1/?sp=1&q=Tower+Saved+Eiffel+Structure+Paris+France+French+Wireless&st=text&r=-0.245,-0.138,1.49,1.49,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>$2.40 PES lEABi
TOWER T0_BE SAVED
Huge Eiffel Structure Converted
into Wireless Station.
From its Top Messages Are Sent
5,000 MilesSoon to Be in
Touch With the United
States.
Paris.From the summit of the Eif
fel tower, 984 feet in the air, scien
tists communicate with ships nearly
5,000 miles out at sea. It is radio-tel
egraphy which makes it possible to
transmit to all vessels within that dis
tance a given time, say the hour of
noon, mathematically exact within the
tenth of a second, the speed of the
Hertzian waves being almost equal to
that of light.
Put in possession of the chronomet
ric time, the sailor determines the ex
act spot where the ship is at that
moment. He calculates the longitude
and the latitude with absolute correct
ness. The importance of this exacti
tude lies in the fact that it allows of
the correction of serious errors. The
best marine chronometers in use are
subject, after a few weeks or months
of navigation, to variations of two or
three seconds or more, and each error
of a second in time corresponds to
the exact position of the ship. A
metre is slightly more than a yard.
The method now used at the Eiffel
tower was first experimented with last
June. An increase in the power of
electric batteries and improvements
in other instruments enabled radio
telegraphic signals to be sent and re
ceived.
Certain wireless telegraph stations
In the United States, which have water
power at their disposal and are thus
able to produce larger quantities of
electric energy, had already sent elec
tric waves as far as Europe, where
they were registered by sensitive ap
paratus.
In transmitting the hour to ships at
sea the co-operation of the Paris ob
servatory is, of course, required. In
the silent observatory are the two
principal clocks regulated to the hun
dredth of a second, which were order
ed by Baillard, the director of the ob
servatory, from Leroy, the chronome
ter maker of the French navy. These
two clocks twice every dayat 11
The Eiffel Tower.
o'clock in the morning and at midnight
will signal the time to the four
points of the compass by means of an
electrical apparatus on the summit of
the Eiffel tower.
Exactly at 10:59 o'clock in the morn
ing and at 11:59 at night the astrono
mer on duty, with one eye on the tel
escope, watches the hand of the clock
and sends th fir,st electric signals to
the wireless telegraph station near the
tower. From there, immediately trans
mitted by radio-telegraphy, they travel
immense distances, warning naviga
tors and other wireless stations.
Then, exactly at the hour, and twice
again at intervals of two minutes, the
clockwork automatically establishes a
contact, by means of which an elec
tric manipulator in the Eiffel tower
sets up a discharge of Hertzian waves.
These waves, spreading through space,
reach the limits of the immense cir
cle of which the tower is the center,
influencing all the receivers 4n this
area and conveying to all, as it were,
the beat of a heart which is felt in the
pulsations of the remotest arteries.
In the wireless telegraphy station,
100 yards away in the Champs-de
Mars, the military authorities hold
sway. The station keeps Paris in
touch with the frontier, and even with
remote posts in Afrfca. It was the
great services rendered by wireless
telegraphy during the French expedi
tion to Morocco which led to the pro
vision of modern quarters to the wire
less telegraph corps in Paris.
These quarters are underground and
it is there that the engineer officers
and sergeants carry on. their experi
ments daily. On one door may be
read the impressive words "Danger to
life." The door leads to the first bat
tery, which has been in operation sev
eral years and gives upwards of 50,-
000 volts and a range of 2,500 kilome
tres.
And so the permanency of the Eiffel
tower is assured. Several times moves
have threatened to rid the city of a
monument which many regard as un
asthetic and cumbrous. As to wheth.
er the tower really is inartistic or not
opinions differ. But if it is considera
tions of utility will override considera
tions of art</text>
   </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn90059523/1903-10-25/ed-1/?sp=24&q=Eiffel+Tower+Doomed+Rocks+Wind+Paris+France+French+Gustav&st=text&r=0.369,0.307,0.345,0.25,0/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>THE Eiffel Tower must come down.
The authorities of Paris have so decreed.
This iron spire, the tallest structure in the
world, and the engineering feat of the last cen
tury, \.i regarded as a dangerous plaything.
When a high wind blows from the south the great
ribbed structure trembles like a frightened horse.
But let a stiff breeze come bowling down from the
north and the tower vibrates until the china rattles in
the cafes, and to those in the observatory at the apex the
sensation is that of a ship fossed by heavy seas.
The fact that the tower is more'sensitive to a wind
from the north than from the south is regarded as proof
of the structural weakness, and from this springs the
theory of danger of collapse.
It is almost twenty years since Gustav Eiffel began
the work of building his sky-scraper. The mark of com
pletion was set for 1889, Exposition year, and on March 31
of that year the tower was thrown open to the public. It
wa« the leading attraction of the big show, and it has
not since ceased to attract attention and coin.
The cost of building the structure was more than
$1,000,000. Of that amount the French government appro
priated $29L',000. Eiffel supplied the remainder, trusting
for his reimbursement to the receipts from admission fees
and other sources.
In this he was not uisappolnted, as the profits of the
first year were almost sufficient to make him whole.
The lease held by Eiffel will expire in next March, and
then, if the present plans of the city fathers are realized,
the work of razing the unique structure will be started.
The plan is to sell the tower to the highest bidder, the
purchaser to be given a certain time in which to remove
what Paris regards as almost a public menace.
Except as a curio and an Investment for its builder,
the tower has been somewhat of a failure.
Much was expected in the scientific world from the
metaphorical observatory, with its physical and biological
laboratories, all 954 feet above ground. But little has
come of this, the enterprise having taken on a rather
commercial aspect.
The Eiffel Tower will ever be considered a colossa*
feat of engineering.
Tlhese Stria! Ihxean F®ds ire nsudhes hM
.'v_V- Ir 'mJf.A?j -i?'^^t Vk^T*i^*v*
THE beanstalk up which Jack, the Giant Killer,
climbed to fame has been sung and pictured until
even little Emma and Annie and Jeannette and
Joe, sprawled there on the nursery floor, can tell
of its sturdy trunk, of its stout, ladder-like branches, of
Its leathery leaves, which the eager hands of their hero.
Jack, could not crush, though he clutched them ever so
tightly.
They can tell you that this fabled beanstalk was so
tall that "Oo! you jest couldn't see the top uv it, so you
couldn't."
DRINKERS IN TWO CLASSES
==Mlsery and L,Mxtuiry==
BOTH CLAIM THEIR VICTIMS OF LIQUOR
LONDON, August 17.
WOMEN who drink are classified by the experts
into two sections—misery drinkers and luxury
drinkers.
Speaking broadly, the misery drinkers come
from the very poor, the luxury drinkers from the rich.
But whatever the cause which first sends them to drink
the ultimate results are the same—a falling birth-rate, a
rising death-rate among infants and the physical degen
eration of the race.
Dr. Claye Shaw, a recognized authority, made it clear,
in discussing the matter recently, that the evil is not con
fined to the lowest order of society.
"My experience," he said, "is that among women of
fashion, women who have nothing to do but to amusa
themselves, there l a a growing tendency to take alco
holic stimulants, and the ill effects of that, both upon the
•women themselves and upon their children, are often very
■erlous
"There is a great deal of private drinking. I know
towns where it is a common thing for young girls to go to
a private counter in a confectioners shop and take a
glass or two of champagne or a glass or two of port.
"There are confectioners' shops in London where wo
men of position do the same thing. And at home there is
•adly too much nipping of spirits in private. It does not
etop at that. Many women drink cologne, many use mor
phia.
"Jt is the result of high living, and an emotional,
unnatural, excited way of life. All this leads to personal
demoralization and the weakening of character. Some
times it is a step towards the divorce court.
"The trouble is that the women have nothing to do
nothing to occupy their minds. The happiest marriages
The lower section consists of four columns resting
upon masonry 85 feet square and 30 feet high. These
curve toward each other, so that they unite as a slnglo
column 620 feet above the ground.
PARIS, October 10.
There are platforms at the 189, 380 and 906 feet levels,
reached by elevators as well as by Btairs. Beyond the
third platform a spiral staircase, which is not open to the
public, ascends to the top of the tower.
On the first platform, which has a floor space of 38,000
Bquare feet, or nearly an acre, there were four restau
rants at the time of the Exposition, and refreshments are
Btill served there.
The view from the top of the tower extends eight y
flve miles on a clear day. At night a searchlight gleams
from the eminence.
Seven thousand tens of iron were used in building the
Eiffel Tower.
Gustav Eiffel made a long leap over precedent when
he planned and built the spiral skeleton of Iron which
made him rich and famous.
The ambition of the Egyptians to pierce the sky with
pyramids carried them less than half as high as this
French engineer went on a comparatively fragile founda
tion.
The pyramid of Cheops 13 only 486 feet high; that of
Cephrenes 456 feet.
The best that Rome can do, with all her boasted
achievements in lofty architecture, is to point to the dome
of St. Peter's—a paltry 448 feet above ground.
London steps into third place in these Old World ver
tical achievements with her St. Pauls dome—36s feet up.
Campanile, the famous leaning tower at Pisa, did not
win fame because of the height of its arcaded colonnades
bo much as because of its obliquity, and yet when we are
told that this tower is thirteen feet out of plumb we
learn in the same breath that it is 179 feet high!
Stepping over to the New World to complete the table
of comparisons more ambitious figures are encountered,
and yet our best achievements are as pigmies in the
shadow of the tower that Eiffel built.
The Washington Monument ranks first, with its 555
feet of gleaming granite.
Second in order" is the quaint, broad-brimmed hat of
William Perm surmounting the heroic statue on the tower
of Philadelphia City Hall. This measurement is 547 feet.
And the sweet little enthusiasts are to be believed.
Odd as It may seem, however, the wonderful mind that
evolved Jack's beanstalk, with a giant castle the first way
station, did not compass the idea that it must have borne
wonderful fruit.
Its pods were surely longer than a man's body, and
each bean larger than a cocoanut. No better weapons
could be imagined for the giant, whose fierce, puffy face
is pictured peering over the ledge of his high domain,
than a handful of these big beans, weli dried, hurled
upon the head of daring interlopers like Jack.
are to be found among the middle classes—the backbone
of the race.
"In the lower orders a great deal of crime is, beyond
doubt, due to the drunkenness of parents. The Inhabitants
of Broadmoor, taken as a class, are not big, violent mani- I
acs, but feeble, degenerate imbeciles, damned before they
ware born by the habits of their parents.
"In the Bicetre Hospital at Paris 41 per cent, of the
imbeciles are the children of drunken parents.
"It has been proved by a French investigator that
alcohol consumed by the mother passes, as alcohol, into
the circulation of the unborn child. The infant is soaked
with gin or rum before it is born, and may develop all
kinds of malformations, physical and moral.
"A woman receives no alcohol when in jail, and Dr.
Sullivan has noticed that when a child is born in prison
that child 1b usually the best of the family.
"The drunken habits of parents' may or may not be
transmitted to the children. When drunkenness becomes
hereditary the family is doomed—erratic conduct in the
second generation, epilepsy in the third, Imbecility and
extinction in the fourth."
It is admitted by the scientists that a drunken father 1
has not nearly so bad a physical effect upon his offspring
as has a drunken mother.
In the north country towns the infantile death-rate is
terrible. Dr. Greenwood, of Blackburn, recently informed
the Town Council that 226 out of 1000 babies' born in the
borough did not live to be a year old. i
More than half the deaths in Darlaston are those of
children who have not reached the age of five. In Lei-
cester, out of an average of 60 deaths each week, 20 are
those of children. In Blrkenhead 178 out of eery 1000
children born die before they are a year old.
The offsprings of drink are insanity, pauper sm epl
lepsy and feeble-mindedness. In London there are 2000 epi
leptics and about 100,000 paupers, and all over the country
there are 110,000 certified lunatic*.
TfflE ST. P^ULGLOBE, SU2s TJ)AY, OCTOBER 25, 1903.
Within a stone's throw are-two business blocks that
tower higher—but these are, nevertheless, not towers.
Tho Trinity Church spire 4n New York has caused
the crooking of many a neck, yet its height Is only 284 feet.
The Bunker Hill Monument stands 221 feet above the
historic sod that undulates about Its base.
It may be said, in justification of all of these beacons
of history and architecture, that they stand for bo much
more than mere height that they possess that In sufficient
degree.
The Eiffel Tower possesses the sole distinction of altl
tude. Barren of other claims upon the public attention,
the need of outstripping—virtually doubling—the elevation
of any other tall structure is apparent.
Scattered over.lreland and Scotland, or,Jiere %nd there
on the Islands of Corsica and Sardinia, are to be found
the ruins of some of the towers of prehistoric times.
These, like those of our cathedrals .and public build
ings of to-day, were built for purposes of utility.
The old round towers ot Ireland, as well tta the
"brochsT of Scotland, were used as places of refuge or
defense in time of war, as wateff towers and as resort for
the recluse.
The architecture was at first plain and severe, while
In later years appeared parapets and pinnacles richly
canopied.
These towers were never mbfe than 132 feet high, with
the average perhaps 80 feet.
In remote times the Moslems' built towers of stone
that they used as minarets. The finest of these belong
to the thirteenth, century, notably the Mlnan of Kootub,
at Old Delhi, which was the wjonder of ail the tribes that
gathered about it.' This towei^ was 250 feet high, built of
massive blocks of limestone and marble.
Not since the days of Babel, if, indeed, before, has the
building of a tower for the mere pride of building it been
essayed. Confusion of tongues Svas the result then.
Coming down to the age «f a*»ial playthings, modern
ingenuity seems to have spelled for itself a lesson—one
less severe than that of Babel, bat, nevertheless, a lesson.
Having ventured past the point of practicability and
safety, the monument erected'by Gustav Eiffel to tho
genius and daring of man faHa; before the force of the
elements, while the dust of ages-icontlnues to settle upon
the sloping sides of the pyramids.</text>
      </result>
      <results>
      <result>
	<id>/</id>
	<rel></rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <id></id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>/</id>
	<rel></rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>/</id>
	<rel></rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <id></id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>/</id>
	<rel></rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>/</id>
	<rel></rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
</topics>
